Hello and welcome back to the second week off our class on Autonomous Navigation for Flying Robots.
My name is Daniel Cremers, and I will start of this week's class where
we learn about 2D and 3D geometry, that we need to model the sensors of our quadrotor.
Before we get into modeling the geometry, I will give you a brief recap of linear algebra,
so that we're all on the same page and speak the same language. Most of this should already
be familiar to you, if it is not, than I strongly recommend that you first attend a class on
linear algebra before continuing here. The entities that we'll be working with in this
class are scalars vectors and matrices. Scalars are just real numbers that we denote by a
lower case letters typeset in italics. Vectors are sets of numbers they are in R^n that we
denote by lower case letters typeset in bold. And matrices are arrays of m by n numbers
that we denote in upper case letters typeset in bold.
When we talk about vectors we typically mean column vectors, which just means that you stack
the n numbers. There are many ways you can see and interpret vectors.
The most intuitive way is to think of a vector as a point in a n dimensional space. So for example, a 3D
vector simply denotes a point in 3D with the three components are its coordinates.
Once we have vectors we can define different operations on these vectors. We can define
scalar multiplication, which simply means you multiply the vector x by a scalar s and
what you obtain is another vector that has the same direction as x, but it is rescaled
by the number little s. With two vectors x and y we can define addition
and subtraction of vectors. Furthermore, for a vector x we can define the length of that
vector or the norm. There is actually different ways to measure the length, the one that we
use in this class is the most common one and that is the so called L2 norm or Euclidian
norm of this vector. And it simply corresponds to the square root of the sum of squared components.
Furthermore, we can define normalized vectors, which is here for a vector x for example the
normalized version x hat is obtained by dividing that vector by its length. What we obtain
than is a unit vector, so a vector of length one that has the same direction as x.
For two vectors we can define a dot product or scalar product denoted by this little dot here.
It's a scalar number associated with these two vectors, which is actually maximal
if the two vectors are in parallel, and then just corresponds to the product of their length.
And in general it denotes the projection of the vector x on to the vector y or vice versa.
And in the case that the two vectors are orthogonal the dot product is 0.
Furthermore, we can define for the vectors in R^3 a so called cross product, that is another
vector assigned to the two vectors x and y, which is orthogonal to the plane spanned by
x and y. And you can remember which direction it is pointing by the so called right hand rule.
And that rule says that if the first vector x
points in direction of your thumb and the second points into direction of your index
finger, then the cross product is a vector pointing in direction of the middle finger.
Here is a more formal definition of the cross product, which allows you to actually compute
the cross product for two vectors x and y. It's given by this expression on the right
hand side, which contains the various components x_i and y_i of two vectors x and y.
In addition, there is a matrix notation for the cross product, where we introduce this
skew- or anti-symmetric matrix, that contains the three elements of x, and then we can reproduce
the cross product of x and y by just multiplying the vector y with this matrix.
This turns out to be useful because it allows you to replace the cross product by a simple
matrix vector product.
For matrices we will use the following convention, an n by m matrix is an array of numbers, where
n denotes the number of rows and m the number of columns.
It has a lot of components, x_ij where the first index i refers to the row and second
index j refers to the column.
For matrices there is actually different types of matrices that we can distinguish.
Square matrices are matrices where the number of rows and columns is equal, in contrast
to the more general case of rectangular matrices. Than we have diagonal matrices, these are
matrices where only the diagonal elements are non-zero. In addition, we have upper and
lower diagonal matrices, which are matrices where the non-zero elements are all above or below the diagonal.
Furthermore, we have symmetric matrices, these are matrices where the transpose is equal
to the matrix itself. The transpose is obtained by mirroring along the diagonal, and so that
leaves the matrix unchanged for symmetric matrices.
In contrast to so called skew-symmetric or anti-symmetric matrices, where transposing
the matrix gives you the negative of that matrix.
Then, we have positive definite or positive semi-definite matrices. A positive definite
matrix is a matrix X such that for any vector a the quadratic form a transpose X a is always positive.
And positive semi-definite if it is always non-negative.
We have orthogonal matrices, these are matrices where the transpose is equal to the inverse.
We will see later in class that orthogonal matrices include rotation matrices but they
can also be for example mirroring.
There are many operations we define on matrices. For example, we can simply define a matrix-vector
multiplication where we multiply the vector x by the matrix M. Furthermore, we can define
matrix-matrix multiplications M_1 times M_2, provided of course that the dimensions of
the matrices are consistent. We'll see for example, that this allows to
model concatenations of rotations. Then we can define the inverse of a matrix
M^(-1). That assumes first of all that the matrix is a square matrix, and secondly that
the matrix is actually invertible. Invertible matrices can be identified by having a
non-zero determinant and by a full rank, equivalent. The transpose of a matrix, as I mentioned, is
obtained by simply mirroring along the diagonal.
Furthermore, there exist various decompositions of matrices. In this class we will be using
in particular the singular value decomposition and the eigendecomposition.
The singular value decomposition holds for any rectangular matrix. It tells you that
the matrix M can be decomposed into a product of matrices U Sigma V*, where U and V denote
orthogonal transformations, and Sigma is a diagonal matrix containing the singular values.
For square matrices we can define an eigendecomposition, where again M is decomposed as
Q Lambda Q inverse. Q being an orthogonal matrix and Lambda being a diagonal matrix, that contains
the eigenvalues little Lambda. There is the eigenvalue equation, which essentially
tells us that a vector v is an eigenvector to an eigenvalue Lambda if multiplying the
vector v with the matrix A does nothing but rescale the vector with Lambda.
In particular these decompositions the singular- and eigenvalue decomposition tell us a little
bit about how a matrix acts on vectors.
What have we learned in this class: we have learned a little bit recap on linear algebra,
we learned the notation that we will be using in this course, we learned about scalars,
vectors and matrices, and some of the most important operations on these.
As I mentioned, if this was not familiar to you, please do go and visit a class on linear
algebra to get back up on track.
In the next class we will then see how these notations and terms can be used to model 2D
and 3D geometry that we need to model this sensors of our quadrotor.