Hello and welcome everybody to lecture video 7.1.
In this video we will look at 2D motion estimation in camera images and this will then form the
basis for visual odometry that we will then introduce in the next video.
So just as a quick recap, remember again how a camera works. We have 3D objects in space
and those objects are imaged by a camera, by a projective camera.
And we modeled this using a pinhole camera model in week three.
The idea is that we have a point in 3D and this point gets projected onto an image plane
and this relationship between this 3D and the 2D point on the image plane is given by
the camera intrinsic matrix K. And then at this point on the image plane
we have a light sensitive cell that measures the intensity and this intensity is then being
read out and this gives us our digital image.
So from the mathematical side this means that we can define an image now as a function that
maps this image plane to intensity values. Of course, if we have a color camera then this
image function would map to a 3-dimensional vector where the components then correspond
to the red, green, and blue intensity. Realistically of course this image function
is only define on a rectangle because it's only there where you have your sensor.
And then, this dimension is defined by the width and the height of your image.
When we are talking about digital images then of course this image function is only sampled
at discrete locations, so if we want for example evaluate this image function at a location
somewhere in between then we will have to interpolate between these sampled values.
And we need to take this into account when we need to compute the derivatives and so
on that this is done in a proper way.
This also means that digital images of course can be represented as a matrix. For example
enumerated from left to right and top to bottom as we know it.
So back now to our original problem of estimating the 2D motion of an image. The problem there
is that we assume that we are given two camera images, probably to consecutive images f_0
and f_1. And we assume that the camera has moved a little bit in between and so our goal
now is to estimate the camera motion u in between these two images. And for the moment
we assume that the camera only moves in the xy-plane, so there is no rotation and it's
a pure motion in the image plane. And we will then later see how this extends to 3D.
But this means at the moment that we can represent this camera motion by a 2-dimensional vector
u that just describes the translation along x-axis and y-axis.
And now, the general idea is as follows, we define an error metric that describes how
well the two images match, given a particular motion vector. And then, the second step is
that we need to find the optimal motion vector that yields the lowest error of this error function E.
And there are different choices here for the error metric. The most common one is called
the sum of squared differences abbreviated as SSD and there the idea is that we directly
look at the differences in the intensities. So we're summing over all pixels but for every
pixel we take the difference between the intensity from the first image f_0, and then, from the
intensity in the second image f_1 at this pixel plus this motion vector u.
And this difference is then squared and summed up and this is why it's called the sum of
squared differences.
And just as a shorthand because we will need this later we call this difference term here
the residual error. And by introducing this equation for SSD this becomes much shorter
because it is just a sum over the squared residual errors.
And now of course, one problem with SSD is that, especially when we're talking about
digital images that our images have only finite size.
And this might mean as soon as we run out of the image or if we move one image with respect
to the other one, then the overlap gets smaller and smaller because this happens. The error
by itself gets smaller because you can't compute any error of pixels that do not overlap.
So this means that the standard SSD has a bias towards smaller overlaps, so it prefers
actually to shift apart both images to have zero overlap and thus zero error.
This means that the standard SSD is not enough generally, but a very simple solution is then just to
divide this SSD error by the overlap area, so this is normalized out. And this is then
called the root mean square error where we just take this error divide it by the number
of pixels and take the square root. A different way for computing this error term
is to use a cross correlation instead of minimizing the differences we seek for maximizing the
products of both images. The intuition behind that is that we are trying
to align both images, and so when they are align well we would assume that the correlate
very well. And this means then that the product between the two images is actually maximal.
So you can think of this as if you have somewhere bright spots in your image, say a white line,
then when this white line coincides with the line from the second image, then these
correlating pixels will yield a very large value in this cost term, and then, indicate a good correspondence.
One problem with normal cross correlation is that the absolute value of this error function
depends strongly on the content of your image. So if you have white or very bright images
then this cross correlation will yield a very large number. And if you're looking at a very
dark scene then automatically then this term will be compared relatively low.
And therefore, it's desirable to normalize that somehow, then one forward extension is
the so called normalized cross correlation where you subtract the mean value of your
images from both input images and you divide by the variance of both images.
And this automatically gives you the score between -1 and 1, and then, it's easier to
interpret how good your match actually is between the two.
And one huge advantage in contrast to the SSD is that the normalized cross correlation
is much less sensitive to illumination changes and the illumination changes of course can
happen quite frequently if your brightness in the room changes or the scene you are looking
at changes. Then the camera might decide to increase the gain or reduce or increase the
shutter time, and then, SSD will not be able to match the images very well.
So back to our algorithm, so we have now defined an error metric E that we can use to evaluate
how good a particular match is. And now we need to find a motion vector that
actually minimize this error function.
And there are different ways of doing this, one option of course is to do a full search
in the neighborhood. So if you can make assumptions on how far your image probably has shifted
then you can do a brute force search for the minimum. This is actually sometimes done because
this guarantees that you are actually finding the right minimum.
But in most cases this is not necessary and people just run a gradient descent like approach
our a Gauss-Newton method and there are even ways when to make sure that even if you have
larger motions to still find the right minimum using a hierarchical decomposition.
So the most common type actually is to run a gradient based minimization method call
Gauss-Newton. This was introduced by Lucas and Kanade in
1981 and this is probably the most famous and most popular method for tracking motion
in 2D images and it's more over all extremely efficient.
So the general idea behind Gauss-Newton minimization is that we linearize the residuals or the
error function with respect to the camera motion that we have.
This then yields us a quadratic error function that we can derive and from which we can set
the derivative to zero. And then, this gives us the normal equations
that we can solve with inverting this matrix.
So now from a mathematical side, we start out again with this SSD error function, remember
that we just take the difference between the two images. We shift the second image by this
vector u take the difference, then compute the square of that and then sum over all pixels x.
And this term we now want to linearize in
u, so we add a small increment to our current estimate of u, so we evaluate it at u plus
delta u, and then, we make an approximation with respect to this delta u.
So this Taylor expansion then looks as follows: the insight here is that this delta u only
appears in this term f_1, f_0 is not shifted only f_1 is shifted by this delta u and so we can
approximate this nonlinear function by evaluation f_1 at x_i plus u, at the original point plus
the Jacobian evaluated at x_i plus u times our increment delta u.
And this Jacobian is nothing else as the derivative or the gradient of the image evaluate at this
particular location x_i plus u. And the gradient is just defined as the partial derivative
of this image f_1 with respect to x and the partial derivative of this image with respect to y.
Now of course you want to minimize this approximated error function. And as you know, at the minimum
of the function the derivative has to be zero so for finding the minimum we can actually
now derive this error function and set its derivative then to zero.
And this is not very complicated so if you want to try this out by yourself just go ahead
and if you summarize the terms accordingly, then you end up with this very linear form
here shown in the middle.
We obtain this 2A times delta u plus 2b has to be zero. And then this individual terms
are composed by these Jacobians. And as you remember from this last slide this Jacobian
is nothing else then the image gradient actually so these matrix A and the vector b can directly
be directly computed from the image gradients where this f_x here stands for the second image
derived with respect to x, f_y stands for the partial derivative with respect to y,
and this f_t here is actually just the difference between the two images, some people also call
that the temporal derivative if your looking at consecutive images.
But now that we have such a simple linear system that we need to solve, we can directly
invert this matrix A or solve it directly using the Gauss elimination method.
And now the cool thing is that all of the computations that we have to do to find a
minimum are extremely efficient because we just need to evaluate the image gradients
and sum over them to build this matrix A and b, and then we have to solve a 2 by 2 linear
equation and that virtually costs no time.
So one strong assumption of course that we have here is that we assume that the image
gradient is actually meaningful. And this of course only is meaningful or this Taylor
approximation is only valid as long as we not moving away too far from our linearization
point, and then, of course this depends a little bit on our image how well this linear
approximation actually holds. But it's clear that the further we actually
move away or the further our image patch is shifted the more difficult it will be for such
a method to find the right minimum.
And now, one very easy and often used method for enlarging this convergence radius is to
perform a so called hierarchical motion estimation where you are not directly estimating the
motion on the image itself, but you scale down or you down sample your image in a pyramid
where every layer of the pyramid halves the resolution.
So instead of having 640 by 480 you would have at the next layer a resolution of 320
by 240, and then, 160 by 120 and so on. And at these higher levels even a larger motion
even on the original image appears just as a motion of 1 or 2 pixels. And then our linearization
holds again and then we can run this Taylor approximation.
And now, the idea of this hierarchical motion estimation is that we estimate the motion first
on a very coarse level maybe 3 or 4 levels higher than our original image. And then,
when we determine the motion there we use that as the initial initialization for the
Taylor approximation for the next finer level. And in this way you can improve the convergence
a lot.
Another interesting thing to note here is that we can also evaluate the quality of our
estimate by looking at this matrix A. This looks as follows, imagine that our observed
image is of course noisy. So it is a noisy observation of our true image or true pixel
x_i and every pixel adds then a small error term that is again normally distributed according
to a certain variance. And then it can be shown that this noise in
the image actually results in an uncertainty of the motion estimate that has a covariance
of this sigma squared times A^(-1). So by evaluating this matrix A or the covariance
of our motion estimate is inversely related to this matrix A times the variance of our
image noise sigma square.
Now this method that you've just seen is actually widely used, everybody of you whenever you
touch an optical mouse runs this algorithm directly on a chip, it can of course be implemented
easily on a CPU but it can also be implemented in hardware and then it becomes very energy
efficient and so on.
So a typical mouse sensor actually runs at very high image rates, this has the advantage
that even if you seem to move the mouse very fast the motion between two consecutive images
is of course extremely small. And then this Taylor approximation holds very well.
And gamer mice for example run at even higher frame rates, then you get an even better resolution
or motion estimate. And actually a computer mouse just has a very
low resolution camera you don't need to much here, some even go down to 16 by 16 some have
a little bit more. But they are very cheap to produce and as I said, everything is already
build into the chip then you directly get the x and y velocity that you can send over
PS2 or USB to your computer.
So this was now a method to align whole images but sometimes you're just interested in the
motion of the individual patches within an image, and then, of course the question is which patches or
which points in the image can be actually tracked or which patches should we actually
track. And it's clear that some patches are much easier to track then others. Obviously
if you have a lot of texture it's easier to track than if you don't have texture at all.
And so the question is how can we automatically recognize good patches that are easy to track?
And just to visualize the different possibilities that we have. If we are looking at a corner
point or at a point that has a strong texture in both directions in x and y direction, then
our patch is actually easy to track because it is constrained in all directions. However,
if we happen to look at a patch that is looking at an edge in the image, then it will be constrained
very well in y direction, but the patch can move arbitrarily in x direction just because
there is no information in the image that tells us where it exactly was. And the other
extreme is that we are looking at a patch within a unicolor region, and then, of course
it is not possible at all to track it because all its surroundings will exactly look the same.
And just an example how this looks for real this is now a real image taken by a camera.
And we again have here this different types of things. For example, if you look at this
green, the first, patch at the roof of the house. Then we're getting this problem of
an edge, so the energy here depicted on the right, we actually see a valley, so it's not
really clear which minimum we should pick if we track this patch. Then the next patch
is the red one where we don't have any texture. Here you can see in the surface plot of the
energy function it doesn't have a very clear minimum. Of course there always is by definition
a minimum, but it's not very easy to find and not very unique.
And then, actually a good patch is here shown in blue on the bottom right. And this is a
situation where we have lots of texture and where our energy function shows a clear minimum.
And these are actually the patches that we are interested in because those patches are
easier to track.
And now, as we said before we can recognize the quality of our motion estimate from this
matrix A, which is also called the Hessian. And so if this matrix A is large then our
covariance of our estimate is small which means that we are very well localized and
this big and small can also be read off from the eigenvalues from the matrix. So if
you compute the eigenvalues lambda_1 and lambda_2 then if these two eigenvalues are very large
then we are looking at a corner. If only one of them e.g. if the first one is large and the second one is small then
we are looking at an edge. When we are constrained in one direction but not in constrained in
the other direction. And both of them are actually small then that means that we have a very high
uncertainty in both directions so this is not a good choice for an interest point or
a key point.
So there have been very corner detectors proposed, so the oldest or most famous one is the Harris
detector. It actually does not need eigenvalues because those were complicated to compute
in that time so there is a simple approximation where you just have to compute the determinant
of this matrix A and the trace of this matrix A. Essentially it is still looking of the product
of both eigenvalues and compares that to the squared sum.
Later when computers got faster the Shi-Tomasi or Kanade-Lucas corner detector was proposed
that just says that if the minimum of the two eigenvalues is larger than a certain constant
then we consider this to be a suitable corner.
There are other detectors as well like the Förstner detector that can localize a corner
even with sub-pixel accuracy this certainly helps if you need highly accurate estimates of points
in your image or patches in your image. There are also FAST corners that became very
popular over the past years, where you apply a machine learning technique to actually reduce
the number of pixels that you have to read out. And this means that the FAST corner detector
is extremely fast and even much faster than this Harris detector. Another popular one
is the so called Difference of Gaussians that is used in the SIFT feature detector which
is even scale invariant. So the Harris detector for example recognizes a corner only at a particular
scale. If you would zoom in into a corner then this corner might, given the right zoom,
appear as a straight line the Harris detector wouldn't recognize it anymore and
the idea of Difference of Gaussians is that you again build this image pyramid and that
you search for corners at all levels of the pyramid and this means that you are invariant
or at least somewhat invariant to a scale change.
Now, we finally come to the Kanade-Lucas-Tomasi tracker one of the most popular and most famous
trackers in the world for 2D motion estimation. The algorithm is as follows, we first find
the corners in the image typically these Shi-Tomasi corners and we do that in the first frame
and then initialize our trackers. So every corner gets a track and then we track
this corner from frame to frame using this Taylor approximation from before and this
is Gauss-Newton method. And then, if it happens that this matrix A or that the eigenvalues
if you're not localized anymore or if the discrepancy gets to large then we delete the
track. If we lost too many tracks then we can initialize additional tracks when necessary.
This is a costly operation because for that you have to scan the whole image for corners.
So we don't want to do that too often, only if the number of tracks gets too low. And
then, you repeatedly run the steps 2 to 4.
The good news here is that the KLT tracker is extremely efficient so it runs in real-time
at CPU so there are many open source implementations of it in OpenCV but there is also a tutorial
for Matlab for example and essentially for all languages that you can think off.
The KLT tracker only tracks this sparse points in the image but it is also possible with
other methods to compute a dense optical flow where you essentially for every pixel in the
image find this motion vector u and this is typically a little bit more complicated for
that you need more processing power or which at least at the moment requires a GPU.
So now to finally demo how this looks like for real this now just a camera video somebody
took and then ran a KLT implementation on it. As you can see these red points here are the
Shi-Tomasi corners. You can see small numbers if you look carefully those are the track
numbers that are be tracked. And when the camera moves the algorithm tries to track
them using this approach that we have shown. And of course it can happen that this tracks
get lost simply because either they fall out of the image or the matching doesn't work
for some reason, we have an over exposure or blur in the image, and then, the tracks
might get deleted.
So to summarize the video of today, we've looked at 2D motion estimation, we have introduced
different cost functions that are typically used, we've shown that this is the
technique which is actually used in computer mice. And computer mice look at aligning whole
image to the previous image. If you are only interested in small patches then it makes
sense to pick good patches for that we looked at corner detectors. And then, we applied
that in the KLT tracker to track different regions in the image.
And this now will be used, this technique, we will use in the next video to estimate
visual odometry for a quadrotor that has a downwards looking camera.