Hello and welcome everybody to lecture video 6.2 on Kalman Filtering.
In this video we will introduce the basic linear Kalman Filter, which is a very efficient
implementation of the Bayes Filter that we looked at in the previous videos.
So as you remember from the previous video we introduced there the Histogram Filter to
estimate the position of a robot in 2D. And the Histogram Filter did that by representing
the state space by using a grid. And every cell in this grid then stores the probability
that the robot is located in this particular cell.
Although this is very easy to understand and very easy to implement it has several disadvantages,
and the most striking disadvantage is that it is very inefficient.
And the reason for that is that we need to discretize the state space of course, and
even in a 2 dimensional world we already need quite many cells to represent the state space.
So even in 2D with a reasonable resolution you can end up quickly with maybe a grid of
100 by 100 or 1000 by 1000. And that needs lots of memory of course but also on the other
hand this needs lots of computational power to update the whole grid.
While this is still feasible for 2D, and actually occasional used by scientists and robotists,
it scales very poorly with higher dimensions.
So imagine that you need to estimate 3 degrees of freedom, then the number of cells already
grows cubically. And if we would like to estimate a state of
a 6 DOF pose in 3D then this grows extremely quickly.
And the other problem is, if you want to have a reasonable resolution, say for example you want to know
the position of the quadrotor up to a centimeter or so, then you need even for a few meters
a hundreds and thousands of cells along every dimension.
So the question is: isn't there a way to represent this state more efficiently?
And this is now where the Kalman Filter comes in. The Kalman Filter does that by representing
the state in a different way, namely using normal distributions. Which means that we
have to store much less information, simply the mean and the covariance to represent the state.
And the second advantage is that because it represents the state using a continuous random
variable it doesn't have this discretization effect of the grid filter.
So the interesting thing is that the Kalman Filter has been developed and used for the
first time in the late 50s.
It was actually developed by the NASA in the Apollo program, so its first application already
was aerial or space navigation to estimate the trajectory of the Apollo rockets.
And the cool thing is, and this is also why it was capable in the 50s, it is super-efficient
because it requires only very few matrix operations and very few numbers even if you have 6 degrees
of freedom or 10 or so.
And its applications today are very wide, so it is not only used in robotics and space
navigation, but also for diverse things such as economics and weather forecasting.
So at basis of the Kalman Filter we have the normal distribution to represent the state.
I guess most of you will have seen normal distributions before, just to remind you a
bit how this looks like.
First let's only look at one dimensional normal distributions which are also called univariate
normal distributions. Imagine we have a random variable of which we say that it is normally distributed
and we write X~N and then the parameters of such a normal distribution are its mean value
and its variance. And this variance can also be written as the squared standard deviation
and the standard deviation is usually abbreviated with a lower case sigma.
And then, we can specify a probability density function for that X takes a particular value
and this is then given by this negative exponential, which looks like this bell shape.
And now it's interesting to note that the most likely spot always is at the mean of
the normal distribution. And the further you go away the less likely the values become.
And just for having an intuitive feeling what's this covariance actually means is that within
one standard deviation around the mean we already have 68% of the probability mass,
and within 3 standard deviations around then mean we already have 99% of the mass.
We can extend this easily to multivariate normal distributions. I indicate this here again
by bold capital letters, so this X here has multiple dimensions, for example 2 or 3 or
6. And then of course also the mean vector needs to be a vector to specify the mean and
instead of having the simple variance we now have a so called covariance matrix.
And then again, we can specify the probability density function, which looks almost exactly
the same, just that we need to use this covariance matrix here and invert it in the exponent.
This is now a visualization of how this density looks like in 2D.
So here we have a random variable, which has two dimensions x and y. And now the z direction
gives the probability density at this location x and y.
And you can see that it still has this bell shape, but now the covariance matrix can shape
the appearance of this bell.
It can be symmetric and a nice around the bell but it can also be stretched in one direction
and it can be rotated. And therefore, it also makes sense to look at the
probability density function from above because sometimes it's a bit hard to see how this
covariance actually looks like in 3D. So if you would move the camera up and then
look from the top on to your plot you can visualize it of course with colors, but you
can also visualize with so called Isolines at a particular height and then again you
can find heights that correspond to certain probability masses inside of them. For example,
you can say that everything which is located inside this red ellipse here has a mass of
68% for example. But even more common is to have an Isoline of 95% or 99% for example.
Now, a few properties of normal distributions, which are important later for the Kalman Filter.
So the first good news is that normal distributions behave linearly, so if we have one random
variable X that is normal distributed with a mean of µ and a covariance sigma. And we
now define a random variable Y that is a linear combination of a matrix A times X plus some
offset B. Then we can directly move this coefficients into the normal distribution. So we know then
that this Y is normally distributed again with a mean of A times µ plus B, and a covariance
of A times Sigma times A transposed.
And the other good news is that if you intersect two Gaussians then you obtain again a Gaussian.
So you can imagine this as follows, you have two random variables X_1 and X_2 and both
of them are normally distributed, but with different parameters.
Then you could compute an intersection just by multiplying this to densities together,
and if you fill in the values then you see immediately that the result has to be again
a normal distribution and the interesting thing is now to look at how the new mean and
the covariance is computed. And we can see that the new mean is actually
weighted average between the old means weighted by the covariance. So essentially, say for
example the second Gaussian here has a very large covariance so it's a very brought and
very wide uncertain distribution. For example X_1 is really narrow and has a very small
covariance, so the random variable X_1 has much less uncertainty then random variable
X_2. Then the result of the intersection will be strongly influenced by µ_1, so by the
first random variable because Sigma_2 is large and Sigma_1 is relatively small. So the influence
of µ_2 will be relatively limited. And then, we can also compute a new covariance, essentially
by adding the inverse of the individual covariances and taking then again the inverse.
And this generaly means that the uncertainty shrinks, so the covariance shrinks, which
means that if you combine two Gaussians then the result will be narrower and more certain
than the original covariances.
And now, let's look again how we can define a process model using these normal distributions.
We had before this stochastic process, which is also called a Markov chain. So we have
the state in the middle, which is now a vector and we have controls u that influence this
state and we have sensor observations z that we can compute given the state. Now our goal
is to estimate the x here in the middle, the x_t, from the previous state the controls
and the observations that we make.
Now, the first ides of course is to represent the full state which is also our belief by
a Gaussian, so we say this random variable X is normally distributed with a certain mean
µ_t and a covariance Sigma_t. And this state now evolves linearly over time for the moment.
For the moment we assume we have a linear relationship, which means that the new state
is linear combination of the old state. So we multiply a matrix A, the system matrix
also called, times the previous state and obtain the new state.
But now, as we said we of course also issue controls and we furthermore assume now that
these controls influence our state, so we have a second matrix B called the control
matrix that says how this issued control is influencing our new state.
And then of course we always assume that there is some noise in our system. For example,
because the quadrotor shakes slightly or because there are other disturbances like wind that
we cannot model well and so we have to assume that there is a third term epsilon that is
our noise. And this noise is again normally distributed
around zero, so it is a so called zero-mean noise with a covariance of Q.
And this equation now describes how we model the evolution of our state, so the current
state is a linear combination of the old state, our controls and some zero-mean noise.
And now, we also want to find a sensor model that is linear. So we say that our sensor
observation z_t depends on the current state and is multiplied with a so called observation matrix C.
And again, for the observations we assume that they are noisy and this noise is again
Gaussian with zero-mean, so we can write now that the following equation that describes
our sensor model that the observation linearly depend on our previous state plus some zero-mean
noise delta.
So, to summarize this the Kalman Filter makes the following two model assumptions on this
discrete time stochastic process we assume that the state evolves linearly and is a combination
of our previous state, the controls and some system noise and we assume that we have a
linear sensor, where the sensor observation z depends linearly on the previous
state plus some noise. And important is again that we represent the
current state x as a normal distribution and we assume that the noise is normally distributed
with zero-mean.
So just to specify a few of these dimensions of these variables we assume that the state
comes from R^n, so a n-dimensional space. We assume that the controls come from an l-dimensional
space. And by no means l does not need to be the same as n.
So for example, we could have a 3-dimesnional state or a 5-dimesnional state but only a
2-dimesnional control. For example, if you have a car that is driving forward then it
has a, even in 2D it would have 3 degrees of freedom, so the state would be 3-dimesnional
for x, y, and phi.
And we only have two degrees of freedom for controlling, this is than called an under
activated system because we can only change the speed of driving and we can change the
angle of our steering wheel.
And then, we have observations which are k-dimensional and again, these observations do not need
to coincide with the dimensionality of our state or our controls. For example, we could
have a 3-dimesnional state but a 2-dimesnional observation, GPS for example from which we
only get our x and y position.
And then, we have the process equation that we've seen before, and this matrix A of course
then needs to be an n by n matrix. The matrix B that defines the influence of the controls
on to the state is a n times l matrix. And in our measurement equation we have this matrix
C, which needs to be a n times k matrix.
And as we said, we assume that our belief is Gaussian, in particular we have to make
certain assumptions on our initial belief, so in the first time step our prior belief on
where the robot is and it is of course a Gaussian but we need to specify for that µ_0 and Sigma_0.
And if we are uncertain about where the robot is in the beginning, then we could choose
this µ arbitrarily. For example, initialize it with zero and then set the covariance to
a very large matrix, which just means that we are just extremely uncertain and that we
almost have a flat distribution over the belief space.
And then, given these properties that we have seen before of normal distributions we can
compute the next state, which is again a Gaussian distribution then, just because it evolves
linearly. And we can make use of the linear property of normal distributions and also
the observations are Gaussian because they are similarly just a linear combination.
And now, if we apply this representation to the Bayes Filter we end up with a very efficient algorithm.
So just for reminding you of how the Bayes Filter look like, this is what we had in the
previous videos. The Bayes Filter keeps track of the belief
distribution, of the posterior at time step t over the state.
And it consists of two steps, it first integrates the motion u and then it integrates the sensor observations z.
So just to remind you how this looks like. And now we can fill in normal distributions
here first in the first step.
So our process model here is the  irst term for which we can just fill in the normal distribution
with the new mean and the new covariance. And we can fill in our previous belief which
is again just a normal distribution, so both of that actually directly can be filled in
in closed from the definition from the normal distribution.
And then, by multiplying this together if you write this out, which is actually not
too complicated to do, then you end up with a normal distribution again fortunately.
And this normal distribution then just has again a new mean and a new covariance that
can be computed from the matrices A, B, and Q.
And this new belief, belief bar as we call it because it's just a temporarily belief,
is then represented with a Gaussian µ bar and Sigma bar.
And then, we come to the second step of the Bayes Filter, where we need to apply the sensor model.
This step looks as follows, so we have this normalization constant that we ignore for
a moment. We fill in the normal distribution as we had
it and our previous belief. And if you multiply these two together, this
is a bit trickier to derive, you end up again with a normal distribution which consists
of a new mean and a new covariance. And now, the new mean is essentially the old
mean or the µ bar plus matrix K, which is called the Kalman Gain at that we look at
in a second, times our observation minus the predicted observation C µ bar.
So it is important to realize here that what the Kalman Filter actually is doing it blends
our previous estimate µ bar and the discrepancy between our sensor observation and our prediction.
And the degree to which we belief our sensor observation is determined by this Kalman Gain
here, this matrix K, which essentially depends on the ratio between different noise terms.
So for example, the uncertainty that we currently have in our state is this sigmar_bar_t and
the noise or the covariance of our sensor observations is this R. And so essentially
it depends on the ratio between our uncertainty Sigma and the uncertainty of our sensor observation R.
So for example, if we increase our uncertainty of the state Sigma then this Kalman Gain will
get larger and we will put more weight onto our sensor observation z_t - Cµ.
On the other hand, if our sensor noise goes up, if this R gets larger, because it get
inverted here a larger R means a smaller Kalman Gain. So the more nosily our sensor is, because it has a larger R, the
smaller this Kalman Gain will be. So the less we will trust our sensor reading and the more
we will just stick to our prediction from the model µ bar.
But nevertheless, in the end we obtain a normalized distribution with a new mean µ and a new
covariance Sigma.
So just to summarize now the equations of the Kalman Filter. We have again, like in
the Bayes Filter, the two steps of applying the motion model and the sensor model. Now
in case of the Kalman Filter the first step where we apply the motion model is also called
the prediction step because we make a prediction of our current state given the controls and
the normal evolution of our system. And the second step is also called the correction
step because we correct the estimate of our current pose given the sensor observation.
And one important aspect to note here again as with the Bayes Filter actually is:
that the prediction and correction step don't have to come alternatingly, so you could have five
prediction steps because you getting the odometry at a much higher frame rate and then one correction
step when you are getting a visual observation.
So these two steps can be executed in any arbitrary order depending on what your sensors give you.
There is of course more to say about the Kalman Filter, in particular, I have omitted all
the intermediate steps in the derivation but in case that you are interested in the derivations,
which are actually not too complicated to understand it's something that you can really
do by hand by yourself, then I would recommend to look at the Probabilistic Robotics book
of Thrun, Fox and Burgard. And in chapter 3 there is the full derivation of the Kalman
Filter containing all intermediate steps that you have to do.
So the good news now on the Kalman Filter is that it is extremely efficient, so it is
polynomial in the measurement dimensionality and state dimensionality. The only costly
thing that we have to do is that we have to invert this expression here, which depends
on the size of our observations and our states, but everything else is just a multiplication
of matrices which is extremely fast to compute.
And the other good thing is that it can be shown that this is actually the optimal solution,
so it is the best estimate that you can get if you have linear Gaussian systems and you
have linear Gaussian sensors.
This is a good approximation actually in most cases. Of course there are situations where it
is not a good approximation, but in most cases it is.
The only problem is that most robotic systems are of course nonlinear. So it is hard to
specify this very simple linear transformation matrix for the state or for the sensor.
Now let's look at how to deal with that nevertheless. So if you have a nonlinear function, instead
of having this linear dependency between the state and the current state we can introduce
a certain arbitrary nonlinear function that just takes the previous state and the control
u as input. And similarly we can define a nonlinear or
an arbitrarily observation or sensor function that given the current state makes a prediction
of our sensor measurement. Then the question is can we somehow use these nonlinear functions
in the Kalman Filter as well.
And in particular, the idea is can we actually linearize these functions, and then, the main
idea is to linearize these functions. And we can do that as follows, imagine we
have these nonlinear function g that we want to use in the Kalman Filter. Then we can just
apply a first order Taylor approximation where we linearize at our current pose estimate
µ at time step t-1. And then, we add the derivative of g with respect to the current
state times the distance of the current state from our linearization point µ. And this
derivative here is also called the Jacobian and it is a matrix. So remember g already
gives us a vector typically if our state is multidimensional and now we differentiate
this with respect to the state again. So we end up with an n by n matrix that we can multiply
with the distance from our linearization point to get this first order Taylor expansion.
The same can be done with the observation function, so here again this h refers to a
nonlinear function that we can approximate by taking the function value at our linearization
point µ bar. And then we add the product of the derivative
of this function h with respect to the state times the difference from our current state
minus our linearization point. And this again gives us a Jacobian now this
is called the observation or the sensor Jacobian capital H that we can multiply with the difference
from our current state and our linearization point to obtain the first order Taylor approximation
of our nonlinear function.
And now we can plug this into the Kalman Filter directly. So we have essentially almost the
same equations as before, just now we use our nonlinear motion function for the prediction
step to determine the µ bar. Then we use this Jacobian G to compute our covariance
based on the previous covariance and by adding this sensor noise.
And then in the correction step we again use directly our observation function h at our
current state estimate to make a prediction of what a sensor probably sees.
And then, this difference is multiplied by the Kalman Gain to update our state estimate
and to shrink the covariance then, to reduce the uncertainty by this sensor update we use
now this matrix H, which is the derivative of our nonlinear sensor function with respect
to our current state.
So to summarize this video. We've introduced the Kalman Filter first for the linear case,
and then, we stated that of course most robotics problems most interesting problems are not
linear. So we've shown a way how to linearize then
the sensor and the motion model and in this case this can then be used in the so called
Extended Kalman Filter to deal with such nonlinear sensor and motion models.
And because this was quite theoretical now the next we will show a very nice example
in 2D that hopefully shade some light on the inner functions of the Kalman Filter and also
give you some intuitive understanding of what the individual matrices mean and in particular
how the choice of this noise variables R and Q influence the estimate of the Kalman Filter.