Hello and welcome everybody back to lecture video 7.2.
In the previous video we have introduced how we can estimate 2D motion in camera images
and now in this video we will extend this to allow a quadrotor to estimate its horizontal
speed using visual odometry.
So as you remember from our lecture on control there are actually several control layers
stacked in a quadrotor. So at the lowest level we have this motor
speed estimation and the motor speed controller. Then we have an attitude estimation typically
using the IMU and gyroscopes. And then, we have an attitude control, for example using
a PID controller. And on top of that we have typically a localization module that can be
based on a camera for example. And that is then used to support velocity and position control for
higher levels of trajectory control for example but also to simplify life for a human pilot.
Today we look at this visualization block over there, today we only look at the so
called visual odometry problem. But we will then extend this next week to
full visual SLAM.
So the basic problem here is that the velocity estimates that we are getting here form our
IMU are very inaccurate, at least for small UAVs like quadrotors that we are looking at.
The problem is that the IMU as you know consists of gyroscopes and accelerometers. And in particular
the accelerometer estimate accelerations and if you are integrate accelerations you end
up with velocities, and if you integrate it twice then you end up with positions. But
any error or noise that you have in your accelerations will end up strong errors in your integrated
velocity and even larger errors in your position.
And this means that you typically can use the IMU to propagate or estimate your velocity and position
for maybe half a second or maybe a few hundred milliseconds.
So the question is: how can we get more accurate velocity estimates that are less sensitive
to this noise from the IMU?
And the constrain of course is that we need to have this estimates in real time because
we need them in our control loop immediately and we want to have minimal delay because
we need it in control.
And the basic idea is now that we have a quadrotor and the quadrotor has a downward looking camera.
And from this camera image it tries to track one or more points in the camera image. And
from this motion in the image it tries to compute back the motion of the quadrotor in the 3D world.
So one first observation here is that if we only use a single monocular camera then we
could not determine the absolute speed. And the reason for that is that with just one
eye you cannot really tell how far the world is away or how large the world is, so the same motion in a 2D image could
correspond to different distances in the real world depending on your flying height.
And this actually means that we need additional sensors and the common choice is then to use
first of all the IMU because we have that anyway. This will give us the absolute orientation
of our quadrotor. Typically there is also a height sensor being used that gives us then
the absolute scale of the world. For that you can for example use ultrasound as is used
in the Parrot ArDrone or you can use a pressure sensor since changes in pressure also correspond
to changes in height.
And one strong assumption which is typically made with this visually odometry sensors that we look at in
this video is that we assume a planar floor. This is strictly speaking not necessary we
will later see how we can relax this assumption but for the moment we assume that we are looking
at a perfectly planar floor.
So here are again our assumptions. For the moment we assume that we have a camera that's
perpendicular looking onto a planar ground. And furthermore, we assume that we know our
flying height for example from ultrasound sensors or from somewhere else.
And then, we have a camera images and we look at a particular point, say here for example
this point exactly in the center of the image and we try to track it as the quadrotor moves.
So for example, in the next image the quadrotor has moved a little bit now to the right. It
still keeps tracking this point that was previously located in the center of the image. Now it
is shifted slightly to the left with respect to the new camera coordinates.
And this point in the world is now imaged onto the image plane. And this is what we
get out of the 2D motion estimation of the image. So we make an observation in the image
that this point has shifted by a certain number of pixels u and v. And of course, there is
now a relationship between these point in 2D and the point in the real world in 3D,
and this is given by this equation here in the middle.
x tilde equals K, where K is the intrinsic matrix of our camera, times our 3D point.
And this 3D to 2D projection of course goes now in the wrong direction because we want
to know the point p but we know x tilde. Remember that this tilde means that this entity
is a homogeneous vector, so it contains our image coordinates u and v but it might be
scaled up arbitrarily by a factor lambda and this homogeneous coordinates now equals the
product of the intrinsic matrix times our 3D point. And if you look carefully you can
see that if you only look at the last column it says that lambda equals Z, so you can identify
lambda here with Z now and then solve for p.
So we can just do that by multiplying by K^(-1) on both sides of the equation and then we
end up with a very simple expression and we can directly read of the motion in X and Y
direction in world coordinates.
Of course the quadrotor is not as friendly and is always looking downwards perpendicular
to the floor, but of course the quadrotor tilts a lot during flight. So this means that the
second image might be tilted slightly but we still assume that it is tracking this point
that we're looking at in the first frame. And now, because we have this IMU onboard
we actually know the amount of rotation, the relative rotation between these two camera
frames and this actually allows us to derotate this camera, to create a virtual camera that is located at the
same spot in the world but it is looking perpendicular to the floor again.
And there is a very easy relationship now between the point that the tilted camera observed
and the point that would appear in this derotated virtual camera.
So because if we know this rotation R from our IMU we can just multiply this rotation
by this observed point p in the tilted camera frame and this gives us the point p prime
that is now expressed in this perpendicular camera.
And this means now that for this virtual camera we again have the situation from the last
slide where we just had a pure translation and now we can fill in that into our equation
as before, so now we are getting the X and Y motion just by derotating it by R^(-1) as
you know which is exactly the same as R transposed times the inverse of the intrinsic
matrix times Z times the homogeneous vector u, v, 1.
So of course the quadrotor not only flies in one plane it also changes its flying height.
And then, let's look at what this actually means. So if the quadrotor is now changing
its height but still keeping track of the same point, then this point appears at different
locations in the image plane. The higher the quadrotor flies the smaller the world appears, and so the smaller this shift in
the image plain becomes. So you see from this catch here that the pixel coordinate actually
gets scaled by the ratio of the two flying heights. So now we not only need the flying
height from the first camera but we also need to know the flying height of the second camera.
But if we know that we can again create a virtual
observation x prime where we scale the two pixel observations u and v by this factor.
And then again, we can plug that into our previous equation that we had. And this
now gives us the full formula how we come from pixel 2D motion estimates in the image
plane to 2D velocities in the real world.
So far we only tracked a single point now for illustration, but of course it is clear
that if you only look at a single point then you are quit sensitive to noise and outliers
and of course the accuracy and the robustness can be increased greatly if you not only track a single point, but a whole
bunch of them. For example the PX4FLOW sensor at which we will look at in a second actually
tracks an array of 4 by 4 points in the image and it runs the majority vote algorithm sample
consensus methods like RANSAC to find the motion hypothesis that has the largest
support from all the points.
Now two hardware implementations examples, you know the Parrot ArDrone of course and
the main board and navigation board together form such a visual odometry sensor. There
is a downward looking camera, there is an IMU, an ultrasound sensor to determine the absolute
flying height, and a pressure sensor that the ArDrone can use when it flies higher than 5 meters,
because the ultrasound sensor only works up to a certain height of course because at some
point you don't hear your own echo anymore. But this is only needed for larger flying
heights if you're going outdoors.
Pressure indoors is difficult because as soon as somebody opens the window or a door then
your pressure changes and so it's not really informative.
One disadvantage of the Parrot board is that
it is closed source, so we do not really know what's going on in there. There is actually
one research paper that you can read but it doesn't go too much into details and there
is no code available. In contrast people from ETH, from Marc Pollefeys
group actually developed this Px4Flow sensor and released it as open source and
open hardware, so you can buy it preassembled but you can also look at the software there
and of that we know much better how it works and what its properties are.
So let's look at that in a little more detail. It's a so called smart camera module it combines
a camera with a processor. And this camera can run at reasonable resolution, but of course
for our application it is desirable that it runs at a really high frame rate. This one
can run at 250 frames per second and you still get a reasonably high resolution image. It
also has a zoom lens on it which means that the opening angle is quit narrow. This has
the advantage that we're then looking at a, so we made this assumption that the floor
is planar and of course if you have a wide angle camera then we see all kinds of things
including the walls and maybe objects and persons walking around.
So it's an advantage to have a zoom lens because then you are focusing on a small patch of
the world and then the likelihood at this patch actually is planar and much larger.
And then, there is also a processor that runs at 168 megahertz so this is quite something.
It even can do a single precision floating point operations and as I said the software
on this processor is open source so you can download it have a look at it, even potentially
modify it or replace it by your own implementation. Furthermore, there is a gyroscope on board
that we need to estimate the rotation change. There is also accelerometer integrated and
there is an ultrasound sensor. As you can see here this is actually a sender and receiver
in one module. So the Parrot ArDrone has a separate sender and receiver and this module
has here both integrated in the same thing. And this sensor does everything that we need,
it directly outputs the x and y speed over a serial link. It also outputs the gyroscope
information so you can use that as well in the Kalman Filter and use that for position
control.
So this is now a demo that shows how this looks like. This is a modified Parrot ArDrone
it's just the hardware left and the motor controller and everything else got replaced
the authors and now this visual odometry sensor is running there it's looking downwards here
Domenik Honegger who's the remote controls but he is not touching any controls and still
the quadrotor is keeping its position. And now the cool thing is that you can directly
control the speeds, absolute speeds in the world coordinate frame. So you can control
that the ArDrone goes up and down and he can command that the ArDrone goes forward and
backward, and left and right. And for that it is just using this visual odometry sensor with its downward looking camera.
And the cool thing of course is that if you have visual odometry then it greatly simplifies
the navigation task for the pilot because you don't need to worry about compensating
for disturbances the quadrotor will stay in place whenever you leave it and so on and so on.
Here is another video that demos that the ArDrone is rock-solid standing in the air,
it doesn't need any markers on the floor, a little bit texture is enough but most floor
actually have that and you can also see the whole electronics that got added to the ArDrone.
It's not only this optical flow sensor but also a different autopilot.
This is now another quadrotor you can also see the sensor works there and here you can
see that it works outdoors.
They also ran some evaluation here, so visual odometry by itself is still problem to drift
but it drifts much less than the IMU. But nevertheless it's of course interesting how
large this drift is and to illustrate that there is quite a little drift they run the following
experiment. They went outdoors and walked through the University Park at the ETH with
a relatively low flying height, manual control, and then, they were manually flying this quadrotor that
was carrying this PX4FLOW sensor and they were just integrating up the position estimates
from the sensor and it's important to note that there was no GPS involved. So the trajectory
they got out of that they overlaid this to this aerial image from Google Maps and then
you can see that this trajectory matches nicely the foot path on the campus. And this is a
good indication that actually the sensor provides reasonable vuisual odometry.
I should mention that there are also alternatively methods to compute visual odometry from different
sensor setups. For example, there is the possibility to use a stereo camera or a depth sensor like
Kinect, we will look at a direct visual odometry method for that next week. But there is also
the possibility to use a wide angle lens and an IMU and not to use any ultrasound sensor
but to use the IMU directly to estimate the scale.
So and this was actually implemented by Stefan Weiss from Roland Siegwarts group at the
ETH. The idea there is to use PTAM which is a monocular visual SLAM library from Klein
and Murray presented at ISMAR 2007. It builds a sparse 3D map from visual features so it
runs something similar to this KLT tracker which you have seen before, but then it additionally
estimates the 3D position of every feature in the world and uses that again to compute
the tracked camera pose in the world. The problem with the visual SLAM in general
is that it gets slower and slower the more key frames you add and so the idea of Stefan
Weiss was to drop old key frames to have a limited or a fixed number of key frames in
your buffer to keep the computation time actually constant.
With that you can guarantee that you can compute the visual odometry at a reasonable frame
rate of 30 Hertz or around that. And then as I said, they also use the IMU
then to estimate the scale. This is also viable and possible it's a bit noisier than if you
directly get your height estimates from ultrasound sensors but it's nevertheless possible and
you need less hardware.
So this video demos that in principle now. This was recorded in MoCap area from
Raffaello d'Andrea at ETH. You can see here that the quadrotor is flying small rectangle
and it's using this visual odometry method here and it spits out the position estimates
here on the right, and you can see that sometimes there is a little bit of noise especially
when the quadrotor shakes a lot. Nevertheless you can recognize this rectangle that it flew
and in this way you can do position control and stabilize your flight.
So to summarize the video of today, we've looked at visual odometry methods for UAVs.
We've introduced one particular sensor setups that is used quite frequently in more detail and introduced
the basic algorithm, and we've also briefly looked in alternative methods for computing visual
odometry that are also used a lot on quadrotors.
Next week is our last week actually. And there we will in particularly present the cutting
edge research results from our group. So we will show some very exiting research work
that we have done over the past years. And as far as possible I also point you initial
references then in case that you want to extend upon this work.