Hello and welcome everybody to lecture 4.2 on feedback control. In this video we will
look at the problem of how to bring a dynamical system, say a quadrotor for example, in a particular
goal state by giving the right sequence of motion or action commands.
For example in the case of a quadrotor we often want to move it to a desired goal location. Say
above a landing spot or to the landing spot. And for that we need to generate of course
a suitable control signal. And this control signal essentially corresponds to the controls
that you give with the remote control. So you can change the roll and the pitch or
the height, and the yaw angle, the heading.
You could not do this blindly, you need to know of course where the robot is at the moment.
And then, you can compare this current location that you will have to observe through sensors
somehow with your goal location, and then based on the comparison on these two you can generate
a suitable control signal.
So before we go into more technical details I just want to give you a very intuitive example
first on what the generic idea behind feedback control actually is.
So imagine for example that you get a morning shower and you get out of the bed and you
jump into the shower. And then, you want to switch it on and you want to have your water
to have a comfortable temperature, say of 35 degrees. So you are in this case the controller
that selects the water temperature and you just switch on the valve or the mixer of your
shower and that will make the water flow of the system. The shower is then called the
system in control theory or the plant. And then you stand below the shower of course
and then you can sense the temperature of the water and then figure out that it's actually
not at the 35 degrees that you expected, but much below. And so you feedback, and this is the
idea of feedback control, and you feedback this measurement to the controller to take
an appropriate action. So in this case you first compare the observed temperature
to the desired temperature. You observe that there is a certain discrepancy of a few
degrees and so you would turn the valve hotter to hopefully make the water warmer.
And if necessary, you do this close looped cycle until the water has reached the right temperature.
So much to the generic idea, now let's look at this in a more technical way. It's often
drawn in block diagram like this. On the left side you can see the reference signal or the
goal state that we try to achieve. And this goal state or desired value is compared to
the current state of our system. And then this difference, the so called measurement
error, is then feed into a controller. And this controller can be arbitrary complex, but for this video
we just look at a proportional, a P controller, as we will see in a second.
And this controller then generates a control output. This can be for example a 1 dimensional
variable that just specifies whether we should turn it hotter or colder or to move the quadrotor
forward or backward. But it can also have multiple dimensions as we will see later.
And then this control goes into our system. For example, into the shower or the pipe system.
And this control then changes the internal state of the system,
so the output of the system is its internal state, which we can then observe with one or more
sensors to obtain a measured state.
And this measured state is then compared again to the reference value
and leads to an updated measured error that is used again by the controller to adjust the controls.
So as I said, the controller can be arbitrarily complex but a very simple and efficient controller,
thats actually used a lot in practice, is just a linear controller that takes the error
that we are getting in and multiplies it by a constant, the so called gain.
So this K here can be anything, any positive value in principal. And in this way we take directly the error values.
And so the controls depend linearly on the errors.
And then, our system can of course also behave arbitrarily complex, but in the case of the shower example,
and also for the quadrotor for position control, we can just tread it as a linear system.
So the new state can be computed from the old state plus the control that we have given.
So if we increase the temperature by 5 degrees, then we would just add +5 to the previous
state of the system. And there might be some error constant epsilon here that describes the
system noise. Things that are out of our control, for example, a changing temperature or water
pressure in the water system.
And then this system state gets observed by our sensor. Again the sensor can be arbitrarily
complex, but for the shower we could just assume that we have a linear temperature sensor
that observes exactly the temperature from the system plus some noise delta that changes
every time constant, but it is distributed according to some distribution.
So now let's have a look, what this does for our shower example.
In the first plot, so now we assume that we have this control law where the control output just
depends linearly on our error. And now imagine that we start at say 25 degrees and we want
to achieve 35 degrees in the shower to have it comfortably warm. Then in the first time
step the algorithm would compare the observed temperature 25 to the desired value 35 and
find that there is a difference of +10. So it would feedback a control or it would generate
a control of +10. And then within one time step this control
would change the temperature of the shower. And in the next time step we already have
reached the 35 degrees, and because we are at the desired value already the error term
will become 0, and as a result, also the control will become 0 then.
Of course this is not very realistic because you always have some noise in such a system.
Both, in the process itself so in the system but also in the measurements and in your sensor.
And now, for this plot I added some noise in the measurements. So instead of returning
exactly the right temperature of the internal state of the system we get a noisy observation
of that. But still we can compare this noisy observation with our desired value and with
the same law as before we can use that to generate a control. And as you cans see, again
we reach roughly the desired temperature but you can also see that it is quite jumpy, for
example roughly at 8 seconds time or so, we reach a temperature of 37 or almost 38 degrees.
And then, later at maybe 12 seconds time it even drops down to 35. So this is probably
not very comfortable in the morning to have such a temperature profile of your shower.
Another problem here is that the controller always generates some control commands, so
you can see that the green line here in the bottom plot is not reaching 0, it always
changes a lot between plus and minus 4 maybe. And this means that if you would be under
the shower you would have to constantly adapt the temperature and that's of course not very
comfortable, but also for a quadrotor this would not be very energy efficient if you
have to give constantly controls just to keep the same temperature.
So as you can see, if we keep it as before, if we chose K equals 1, so directly used the error
as the control, then we get a relatively poor performance. And now the question of course is:
how can we improve on that? And one very simple way is to lower this gain K,
to a lower value, say 0.15. If we observe 10 degrees difference between our current
value and the desired one, then we will only try to adjust it by 1.5 degrees per time step.
And that makes us somewhat more robust against noise, we kind of filter away the noise partially.
But it also means that it takes much longer then to reach our desired temperature.
So in this example for example the red line, which is the true line of the temperature
reaches 35 degrees around 20 seconds time. But nevertheless we can see that it keeps
the desired temperature relatively well. Despite this large sensor noise that we have in our system.
But the problem obviously is that, if you lower the gain to much, then your system or
your controller will get slower and slower and it will take more and more time to reach
the desired value.
So you could think of how large can you make this gain that it still works.
And you might also be tempted to make the gain larger than 1. And this should be noted
that this is always problematic actually. For example, consider this example where we
chose a coefficient of 2.15. And now what happens is that it always overshoots a lot because
it finds that there is a 10 degree difference between the current value and the desired
value. So it will multiply that by 2.15, and then, add 20 degrees to that and then be much
too high. And then, in the next time step it will find that the temperature is way too high
and then reduce it and so on. And this will start to oscillate and actually
this oscillations will increase over time.
So be careful with to large gains.
Another thing that happens often in practice actually, when you program a controller,
is that you might end up with the wrong sign either in the coefficient or in the way how you compute the errors.
So if you observe when you doing the exercise for this week, and you observe that your quadrotor
shoots away in one direction, then maybe check the sign of your error function or of
your coefficient.
So let's see what's happens if we chose a negative coefficient.
And then what we can see, if the algorithm or our controller finds that the temperature
is too low it will even make it lower than before. And so the shower reduces the
temperature more and more. This is a fun example of course, the temperature
drops to negative degrees and then at some point convergence to -272 degrees.
So this is the absolute zero point. And this is actually an interesting aspect
that in most practical cases you can get saturation effects, either in the state space so that
the shower can't get colder than maybe 0 degrees Celsius and that it can't get hotter than
maybe 100 degrees. So you don't want to get it hotter than 60 degrees, so you have saturation
in the state space. But at the same time you can also have saturation in your control space,
which means that you can't arbitrarily fast open the valve for hot water for example
or you can't fly or accelerate arbitrarily fast with a quadrotor. And this is then called
a control saturation, which just means that your control has a maximum and a minimum value
that you can give.
So for example, if you have to open the valve by hand, then maybe you can only rotate it
at a certain speed. And this might mean that it takes a few seconds until you have opened
it enough to get your 35 degrees of desired temperature.
Time delays are another very important problem that you have in most practical systems,
especially in a shower that you don't know or that you don't know the dynamics. This
can be a very tricky problem, so the thing is that you switch on, or you try to increase the temperature,
but nothing happens. So for example here in time step 8, the valve is opened or the temperature
is being changed. But in the blue line, which gives us the observations from our systems,
nothing changes for 5 seconds, because we have a time delay of 5 seconds.
And only after these 5 seconds we get the first readings of the changed temperature,
but by the time we think that we have reached the 35 degrees, which is roughly at time step
19 here, the shower is already much hotter, maybe at 38 or so. Because we don't know we
overshoot. And then, we need to reduce the temperature again, give negative controls to bring the
temperature down to 35 degrees.
And this first effect here is called overshooting, so if you're going beyond the desired value
that you are actually trying to achieve. And if it goes back and forth around your desired
value, then this is called an oscillation. And in the worst case, depending on how your
delays are and what the dynamics are of your system this can even lead to destabilization.
One solution always is obviously to lower the gains of your controller, but as we have
seen before this is probably a bad idea. It can help, but the disadvantage is that the
convergence takes much longer, and maybe you have to wait a few minutes then in the shower until
you get the right temperature that you desire.
So let's look at this time delay problem in a little bit more detail, because we will
also need it for the quadrotors. The problem in general is that you might have several
places where time delays can occur. Actually in all of these components you could have
time delays, so of course, the most obvious one in the shower example is that the water
pipe might introduce a considerable time delay if you have huge pipes with little water going
through them. But also your measurement system, your sensor
might introduce a certain delay, and also your controller or the communication between these
components might introduce delays.
So one question here now is: whether or not we can actually distinguish between the individual
time delays from within the controller? And the quick answer here is that it's not possible
to distinguish that for the controller. The dead time or the delay of the system or of
the whole loop is not observable, it always appears as if you have a system with 1.2 seconds
delay in this case.
So there is a simple solution to accommodate for delays. And that is the so called Smith
predictor, which allows you to use higher gains then you could use if you just ignore the delays.
However, the Smith predictor requires a very accurate system model and you might not have always
such an accurate model. So the idea of the smith predictor is as follows.
Again, we have a controller that compares the current predicted state with the desired
state, and then generates a control signal that we feed into the system that has a certain
delay. But instead of sensing the output of the system we have a delay free system model
that we calibrated and that we think is accurate as possible to model our real system.
And this model is delay free, so it gives us immediately the expected observation from
the system at the current time step. And we can then feed that back into the controller
to compare it to the desired value.
Now this by itself would only work if you have a perfectly accurate model, which of
course is never the case in any real situation. But this is where the Smith predictor idea
comes in. We still have a sensor then that observes the system state, but remember this
observation set t is actually time delayed by a certain time delay.
And what we now do is we also time delay our prediction z^(pred) that we got from our system
model and we compare these two. And if our model is perfectly accurate, then the difference
between the real sensor observation and the delayed sensor observation should be zero.
If it's however not perfect, then we will get here a residual that we can use to correct
our delay free prediction. And in this way we can take advantage of both,
the delay free system model, but we can also deal with deviations from that. So if our
system model doesn't do anything or is partially wrong then we still have this normal error term
that just considers the difference of the sensor and the model.
So let's first look at a very simple example, where we assume that we have a perfect system
model of our shower, and we have a 5 seconds delay.
The Smith predictor results in a perfect compensation because we know exactly what's going on in
the system. And we can perfectly compensate for the delay then.
Of course, this is completely unrealistic in practice because you never have a good model
or a super accurate model, there will always be some parts of the system that you can't
model exactly. And the other problem is that you typically don't know exactly about the
delay. in some systems you know, but if it's a communication delay for example, that you
get through wireless then this delay or the bandwidth might change as you fly and it's
not always possible to know how long the signal was traveling.
Because you have these uncertainties, the question is: whether you should better over-
or underestimate the time delay?
Let's consider first if we would overestimate the time delay what the result would be.
And then, the effect is as follows: so our system, the Smith predictor predicts too far
into the future, which means that it thinks that just by giving it a certain control command
that we have already reached our desired goal location. Because in a very distant future
we already might be at the desired state or we might even overshoot. So it will greatly
reduce the controls and in the next time step, because it thinks that we're already going
too fast. And then it would project that into the future,
and then realize that it is actually to slow and so it would go back and forth and oscillate.
And as you can see this is clearly not optimal. And it also leads to large changes in the
control. Which is actually not what we want because this costs a lot of energy.
An alternative then is to underestimate the time delay and that is actually what's often
done in practice. Because then you don't get this overshooting effect of you prediction.
Although you still have a certain discrepancy between your model and the actual system, because
you underestimating the time delay. But in this way you can use your model to compensate
for half or maybe 90 percent of your time delay and you consider the rest, as the noise
or the thing that you try to not model and just use directly the sensor readings.
This leads of course to a slightly slower convergence in the end but it circumvents oscillations and
makes your approach the goal state nicely.
So this concludes the video then for this session. We have looked at the control problem, the
feedback control problem in particular. We have introduced proportional control and we
have briefly looked at delay compensation using the Smith predictor.
And then in the next video we will extend this to a full PID control and then apply
that to a position control for quadrotors.