Hello, and welcome, everybody, to the first lecture
on Autonomous Navigation for Flying Robots.
My name is Jurgen Sturm, and I'm a post-doctoral researcher
in the Computer Vision Group at the Technical University
of Munich.
This course is about quadrotors, and I guess that most of you
will already have seen a quadrotor in action.
Maybe some of you even own a quadrotor,
or have flown one yourself.
This one here is a very popular platform.
It's called the Parrot AR.Drone.
It was originally meant to be a children's toy,
but it turned out that this is a versatile platform also
for quadrotor research and teaching with quadrotors.
To pilot it around, originally, the idea
was to connect to it with a smartphone,
and then the quadrotor will copy the motions of the phone.
So if you tilt your phone forward, it will move forward.
If you tilt it backwards, it will tilt backwards,
and then also fly backwards.
Same for left and right.
The thing that makes it so cool for us
is that it has a whole bunch of integrated sensors,
and that it transmits all of the sensor data
back over wireless, so that we can use it, then,
on the computer.
For example, it contains accelerometers and gyroscopes
that it uses to estimate its attitude,
and to keep the quadrotor leveled.
It also has an ultrasound sensor to measure the distance
to the floor, and then to keep the flying
height of the quadrotor constant.
It also has a visual odometry sensor
that estimates the horizontal speed
of the quadrocoptor that's, for example,
important during hovering, or during flying in general.
And it also has a forward camera,
at a higher resolution, that you can
use to shoot images or shoot nice aerial videos.
And with that, you can, for example, fly around your house,
look around a corner, or, if you fly high above your house,
you can record nice aerial videos of it.
And as nice as it is to pilot a quadrocoptor by yourself,
the question that comes immediately into your mind,
as a computer scientist, is, how can you actually make
this quadrotor fly autonomously?
And this is actually the main goal of this course,
to teach you how to program the quadrocoptor so
that it becomes autonomous.
And that involves, of course, all kinds of topics.
For example, we have to estimate the internal state
of the quadrotor from its sensor readings.
That means you need to know its attitude,
but we also want to know its position.
And we estimate that from GPS
noisy GPS readings, for example, or images
that we're getting from the quadrotor.
And once you have the state, the next question, then,
is how can we generate suitable control commands
to make quadrocoptor fly towards the desired goal position?
And then as a tool to generate a whole path,
collision-free path, that takes the quadrotor from A to B.
So this is the course content, by week.
This week, we start with an introduction,
showing why a quadrotor flies, what the flight principle
is, what sensors it typically carries on.
And then we will briefly review current state-of-the-art
methods in quadrotor research.
So with that, you will get a good feeling
for what's currently out there, and what the open problems are.
Then, in the second week, we will
give you a brief recap on linear algebra,
and look, in particular, then, at 2-D geometry
and coordinate transference between different coordinate
systems.
In the third week, we will then extend this to 3-D geometry.
In particular, we will look at projections
of cameras using the pinhole model.
And we will introduce the mathematical models
for all kinds of sensors that are typically
employed on a quadrotor.
In the fourth week, we will then look
at motors, and motor controls, in particular.
And this will then give us the possibility
to steer the quadrotor in simulation
towards the desired goal location.
In week five, we then introduce probabilistic state estimation.
We will do that, first, by giving a brief recap
on probability theory.
And then we look at Bayes' law, and how
that can be used to infer the growth state.
In week six, we extend this, then, to the so-called filters,
like Bayes' filter, but, of course, also the Kalman filter.
And then in the exercises, you will
implement parts of a Kalman filter-- of an extended Kalman
filter-- to track the position of a quadrotor, given a GPS
signal.
Then, in week seven, we will introduce
so-called visual odometry sensors,
and we will look in more detail how these sensors work,
and what the underlying algorithms are
for computing visual odometry quickly.
And I'm really looking then forward to week eight,
where we will present you some really cutting edge research
results from our group here-- just to show you
what we are currently working on--
and present some of the really new approaches
that we've been publishing over the past years.
This course, as I said, consists of eight weeks.
Every week, there will be video lectures,
roughly between 30 and 45 minutes long.
These videos will be interleaved by interactive exercises.
Partially, this will be interactive quizzes
where you have to type in the solution,
and also arithmetic problems, where
you have to do some calculations on paper.
But actually, the most interesting part
are the hands-on programming exercises
that you will have to do in Python.
We have developed a web-based simulator for a quadrotor,
and this means that you can immediately
try out all your skills that you have learned
during this course on a simulated quadrotor.
And we took special care that actually the code
that you will be writing will be also executable
on a Parrot AR.Drone.
So if you happen to happen a Parrot AR.Drone,
you can try out the solutions to the exercises
directly on the real thing.
This was now the first video.
In the next video, I will introduce
why quadrotors are so cool.
And what the potential applications,
also commercially relevant applications of quadrotors,
might be in the future.