Hello and welcome everybody to lecture 5.1.
This week we will look at the problem of state estimation.
And this will actually keep us busy for the next two weeks because next week then we will
use the basics that we introduce this week to introduce the Kalman Filter. And then show
how we can use that to estimate the pose of a quadrotor even from noisy measurements,
such as visual odometry or GPS.
So before we dive more into the technical problems I first want to clarify a few terms.
As you know from last week we can describe the state of our system with a variable, which
is then typically referred as the system state or the world state.
This world state represents then the current state of the system. So for example, if we
have a quadrotor flying in a 3D world we could describe its state using a 3 dimensional vector
describing its position. If it's hovering above a landing site at the
same time we could also depending on the task that we are looking at, we could also model
its relative position to this landing site or the position of this landing site in the world
and the quadrotor in the world.
So when we talk about the world state then we mean the actual state of the world,
the actual position of the quadrotor in the world.
Of course, we need an internal representation then of this world state because we need this
world state for applying our PID-controller for example.
And this is then called the belief state, which is the internal representation of this
world state. And it is important to note here that this
belief state does not necessarily have to match the real world state.
Because as you know, all sensors or all observations that we can make are noisy, so it's not guaranteed that
what the robot actually thinks where it is, is actually where it really is.
So we have already discussed this a little bit. The question then of course is: what
are the relevant parts of the world state that we really need to model? And that depends
to a great deal of course on the task attend that we try to solve.
So for a quadrotor in general it's of course very important that we know its position in the world,
and then, typically this is somewhere between the 2 dimensional position or a 3 dimensional
position or maybe even a 6 degree of freedom pose in 3D space.
We're generally also interested in the velocity. We need  that remember for the derivative part in the PID-controller.
We might also be interested if we are flying through the world, of course we want to know where the obstacles are.
Maybe if we need to do path planning we also need the map.
And then, all of these components actually are part of the world state and need to be
represented somehow, both by the world state but also in our belief state of the world state.
There might be other things, like other objects in the world that we might interested in, like humans for
example or other robots if the quadrotor is exploring an environment in a swarm.
And as I said, depending on the application that you are looking at, there might be much more things
that you might have to represent in your world.
The problem with that in general is that without sensors we cannot directly observe the world
state although we need it. So we need to estimate it somehow.
And there are two sources of information generally on a robot. The first one is that we carry
along a large number of sensors of course, so we can try to infer the world state form
sensor readings. The second option is that we know which actions that we sent to our
motors. So we can use that to compute an odometry for example, as we have already done.
So from the actions that we have given to the robot we can then infer the world state.
Ideally of course you would use both, the sensor observations and the issued motion commands
that you have send to the motors.
So let's first start with the sensor model. As we have said, the robot perceives its environment
and the world state through its sensors.
And this is typically modeled using a so called sensor functions. A sensor function takes
the world state as input and then generates a sensor reading. In practice of course this
is then implemented in hardware because you have a real sensor that you apply to the real
world, and then, it spits out a sensor reading.
And then, our goal is to invert this process and to infer the state of the world from
the sensor readings that we made using the sensor.
Similarly, we can define something similar for the motion model. So imagine that we have
executed a certain action or given a certain control command u to our robot for example
that we wanted to move forward at a certain speed.
Then we can update our belief state about the world state according to a particular
motion model. For example, given the previous state and the executed action we can then
compute what the most likely state will be where we are in.
And the problem here in general is that all sensor observations that we are getting are
noisy or potentially missing or partially observed the world state. And so it's not
easy to infer from the sensors observations directly the world state.
The second problem is that all models that we can think of and that we can specify
are partially wrong by definition because a model can only be specific up to a certain
degree. And they will also be incomplete because there
are some effects that you cannot model or that you don't want to model because it would make
your model to complicated.
And as a last point, we have typically some prior knowledge about the application in general
or how the environment looks like or how the robot behaves.
And this is something that we want to include of course in our inference process.
And this all together now leads to the so called probabilistic robotics paradigm,
where we say that we cannot be absolutely sure of any of these variables,
but what we can do is to specify probabilistic models to describe it. So for example, instead
of having this deterministic sensor function that maps the world to a one sensor reading
we introduce a probabilistic sensor model that defines a probability distribution over
possible sensor readings given a particular world state.
Similarly we can define a probabilistic motion model then that says when we are in
a certain state and we give a certain motion command that there is a certain probability of possible outcomes
or the pobability distribution over the possible outcomes then of this action.
And then we have to look at two inference problems, namely first of all we want to fuse data
between multiple sensor sources. For example, if we have a camera that provides us some readings
and we have an ultrasound sensor and an IMU sensor. And we want to combine all of these sensor
observations into a single estimate of the world state. And then, we're not only making
a single observation of a sensor but of course we get continuously sensor readings from these
sensor so we want to fuse it over time, this is then called filtering.
And then, the Kalman Filter at that we look at next week is a very efficient variant of
a filter to do that. And this could for example just be based on the sensor readings that
we getting. But as we said before, ideally we want to fuse the data both, from our sensors
encoded by z_1 to z_t and our motion commands that we gave in between, here denoted by u_1 to u_t.
So to summarize this: We have introduced the concepts of the world
state in the real world, and then, the internal belief state of the  robot.
We've looked at sensor models and motion models.
And we motivated why we need probability theory then to model the uncertainty that arises
from different sources.
And then, in the next video we will give a brief recap on probability theory just as
a refresher that all of us are on the same page.