Hello and welcome everybody back to lecture video 5.3.
In this video we will introduce Bayes law and then explain how we can use it to infer
the world state from the available data.
And in terms of data we actually have two sources that we would like to use to infer
the world state, namely first we have sensor measurements
that we denote with z and those sensor measurements
can for example be GPS observation of our position in the 3D world.
But we also have knowledge about our controls that we have send to the motors. And those
will be denoted by u.
And then, of course we need to model the relationship between these senor measurements and our world state.
And for that we already introduced the sensor
model that describes the probability between x and z.
And our motion model that describes the relationship between our previous world state, the motion
command that we issued and our new world state.
And now it's important to look closely in which direction we are actually reasoning.
If we go from the sensor readings to the world state, so we make observations from the sensor
and use that to infer the world state, then this is called diagnostic reasoning.
If we however go from the world state, if we assume that we know the world state and
try to infer what sensor readings are likely then this is called causal reasoning.
Typically, at least in our situation we are interested in diagnostic reasoning. We would
like to know where the robot is in the world, given that we make certain GPS or odometry
observations.
But the problem is that diagnostic models are typically very hard to specify and in
contrast causal models are much easier to construct.
Because in this way, for a causal probability distribution you can just go from the world
state and then make predictions on what the senor is likely to report.
And with Bayes rule that we will introduce on the next slides we can use a causal model
that's much easier to construct to actually do diagnostic inference.
So Bayes rule directly follows from the definition of the conditional probability, remember from
the previous video that we can write the joint probability as the product of the conditional
probability times the prior.
So for example, we can factorize the probability P(x,z) into the conditional probability P(x|z)P(z)
and that, of course, because we can reverse the variables equals also the probability P(z|x)P(x).
And if we reshuffle these terms then we directly obtain Bayes rule. So there is no magic behind
Bayes rule, it's just the definition of conditional probability.
And it says then that the probability of x of our world state given z our sensor reading, P(x|z),
can be obtained by taking the probaility of P(z|x) which is our causul model, which is easy to compute,
times the probability  P(x) divided by the probability P(z).
Let's look a little bit closer at those terms and how difficult they are to obtain.
As we have said, this causal model P(z|x) is typically easy to construct for a given sensor.
P(x) encodes the prior on the world state,
so how likely is it that we are in a certain state? That is typically either known from
the previous time step or you just assume a certain prior depending on your application.
But then, you have a denominator the prior on sensor observations. And that's typically
very hard to specify, this term generally says how likely it is to make a certain sensor
measurement. And depending on your sensor this is might be unknown. So it is unclear
how often you actually see a white pixel for a camera or how often you make
a certain distance measurement with an ultrasound sensor. That pretty much also depends on you
environment around you, and so it's a bit complicated to find this term.
But there is a nice trick actually to get around this. And now, the idea is that we
just ignore that for a second. We first compute unnormalized likelihoods that do not necessarily
sum to 1. So we compute the likelihood of x given z, L(x|z), just without the denominator.
And then in a second step we sum all likelihoods and we know that to turn this distribution L into
a proper distribution it has to sum to 1. So we can just divide through the sum overall
likelihoods in step 3 then.
And this gives us a proper probability distribution of P(x|z).
And the same derivation actually for the Bayes rule that we had before also works in the
presents of background knowledge.
So, if we now assume that we have a certain background knowledge set. Then we can still do the same
separation for x and y as before. And that gives us then the Bayes rule with background knowledge.
So the only change here is that we always have our variables x and y conditioned additionally on
a variable z, which just stays on the right side in all of the expressions.
And we will need that in a view slides.
So because all of this was quite theoretic so far I thought that we should first look
at a simple example to clarify maybe a few things to show you how Bayes rule can be applied
in practice.
So imagine that we having a quadrotor that is seeking its landing zone. And lets further
more assume that this landing zone has been marked with many bright lamps, and furthermore,
that the quadrotor has a brightness sensor onboard to detect actually these lamps.
For that it might have a special purpose brightness sensor of course, but you can in principle
also treat a camera as a sophisticated brightness sensor, just by summing over all pixel intensities.
Now the problem in this example, or the reason why this is actually interesting is that there
are not only lamps at the landing site, but there are also some other lamps distributed
around in the environment. So the robot cannot be 100% sure that when
it sees a lamp or when the brightness sensor triggers that it is actually above the landing site.
So to formalize this problem now a little bit, assume that we have a binary sensor that
gives us a reading either of that it detected brightness bellow it or nor.
And furthermore, our world state is also quite simple, we are only interested in this binary
variable x. Whether we are at home above the landing site or we are not.
And now we can specify a sensor model where we specify the probability of detecting brightness
when we are above the landing site. And for that we could for example determine
experimentally that the brightness sensor triggers above the landing site at a
probability of 60%. And by flying around at other places we might furthermore measure
that the brightness sensor also occasionally detects brightness when we are not above the landing site.
And this value could be specified to 30%.
And as you can see, if you build up a sensor model like this, this is now a causal sensor model
because being at home or being above the landing site causes the sensor to trigger or not to trigger,
is quite easy to construct or to measure also empirically, we could just fly with the robot or hold
the quadrotor above the landing site, and then measure how often it actually detects
the brightness.
Furthermore, we need to define a prior on our world state, if we don't have any preference,
if we are 50-50, so to speak, whether we are above the landing zone or not we could set
this probability to 0.5.
And now, let's furthermore assume that the robot actually observes light, so z equals bright.
And now, we would like to know what the probability
is, given the sensor model and our prior that we are actually above the landing site given
given that the brightness sensor has triggered.
And as you can see from the simple example already, it's not straight forward to tell
the result because the sensor model goes in the wrong direction. And now, we need this diagnostic
reasoning to determine the world state from our sensor readings.
But fortunately, of course we are aware of Bayes rule, so we can use Bayes rule now to reverse our
causal knowledge, just by filling in now the variable names
in Bayes rule we obtain the equation in the middle. And now the only thing that is new
is actually the denominator, where we already filled in the normalization constant which always can be
computed just by summing up over all possible values of our world state.
And if we then fill in the values and compare it. We find that after making this observation
that light was detected bellow the quadrotor,
then the probability of being above the landing spot increases from 0.5 to 0.67 which is considerably
higher but it might not be confident enough to actually trigger a landing behavior.
So now let's suppose that our robot obtains another observation just to verify or to consolidate
its hypothesis that it is might be above the landing spot.
And this second observation could now come from the same sensor, just taken a view seconds
later or it could come from a completely different sensor.
And then, the question is: how can we integrate this new information in our probability estimate
or in our estimate of the world state?
So more generally, how can we actually estimate the probability in which world state we are,
given that we made a sequence of observations z_1 to z_n with our sensors?
And for that we can now use Bayes formula with background knowledge that we've seen
in the previous video. Remember that when we want to apply Bayes rule in a setting where
we have background knowledge, then we can just keep this background knowledge always
on the right side of the bar.
So when we apply this Bayes rule now with background knowledge we obtain this relatively large
term in the upper right. And now let's first look at the data likelihood
that we would now have to evaluate. So this says that we need the likelihood of making
a sensor observation z_n given the world state and the values of all our other sensors.
And this probability or this likelihood might not be easy to construct because for that
we would have to know how all the individual  sensors interact with each other. And how
they interact with the world state and that is not easy to specify.
But we can make a reasonable assumption here, which is the so called Markov assumption.
And the Markov assumption says that the sensor measurement at time step n is independent
of all previous sensor measurements as long as we know the world state x.
So it doesn't matter at all what all the other sensors measure as long we know what the world
state is. We can make a prediction using the sensor model what our sensor will tell us.
And this now simplifies a little bit the expression from above.
We can strip of this whole dependency on z_1 to z_(n-1) by applying the Markov assumption,
but still this other two terms still remain and give us a hard time.
But then, we remember that we can apply this trick with the law of total probability in
the denominator, so instead of computing this prior probability of a certain sensor reading
we can just replace it by a normalization constant and then say that we postpone this
normalization until the end because we know that this probability distribution over the
world state, our posterior probability distribution over the world state, has to sum to 1 at the
end because it needs to be a proper probability distribution.
And now, we still have one complicated term here on the right side the probability of
x given the sensor measurements of z_1 to z_(n-1). But now it becomes apparent that
this is actually the same as what we have started in the beginning. Just that we have
already removed now the latest sensor observation z_n.
So we could just apply again this principle Bayes rule recursively and this gives us then
a very neat expression as we see in the last line. So when we apply n times Bayes rule
then we obtain n normalization constants, but in principle that doesn't matter to us
because we, anyway, normalize then at the very end. And then, we take the product over all the
individual sensor models for the i'th sensor and only at the very end we need to multiply
with our prior probability of what we thought in which world state we are in the first place.
So now let's apply this to our toy example here. Again the quadrotor seeks for the landing
zone. It has detected the bright lamps below it but now let's assume that it has a second
sensor with which it can actually detect a visual marker, like this letter H for example
below the quadrotor, which gives a very strong indication whether or not we are at the landing site.
And for this marker again we can specify a causal sensor model.
So we can for example say that this sensor gives us a detection in 80% of the cases when
we are above the landing site. And it also gives us false-positives at a rate of 10%
if we are not above the landing site. And remember from out previous example we computed
a likelihood or probability of 67% that we think that we are above the landing site given that
we have observed the lights. So now let's assume that the robot does not
observe the visual marker bellow it and we get a second observation Z_2 that equals not marker.
And now the question is, what is the probability of being home now that we have obtained the
second sensor measurement? And now we can either apply this recursive Bayes rule from
the last slide or we can just apply Bayes rule once more and reuse the values that we
have already computed.
So by doing that and filling in the values we now obtain a probability of 31% after we have not observed
this visual marker.
And you can see that this second observation outweighs the first observation by a lot, which mostly
comes from the fact that this sensor  is much more specific which is reflected in
the probabilities stored in the sensor model.
And now, the second part as we said in the beginning or the second source of information
that we have are our actions and controls that we give to the motors. Those actions
of course also lead to changes in the world state, just because for example if we fly forward,
then obviously the position of the quadrotor changes and the position is most likely part
of our world state that we try to model.
But of course, other parts of the world state might also change that are not under our control
for example other agents or other quadrotors might move as well, there might be humans or other
things that are going on that have influence on the world state.
And even if we don't have other agents in the world the world state might change over
time because it has an intrinsic dynamics for example.
And now in any case the question is how can we incorporate the actions, and in particular
those actions that we are aware of, so to speak our own actions that we have send to
the motors.
So the typical actions that a quadrotor does is obviously to change the speed of its motors
which leads to a change in pitch and roll, and thrust, and so on.
But it's also important to know that even then the world state and in particular the
position of the quadrotor changes when the quadrotor does seemingly nothing, just because
the quadrotor is always in motion and so it will always drift and shake even if you see
to do nothing.
The other interesting observation here is that the actions are actually never carried
out with absolute certainty, so even if we specify to fly one meter forward we cannot
be sure that we actually ending up at the position of plus one meter.
So it is important to realize that actions generally lead to an increase of the uncertainty of
the state estimate. While measurements from sensors generally decrease the uncertainty
because we know better and better the more sensor observations we take where we actually are.
So as we said before to model the relationship between the world state and the actions we
need a motion model or an action model.
And this can be specified using conditional probability density functions where the new
state x' depends on our previous state x and the issued control command u.
So to illustrate this here with a simple example, consider the following toy example.
Imagine that we have a quadrotor and it can only execute a single action namely to takeoff. And for
some reasons we are only interested in a very small part of the world state namely whether
the quadrotor is on the ground or in the air.
And then, we can model that using a so called transition diagram as depicted here on the
slide. So the notes here correspond to the different
world states. So we have two notes, ground and air, and we have some arrows in between. Those
arrows indicate the transition probabilities between these states according to a certain
action. So when we are for example located on the
ground and we execute the takeoff command then with a probability of 90% the quadrotor
will actually takeoff but with a probability of 10% it will still stay on the ground. This
could have various reasons. For example, it might not receive this command
because the wireless connection is temporarily blocked or the battery might be empty. But
in principle you can consider all of this as being noise. And different states of the
world might have a different noise behavior in this motion model.
And then, once the quadrotor is in the air it will stay in the air with 99% probability,
but even then occasionally it will end up on the ground again for example because it runs out of battery.
And now, for actually estimating the world state based on the actions that we have issued
we use the following formula. The problem again is of course is that we want to estimate the
probability of the world state, given that we execute a certain command u.
And we cannot read this out from this motion model directly because we don't know what
the previous world state was. But as you know always when we are uncertain about the world
state we can just integrate over all possible world states or sum over all possible world
states x, and then, multiply the motion model with the prior probability with what we thought
that we are in this state.
And of course this applies both to the discrete case as this previous example, as well
to the continuous case when we are dealing with continuous positions in 2D or 3D.
So to illustrate this once more for the takeoff example: imagine that our prior belief
on the robot state is that the robot is located on the ground.
So P(x = ground) is 1, and then, the robot executes a takeoff action once. And then,
we are interested in computing the probability of the robot being still on the ground after
this action.
And we do this by filling in values by applying this formula from before and then filling
in values. And we see, we can confirm now algorithmically that the robot will still
be on the ground with a probability of 10%.
This summarizes this video. We've looked at the Bayes rule, today at the
derivation of the Bayes rule. And then, we have shown with various examples
how we can use the Bayes rule to actually fuse data from multiple sensor observations
into our state estimate. And how we can use the actions and motion
commands that we have issued to update our belief of the current world state.
And we will need both of that next week to introduce the Bayes filter and the Kalman filter.