Hello this is video 4.3 on kinematics and dynamics.
In this video we will look at how rigid bodies behave under the influence of forces and torques
that are being applied to them. And then we will see how we can use that to
model the motion of a quadrotor depending on the thrust of its motors.
So kinematics in general describes the motion of rigid bodies. Typically you can describe
the state of rigid body then in classical mechanics by its position in space, by its current velocity,
and by its acceleration. And then you can find very simple rules. You know
that if you integrate up acceleration you get the velocity.
If you integrate velocity you get position.
And just to immediately give you an example how this might look like: imagine that we
are looking at a rigid body that is living in a 1 dimensional world. So we can describe
its position just by using a scalar x, describing its position in space.
We can describe its speed also by a single scalar x dot,
and then, its current acceleration by x double dot.
And then, we can apply an action. To add that in our example, now just changes are being added to the acceleration
of this object. And we need a time constant delta t that tells us how much time passes
by form one moment to the next.
And given that we can specify a linear process model that tells us how we can evolve our
state from time step t-1 to time step t. And you have probably seen that before you can
say that the current position equals the previous position plus delta t times our current speed.
This is the first row of this system matrix, in the second row we have the relationship
that the current speed depends on the previous speed plus delta t times our current acceleration.
And we just keep the acceleration the same as long as nothing else happens. And then,
to this state we add our control input u. Just by this simple vector 0,0,1, which just means
that we add the action to our acceleration. And using that you can already get a simple dynamical
system of an object that floats in 1 dimensional space.
Now dynamics is the theory that relates forces and torques to such accelerations, as you
might know from school: forces induce a linear acceleration on the body, while torques induce
an angular acceleration. You can say that a torque is the turning-force that makes something turn.
Let's start with forces first, a force can be represented by a vector and they can be
summed up. So if you for example apply two forces to
this soccer ball here in x and y direction, then this corresponds exactly to the force as if you
would have applied a force along this diagonal line F_x + F_y.
And the force that you apply to an object directly relates to the acceleration that
this object perceives. And this acceleration then also depends on
the mass of the object, so a heavier object is more difficult of course to be accelerated
or to be moved.
A torque you can say, loosely speaking, is the turning-force.
So if you have a lever arm that you try to move you can apply a force on one side
and that will induce then a torque on the rotation axis.
And this torque that is generated depends on two things: it depends on the force of
course, the more force you apply to a lever arm the more torque you get. And then again,
it depends on the distance of the place where you apply the force and the rotation center
which is denoted here in this graphics by r.
And as before, it also depends on the mass or the mass distribution on the object, which
is typically captured by this inertial matrix J here that then relates the torque to the
angular acceleration, here denoted by bold alpha.
And now let's see how this translate to quadrotors. As you have seen before, the quadrotor consists
of 4 propellers, and every propeller generates some thrust. And this induces a certain force,
so we have now 4 sources of force that push the quadrotor up.
And we have the gravitational force that pulls the quadrotor down at the same time.
And if we count all of this forces together in the vertical case then the quadrotor hovers
exactly in place, if the thrust forces of all for rotors exactly match the gravitational
force that pulls it down again.
And at the same time, every propeller also induces the torque, which is the counter torque
that's generated by the propellers moving the air.
And we have to make sure that all of this torques actually sum to 0, in order not to get any motion.
So this graphics shows again, now if we want to hover in place all of the 4 forces have
to equal the gravitational force, if it's larger, then we actually accelerate to the
top.
So the resulting force is the force that is being applied to the body of the quadrotor.
Now if we turn the quadrotor slightly, then this thrust force is not in a line any more
with the gravitation. And this means that we can separate this resulting force from the motor thrust
into a vertical component F_z that compensates then for the gravity or that has to compensate
for the gravity if you want to keep the same position. And an x and y component that actually
makes the quadrotor go forward or sideways.
And because all of these forces are actually vectors, we have to transform the thrust vector
into the global coordinate system by using for example a rotation matrix to be able to
compute the acceleration in global coordinates.
Then if we want to change the attitude of our quadrotor, we can bring the motors into
a mode where the two opposite motors produce  a unequal thrust, and this then induces a
certain torque around the rotation axis or the center of the mass of the quadrotor.
And again, by the formula from a few slides before we can then compute the resulting torque and that leads giving
that inertial matrix J to a certain induced angular acceleration alpha.
And then for rotating around the vertical axis we can also modulate the speeds of the
rotors in such a way that the sum of the torques does not equals 0 any more, but the left
turning motors are turning faster than the right turning ones for example. And that
induces the torque on the overall system.
So this already summarizes this video, we have looked at rigid body kinematics. Just
remember that every rigid body can be described using its position, velocity, and acceleration.
And then we looked at what accelerations forces and torques actually produce.
And then, we just applied that to quadrotors because this is what we need.