Welcome back everybody to lecture video 6.1 This week we will look at filters in general.
And now in this first video we will look at the Bayes filter, which is a direct extension
of what we have seen last week with the application of the Bayes rule.
So one assumption that we already made last week is the so called Markov assumption.
It states that the observations only depend on the current state,
so if we have an expression like this that we want to infer the likelihood that we make a certain
sensor measurement, given the hole sequence of previous world states and previous sensor
measurements, potentially previous motion commands. Then we can actually collapse that into
the very simple expression of the probability of the sensor measurement, given our current
world state. And furthermore, the Markov assumption also
says that the current state only depends on the previous state and the current action that
we have issued. And these two assumptions are called the Markov
assumptions and they strongly simplify the dependencies between these individual random
variables. A different way of drawing that is in such
a process diagram or a Bayesian network as it is also called.
Here the nodes correspond to random variables and arrows in between two random variables
represent dependency between to random variables, so for example here in the middle x_t depends
on u_t because it has an arrow in between but it also depends on the previous state x_(t-1).
And the sensor observations z_t for example only depends on the world state x_t.
And this is now a temporary process because in
every time step we have a world state variable x_t, we have a motion command u_t, and we
have a sensor observation z_t. And something like this is called a temporal process
because the individual notes are actually random variables this is a so called stochastic process.
And this is the model that lies behind many
of the filters that we will see this week. So the underlying assumptions of the Markov
filter or the Markov assumption are that we are actually living in a static world so if
things are not influenced by an action that we are actually giving or that we are model in
this vector u, then we assume that everything else stays the same.
Furthermore, we assume that the noise that we have on our sensors is completely independent
because if this noise would be dependent on each other then we would need additional arrows
in between the noise variables And furthermore, we assume that our model
is perfect and that we don't have any approximation errors that again might violate this independence assumption.
So and this now is the basis for the Bayes
filter. The idea is as follows, we again have a robot
for example that goes around and takes a sequence of observations z_1 to z_t and during that
it issues a sequence of actions or motion commands u_1 to u_t.
And it is also equipped with two models namely a sensor model that describes the mapping between
how likely sensor readings are given that we are in a certain world state.
And we have an action model or motion model that describes how our actions influence the
world state. And we generally assume that we are given
a prior probability of the system state that is denoted by P(x).
So if you have to build a system like this and don't know what's a good initialization
for your prior is, then typically it's a good idea then to have a very brought prior, for example
a uniformly or almost uniformly distributes your belief mass.
And from these assumptions here or from this input we want to compute the world state of
the dynamic system at all times from t_1 to t_t, to the end or the current time step.
And this probability then, so that's the probability of x_t given the sequence of sensor observations
from time step 1 to time step t is also called the belief.
Instead of writing down P(x) given all this sensor input sometimes we just write the belief
of x at time step t. And now the Bayes filter algorithm works as
follows. We first integrate the motion command that we have issued into our belief and create
a second or temporarily belief value Bel bar. And we do that by applying the motion model
as before, as we have seen last week. And because we don't really know what the
world state is or what the world state was at t-1 we have to integrate or sum up over
all possible world states at this time step to make sure that we model the uncertainty that we had
in our previous belief correctly. And then, in the second step we update this
belief again using the senor model. And as you remember we had this denominator
here actually where we had to divide by the prior on sensor measurements, which was hard
to compute and so instead we typically just add this normalization constant here that
we compute afterwards by making sure that the belief distribution is a proper distribution,
which means that it has to sum to 1 at the end of the day.
It should be noted here that the Bayes filter also works on continuous states, so in this
case you can just replace the sum in this equation by an integral and also the Bayes
filter works although we now have here two separate steps.
It can also work if you have much more actions for example or if they are not in sync anymore.
So you can run these two steps independently depending on how often you get a motion or
sensor updates. And now, I thought that it might be very helpful
to immediately give a good example or an intuitive example how this could look like.
And I do that with the so called histogram filter or grid filter as it is also called.
The goal here is that we want to localize a robot that is moving in such a grid world.
We represent the world state by a state variable x that has two coordinates, so it is a 2 dimensional
state space where the first coordinate reflects the x position and the second coordinate reflects the
y position. And we now have a belief distribution that
we can visualize here as a grid as well. And the brightness now of every cell encodes
how likely it is that the robot is located in one of this cells.
And white means that is very unlikely, so a probability of 0.
And black would mean absolute certainty that the robot is at a certain place.
And now using such a grid we can easily model uncertainty.
So for example, if we think that the robot is located here at this grayish cell but it
might also be in one of its neighbor cells. Then we can use different shades of gray to
indicate this uncertainty. Furthermore, we assume that this robot can
move around, it can issue one of four motion commands: it can go north, east, south, west
and the robot can move exactly one cell in each time step.
And we furthermore assume that the actions are not perfectly executed by sometimes it
happens that the robot does not get to where it actually wants to.
For example, if it wants to move to the right, even when it was perfectly certain that it
was in a certain cell. After issuing this motion command it would only be certain to a certain degree
still that it ended up in this right cell and with a smaller possibility it would end
up in one of the neighboring cells. So in our model we would say that it has a
success rate of 60% to end up in the cell that it wants, and there is a likelihood of
10% that it moves to far or to close or it moves one cell up or down.
And then we add a special marker to one particular cell.
Or we have a special sensor that can sense a marker that is located in one of the cells.
And then, the robot while it is going around can sense this marker. You can think of that
as for example, this brightness of these lamps from the landing site that we had earlier.
And because everything is a bit noisy it might happen that the robot also detects the marker
when it is one of the adjacent cells. Now let's do a simulation run, please forgive
me that the shades are not perfectly reflecting the likelihoods because everything is hand
drawn and not exact, but in the next video when we do the same with the Kalman filter
you can see real probabilities being computed by a program.
So this is our initial state we assume in this case now that we are perfectly certain
of our world state. So we know that the robot is located exactly
at this black cell here in the middle. And it now issues a motion command it goes
to the east and for that we have to apply the first step of the Bayes filter.
So we apply the motion model to our belief state, which means that we take the old belief
state as input and convolve it with our motion model. This will then lead to this blurred
belief state on the right, where we are pretty certain that we actually moved to the right.
But with a small probability it might also have happened that we moved
in one of the adjacent cells. Now, we apply the second step of the Bayes
filter. We apply the observation model. Our sensor reported that it hasn't detected
a marker, so that doesn't change a lot but actually in the cell that is next
to the marker actually gets a slightly low probability because we would have expected
that if we are close to the marker that there is a certain residual probability that we
see this marker also from the adjacent cell. Now we walk again, in the next time step we
again walked to the right. So we apply Bayes filter step 1, the motion
model. And this shifts the whole probability distribution
now a little bit to the right but it again blurs it because our motions are quite inaccurate.
And the result is shown in the grid on the right.
And now we apply again Bayes filter step 2, we apply the observation model and in this
case we now assume that the robot has observed the marker and so we update our current belief
using the sensor model. And this then results in the following distribution,
so the most likely cell is now one cell to the left of the marker, but there is also
a considerable probability mass on the cell with the marker.
And now the question would be: what do should the robot think where it is?
And now you might be tempted to say: well obviously the darkest cell is the one, left
of the marker. But there is actually no easy way of extracting
or specifying now the discrete location of the robot.
It is a probability distribution, you can always say the most likely cell is the cell left of the
marker, but in principle we can't know. It's either somewhere in between these two cells.
So to summarize this video, we have introduced
the Markov assumption that enables us to run very efficient recursive Bayesian updates
on the belief distribution. It's a very useful tool for estimating the state for a dynamic
system and it forms the basis of many other filters.
In particular the Kalman filter that we will now finally look at in the next video.
But also other filters like the particle filter, hidden Markov models, dynamic Bayesian networks,
and partially observable Markov decision processes for example and many other tool in statistics.