Hello.
And welcome back to the third part of the first lecture
on autonomous navigation for flying robots.
In this video, I will explain what
it is that makes a quadrotor hover at a certain position,
and what motion commands you have to give to the motors
to make it move in a particular direction.
So as you know, a quadrotor consists of four rotor blades.
And each of these rotors actually
produces a certain air flow and in turn an acceleration force
onto the body of the quadrotor.
And so if you fire up all the four motors at a certain speed,
then you can take off.
And if the thrust of all the four motors
combined together exactly compensates for earth gravity,
than the quadrotor will vertically stay in place.
The second thing is that you have to make sure
that the torques of all the four motors sum exactly to zero,
because if you're not doing that, if say all the four
rotors would rotate in the same direction,
then that would induce a contour-torque that would start
to rotate the quadrotor around it's yaw axis.
And this is physically implemented
as follows on a quadrotor.
You always have two motors, the opposing motors mounted
on the same arm that are rotating in the same direction,
and two rotors, the other two motors rotate
in the opposite direction.
And in this way, the torque of all the four rotors
sums to zero while the trust compensates for earth gravity
in hovering mode.
Now for ascending, you can just increase equally the speed
of all four motors and it will slowly move up your quadrotor.
On the other hand, if you reduce the speed equally of all four
motors, then you will reduce the overall thrust.
And that will bring down your quadrotor again.
Now as I said, for keeping the orientation,
it is important that the torques of all four motors
sum exactly to zero.
However, you can also use this principle
for inducing a certain rotation.
For example, if you want to make the quadrotor turn to the left,
you would increase the speed of the clockwise motors,
the right-turning quadrotors, that will then
lead to an induction of a torque that
will move the quadrotor to the left, that
will turn the quadrotor to the left.
On the other hand, if you want to turn right,
then you would increase the speed
of the left-rotating motors and decrease
the speed of the right-rotating motors.
Of course, you have to make sure that if you
want to keep your vertical position,
that the overall thrust of the four motors
exactly equals earth gravity.
Now for moving forward-- so forward in this schematic
here is the up direction.
If you want to move forward, you can do as follows.
You reduce the speed of your front motor
and increase the speed of your back motor.
And in this way, the quadrotor will tilt forward.
And in this way, the thrust is no longer perfectly aligned
with earth gravity, but it's slightly out of the axis.
And that will lead to an acceleration,
then, in the forward direction.
Similarly, if you want to fly backwards,
you would increase the speed of the front motor
and reduce the speed of the back motor.
And that will turn your quadrotor,
change the attitude of your quadrotor to the back,
and the again lead to an acceleration,
to a horizontal acceleration of your quadrotor.
Similarly, you can also move to the left
and to the right with the same principle.
And of course, you can also combine all of these motions
at the same time, for example to move to the left
and at the same time rotate to the left
to ascend and rotate and so on.
Good.
So this now brings us to our first and most
important platform.
As I said before, we will use the Parrot Ardrone
as the example model throughout this course.
If you happen to have one, you can also run all the exercises
then on the Parrot Ardrone.
But before we switch to the simulator,
it's also interesting to look a little bit more
at the hardware side of things.
So it consists obviously of four motors.
Those are so-called brushless motors.
Next week, we will look more at how brushless motors work.
They have a nominal power consumption of 14.5 watts,
so the overall quadrotor pulls around 60 to 80 watts,
with some loss there.
Every motor has its own motor controller
that runs a small CPU that controls the motor speed.
And there is a strong lithium polymer battery included
that powers the quadrotor between 10 to 15 minutes.
And the battery sits in the middle of the quadrotor.
Good.
We've also looked already a little bit at the sensors.
Here are more technical specs.
So we have an integrated inertial measurement unit inside
of the quadrotor that consists of a three-axis gyroscope,
a three-axis accelerometer, and a compass, or a magnetometer.
We'll also see next week more or what that means
and what the sensing principle of that is.
We have an ultrasound sensor to measure the distance
to the floor and additionally, a pressure sensor
that can be used whenever the ultrasound sensor doesn't
work anymore.
So ultrasound only has a range of maybe three meters or so.
So if you fly higher, especially outdoors,
ultrasound is not very useful.
But you can measure the air pressure.
And that then again tells you about your flying height.
There is also a visual odometry sensor
that is actually a camera running
at 60 frames per second.
We will also use the images from this camera
in the remainder of this course for tracking the position
visually of the quadrotor.
And there is a front camera at HD resolution
that we can also access from the PC.
So at the core of the Parrot Ardrone,
we have a full Linux system running,
consisting of a Cortex A8 processor running
at one gigahertz.
You can log into that system just
by telnetting to this computer.
It also has a USB2 host adapter in it
so you can add additional memory for recording videos,
for example, or a GPS module.
There are also hackers out there who
added attached completely different hardware to that.
And it carries a wireless network adapter,
with which we can communicate when
the quadrocopter is in the air.
And a good thing and that makes it so attractive
for us is that the API is fully open source, so it
is possible to communicate with the quadrotor
and get all of this sensor data and send back
motion commands to the quadrotor.
Next to the Parrot Ardrone, there
are also many other platforms currently available.
I've shown here a few that we also have in our lab,
although I have to say that the Parrot Ardrone is
by far the most popular among our students.
We also an Ascending Technologies Pelican
quadrocopter.
That's the one here shown in the top right.
It's slightly larger than the Ardrone.
It weighs around one kilogram.
And the good thing there is that we have a full computer there
and actually a Core 2 Duo processor running Ubuntu.
And we also have several USB plugs
so we can add additional sensors,
like a camera here on the top or an RGBD camera
like the Asus sensor here at the front of the quadrotor.
AscTec sells different other platforms,
like the Hummingbird that is quite
popular in Vijay Kumar's lab,
but also the Firefly, which is their new model, which
has six propellers instead of four.
Another very interesting platform
is the Crazyflie nanocopter.
It's much smaller than the other ones.
But it's also more difficult, then, to extend,
so the camera that we are mounting on it
only weighs four grams.
And this makes, of course, life much harder
if you have to use such a small and lightweight camera.
There are also a whole bunch of open source
and community-based projects, like the Mikrokopter,
for example.
You can buy the parts from their website.
But you can also get them from an electronics market
and essentially build it all by yourself.
So this now already brings us to the next interactive exercise,
where you can test your understanding of the flight
principle.
We've implemented a web-based quadrotor simulator.
And you can program it in Python.
And we now want you to use this simulator
to make the quadrotor to move in a particular direction.
So that means for the moment we assume
that we have absolutely no noise, so the quadrotor will
exactly follow our commands.
But so you need to specify a sequence of motor commands
that will make the quadrotor ascend and descend
and then fly forward and fly left.
And you can also find combinations of these motor
commands to make the quadrotor follow
a certain pre-specified path.
Of course, this is done completely without sensor data,
so we're flying completely blindly
through the environment.
But nevertheless, we thought that this gives you
a good understanding of the flight dynamics of a quadrotor
and that will then form a good basis
for the remainder of this course.
So have fun doing this exercise.
And then see you back for the last exercise this week
where I'll briefly outline the history of quadrotors
in general and in research.