Hello and welcome everybody again to Autonomous Navigation for Flying Robots.
In this video we will look at motors that are typically used in quadrotors and suitable
motor controllers that generate signals to make the motors swing at a particular rate.
A very simple motor is the so called DC motor. It just consists of two things, namely the
stationary magnet on the outside, and then an  electromagnet on the axis that is able to spin.
The electromagnet, when it is switched on, uses a magnetic field. And that in turn uses a
torque on the axis, and this makes the axis spin. To align the magnetic field of the electro
magnets with the permanent magnet on the outside.
But then this motion comes to a rest as soon as the magnets are aligned. And when this
happens typically a split ring changes the direction of the current such that the motion
of the motor continues.
The principle is very simple, which means that you can easily build one yourself, maybe
you already build one at school, as visualized here in the middle image.
Also the advantage of DC motors is that you can make them super small so that they are
really suited well for nano-quadrotors like the CrazyFlie depicted on the right.
To control the speed of a DC motor you have to adjust the power. So if you give more voltage
to the motor it will start spinning faster, and if you reduce the voltage then the rotation will slow down.
But the problem of course is that we have a micro controller or a computer
from which we want to specify the motor speed. So the question is how can we actually modulate the
power using a digital signal?
And then, a common approach that is implemented in hardware in most micro controllers is the
so called pulse width modulation, also abbreviated as PWM.
And there the idea is that you have a digital signal that you switch on and off very quickly
at a certain frequency.
And then the amount of time that the signal is switched on during this period is called the
duty cycle. And the larger this duty cycle is, with respect
to the full period, the more power you actually transmit.
So for example, if the duty cycle is 0 then you do not power at all the motor. If the
duty cycle is during the whole period, then you would power it at full speed.
You can continuously smoothly change this duty cycle and in this way regulate the speed
or the output power for the motor.
Of course this digital signal then needs to be amplified using a MOSFET. For example,
to actually generate the high current that you need for powering the motors.
An alternative to DC motors are the so called brushless motors. There you have the electro
magnets on the outside and they are stationary. And then you have permanent magnets on the
axis, and this axis can either be in between the coils or outside around the coils.
We need at least three coils for building a brushless motor. But most brushless motors
used in practice have much more, as you can see here in the images.
The advantage of brushless motor is that you don't have brushes, you don't need a split
ring to reverse the current. And that means that motors need less maintenance
you never need to replace the brushes there is less mechanics.
And also the efficiency is much higher because you can regulate better the power that you
give to the electro magnets.
The brushless controller is a little bit more complicated than a controller for a DC motor
you need some electronics. But before we go into the details, let's first
have a look at the wiring scheme of such a brushless motor, shown here on bottom left.
Typically the three coils that you have are connected to three pols A, B and C. And then
the other side of the coil is soldered together between all coils.
And then, you setting a certain current between two coils, for example between A and B or
between B and C. And you setting an AC signal there and the
signal between these pairs of coils is shifted by 120 degrees. And that induces a rotary
magnetic field then on the coils and that will make the axes of the brushless motor spin
at the frequency of these three signals.
And so you need to have a micro controller that is able to generate such phases at the
desired speed. And for that you typically need a micro controller that then outputs
a PWM signal again for the three motor phases.
Now, in this case it's again possible to convert this PWM signal using an AC converter, just
consisting of a capacitor and a MOSFET chip to improve the power output because the micro controller
can't power directly the motor of course or the electro magnets.
So you run then to an AC converter and that gives you then an analog output. And that
are the three phases for the motor.
You can buy such motor controllers very cheaply, here in this picture on the right you can
see such a controller. It's very small, it gets the power from the
battery with the two thick red and black cables. And it then outputs the three motor phases in the left.
And for actually reading in the signal you have the small thin cable that goes then to
the autopilot board of the quadrotor.
On interesting thing is that you can actually
measure the position and the speed of the motor by evaluating the electromagnetic response
on this three motor phases and in this way the motor controller can tell you whether
the motor got stuck or whether it's rotating at the right speed. And of course you can also
use that to achieve the exactly desired rotation speed.
So to communicate with the autopilot board, you could again use the PWM signal. But it's
even more efficient to have a micro controller for the motor controller and you have a PC
or again a micro controller for the autopilot. So a digital protocol is more efficient.
And then one protocol that is used a lot is the I^2C-Protocol, which is just a serial
connection, a parallel bus. The cool thing is you can connect all motors then to the
same I^2C bus. The individual slaves are addressed using
an address and you can transmit at really high speeds.
This is typically used as I said to communicate the motor speed from the autopilot board to
the motor controller. And the actual motor speed or the actual motor properties are
send back to the autopilot.
Just to fill that in with a nice example, this is now taken from the Parrot ArDrone,
but you can find similar constructions on other quadrotors as well.
This is the motor board or the motor component of the ArDrone. It consists of the brushless
motor of course. On the inside the motors has three cables coming out of it
for the three motor phases. And these phases are driven by the AC converters,
those are the three chips here on the right. And then there is a small AVR CPU, this is
for the micro controller that generates the PWM signal for the AC converters.
And then the motor is not driving the propeller directly on the ArDrone, but there is a small
gear in between. Other quadrotors directly drive the propellers, so this depends a little
bit on the speed and the power of the motor that you are building into.
So to summarize the lesson learned today in this video.
We've looked at DC motors that are used on some quadrotors and brushless motors that
are typically used on larger quadrotors. We've looked at the corresponding motor controllers.
And we've looked at the ArDrone implementation of the motor controllers.
In the next video we will look at methods for generating suitable control signals, because
now the question is, what motor speed do we actually want for each of the four motors?
And even at a higher level, what attitude do we want and what velocities do we want
of the whole quadrotor?