Hello and welcome to video 4.4 on PID-Control.
In the previous video we have seen how we can model the rigid body kinematics of a rigid body.
And we will use that again now for bringing on our example from P-Control before.
So consider just a simple rigid body like the soccer ball here that is free floating
in 1 dimensional space, without any gravity.
This means that the body itself is located at a certain location x and it's moving
in a certain direction x dot.
And so we can specify a really simple system model, where we just say: the current position
depends on the previous position plus the current speed. With that we assume that our
time constant delta t equals 1.
And now assume that you are starting at the origin. So our current position is 0, and
also our current speed is 0.
And then, if we look at the time evolution of such a system we can see that nothing
changes because in every new time step we just add 0 + 0.
And that means that our object, will stay exactly at the same point.
Now imagine further that we can now apply at every time instant a certain force F_t.
And just for simplicity we assume that this force is our control, u, maybe scaled by some factor.
As we now, this force that we apply leads
to an acceleration, x double dot, and imagine now that we want to find controls so that
the rigid body moves to a desired location of 1.
And now, as we already know, we could just apply P-control to that, which means that
the desired location x_des minus our current location x_(t-1) from the last time step.
And then, we multiply that by a certain control gain K to obtain our control signal.
Now what will happen if we apply this to a rigid body?
And then, the result looks as follows: we start again now at the origin of our object,
and we want to go to a location of 1. So our P-controller will generate a large control,
in this case of 0.15, because we have set K to 0.15, which will make the object accelerate
towards its desired location and then roughly at 4 seconds time we will hit the desired
location. But because we still have some inertia the object will continue beyond this point and actually
overshoot massively up to a position of 2. And then, during this time already our controller
will generate a negative control output to decelerate the object
and you can see that this leads to a very bad oscillation. And actually does not make
our object come closer to the desired location.
So this is not good, P-controls for rigid bodies that are not damped are not sufficient.
The idea is now to use a so called derivative term, so we have a so called PD-controller then,
where the first part is exactly the same and the second part at the same time tries to
minimize the distance between the desired speed that we try to achieve and our current speed.
And this now means that at this location of 1 we desired to have a speed of 0 so our x dot desired
equals 0 to make sure that at the end, when we reach this goal, we want to have 0 velocity.
And then, this leads to the following behavior: you can see now in the bottom plot we still
have a proportional part that will accelerate our body to what's the desired location.
And we have the blue line that shows the differential part now that immediately decelerates our
body but at a smaller overall rate and this will lead to the nice behavior that we've see
in the first plot with the red line that moves towards our desired location, but slows
down before it actually hits it.
And so you might wonder now, what would happen if we set lower gains for this differential part?
And then, we get again this behavior that
we have seen before, so the red line overshoots now to our desired location, because the slowing
down is not strong enough. On the other hand, if we set higher gains for the differential
part we end up with the following behavior: it still approaches the desired location
nicely, but it takes extremely long like 25 seconds in this example and it could be much faster.
So this K_D can also lead to a slower convergence then in the end.
Now let's consider the following, before we've just lived in three floating in space, but what
would happen if we add gravity to our system?
So imagine that next to our controller force F that we generate we add this gravitational
constant that accelerates our mass with a certain force.
And then, the effect is as follows: we start at 0, again we want to go to 1, but then, the funny thing
is the object falls down roughly to 60 meters.
And after say 20 seconds or so the PD-control generates sufficiently strong control signals to actually
make the object not fall down any further. But this is obviously not what we want, so
this would be the case if you just use PD-control without gravity compensation.
Then, the quadrotor would never reach its desired location.
So what you can do then in such a case is to add an additional term that compensates
for the gravity or for any other disturbance that you might be aware of.
So directly into our control model we can now include a term for removing this gravitational
force to compensate this gravitational force directly.
And similar to that, any other known dynamic disturbance can be removed in this way.
And then the effect is again as we have seen it before, we can go smoothly form 0 to 1,
just by directly compensating force.
The next problem now is: imagine that we have some systematic errors in our system. For
example, our joystick might not be at the right position, the motors might not be equally
strong. It could happen that one motor is a little bit weaker than another one. For
example, because it has a broken propeller or just because it doesn't run as smoothly
as another motor or it just might be a little bit unbalanced on the quadrotor or there might be some external
disturbance like wind that constantly pushes away the quadrotor in a certain direction.
And if we add something like this, in this example we have added wind from below that pushes the object upwards.
And this is now again similar to what we had before with the gravitation.
The object is now approaching this desired location  of 1 but it overshoots and it converges on a
value that is not our desired value.  So it converges here on say 1.3 maybe. And on this location the PD-controller generates
enough control output to not deviate any further from our desired value but as you can see
it does no converge on our desired value. So the questions is: how can we deal with
such systematic errors, how can we extend our controller to deal with something like this?
And the answer now is to estimate this bias term by integrating over all errors that we
had before from the very beginning to the current time step.
And this is then called a so called integral term, which you can see here on the right.
We again have a coefficient or a gain for the integral term, here denoted by K_I, and this term will
build up and then compensate for such errors. So in the example that we have seen before, again
we get some overshooting because initially this integral term is 0 so the algorithm doesn't
know that we have a disturbance.
But as soon as we overshoot and have observed this error this integral builds up and then
compensates for it over time and you can see that now our controller
nicely converges on the desired value.
And in the bottom plot you can now see  how these three terms actually contribute to
this behavior. So we have the bright red line corresponding
to our proportional control output, the blue line corresponding to our differential output,
and the bright green line corresponding to our systematic integral term.
So it is in general a bit tricky to use the integral term, its generally fine for
steady state systems, so systems that can actually reach their desired location and
then it is very reasonable and very good to do that. But it might also happen that you
have a system that can never reach a certain location and this might create a
so called wind-up effect, which can lead to a disaster or at least to a strong delay in you controller.
And now to see why this a problem consider the following example: imagine that we want that
the quadrotor goes to a certain location, but then on its way get stuck in a tree, so
it cannot reach the steady state. And then it is interesting to look at the
effect of this being stuck on the integral term.
And then, we see the following behavior: the quadrotor is send to a location of 10 in this
example, so it goes quickly towards this location, but roughly at the position of 5 it get stuck
in a tree. And from there on this integral term keeps building up, because it realizes that
it needs to give more power to the motors apparently to reach its goal location, but it can't because
it is stuck. And so this integral term grows larger and larger, as you can see in the bottom plot.
And if we send now the quadrotor at the time step 10 back to the origin it won't go, because
this integral term still outweighs our proportional-controller that tries to move the quadrotor back.
And this is why the integral term is sometimes a bit difficult and dangerous to be used.
Another problem of course is that we generally not only have one degree of freedom that we
try to control, but typically multiple. In case of the ArDrone we have 4 degrees of freedom
as you know, we can go forward, sideward, we can rotate, and we can change the flying height.
And this is common with many systems, this is then called a MIMO system - multiple input
multiple output. And also it would be of course nice from a
theoretical point of view to control all degrees of freedom at the same time with the same controller.
Most often these controllers are just being
decoupled, so you have 2 or 4 independent PID-controllers, each one just controlling
one degree of freedom. And then of course the plant, or the system,
that you are looking at couples all of this degrees of freedom, but as long as this coupling
is very loose it doesn't hurt to assume for the controllers that these degrees of freedom
are actually separate.
Another interesting question is then: how to choose then the coefficients? The problem
here is that if you make the gains too large, as we have seen it can easily lead to
overshooting and oscillations. However, if you make the gains to small, then it might take
a very long time to converge. Still a good heuristic is to increase your start with small gains,
and then, incrementally increase them until you see a good behavior. If you see oscillations
you know that you made them too large and so on.
There are some heuristic methods that you can follow that tell you how to tune these
parameters, but in practice people often do it just by thump. Try out different values
and finding then a parameter setting where you see a reasonable good behavior.
Of course, there are more advanced techniques and the whole field of control theory studies
these problems, but for our case and especially for the simulator that you'll be using this is completely sufficient.
Another thing is of course that we are not only having one controller typically, but
a whole sequence of controllers. For example, as you have seen before in hardware we already
have motor speed controllers at every motor of the quadrotor, which internally runs not
necessarily a PID-controller. Depends on what motor you have, if you can sense the speed,
then there is typically something like a P-controller inside. And then, on the next level on the
ArDrone for example, this happens onboard is the attitude estimation where you use the
gyroscopes and the accelerometers to estimate the orientation of the quadrotor and then
generate a suitable attitude control commands. And on top of that you might have a localization
module that you're giving the camera images or your GPS signal to compute your position.
And then, you might have a PID-controller that controls your position. And even above
this layer you might have a trajectory control that generates waypoints
to which you want to send the quadrotor. And it's important to note here:
just stack different controllers above each other. This is then called cascaded control and this works well
as long as the dynamics of the outer system are by at least a magnitude slower than the
dynamics of the internal system. So for the internal controller the set point
then appears to be static. And for the outer controller the dynamics of the internal system
are so fast that it also appears to immediately converge.
So to look at an example now, the ArDrone also uses several control loops. From our perspective
we have an inner loop that runs on the embedded PC, which controls the attitude and the speed
of the quadrotor. And then, the outer loop runs on a Laptop
and implements the position control.
And these two control loops run at different speeds, the internal loop, we don't really
know, but it probably runs at a frequency around 1 kHz. Whie the outer loop runs depending
on you wireless connection runs at approximately 15 to 20 Hz.
And there is another interesting insight, the PD-controller is actually equivalent to a spring-damper system.
So you can imagine that you have your quadrotor that's supposed to go to this desired location
and it's actually being pulled like with virtual springs towards this desired location.
And if you look very closely on this video you can see how this quadrotor moves back
to its set point. And you can see how it is being damped by the D-term of the PD-controller
and how it is being pulled towards its set point using the P-part.
This is actually a very nice demo that we have published as open source and if you have
an ArDrone at home you can just download this demo. You need a Linux computer running ROS
on it, but it is all very well described on this wiki page, so please feel free to try this out.
So to summarize the lesson of this video. We've looked now at full PID-control, remember again:
P stands for the proportional term, I stands for the integral term,
and D stands for the derivative term.
And we have seen how we can stack multiple of such controllers in a cascaded control.
And how we can decouple MIMO systems that have multiple inputs and multiple outputs.