Welcome back everybody to lecture video 8.3.
We looked before at feature based visual SLAM method in particular for navigating the ArDrone
visually. And in contrast to that we will focus in this video now on so called direct
methods for visual odometry and visual SLAM that essentially are an extension of the KLT
tracker in the 2D case to full 3D.
And to see why this is actually a good idea let's look at the following video. This is
just a video feed from the quadrotor the ArDrone here is flying through one of our offices.
And you see you get a bit shaky image, but nevertheless, as a human when you looking
at it you get a quite good understanding of how the scene looks like and you also can
imagine very well where the robot is currently looking at.
And now if we run that through a feature based visual SLAM system like PTAM. And we have
seen that PTAM works generally really well. And then, PTAM is actually only focusing on
so called feature points that have strong gradients and it rejects everything else.
And then, again suddenly not so easy any more to see how the quadrotor is moving in 3D space
and it's also not so easy at all to see how the world looks like. Because we're actually ignoring
or just not observing large parts of the world.
So when we realize that - maybe two years ago - why not focus
on methods that use more of the image data, maybe all of the available image data. And
then, we came up with the following approach and I should say here for the moment we assume
that we have a depth camera but we will relax this later on to just a normal monocular camera.
So imagine that we have such a depth camera and it's located at a particular 3D pose looking
at the world. And then this camera get moved to a second location and takes another image
of the same scene. And then, of course we would like to know what the 3D transformation
between these two camera poses is. And now, the basic idea here is to exploit the so called
photo-consistency constraint, namely if we look at a particular point in the world from
one image we can reconstruct it in 3D because we have the depth of this pixel. And then,
we can reproject that if we knew the transformation between two images we could transform this
point in the coordinate frame of the second image. And then, ideally the intensity or
the color of this pixel should exactly match the color of the first image. And this photo
consistency constrain actually holds for all pixels. And this means that in contrast to
only say maybe a 100 or 200 visual features that we're tracking. This photo consistency
constraint should hold for all pixel in the image. And even if you're only dealing with
VGA images, 640x480, this gives you 200.000 constraints or a little bit more that you
can use to estimate your 3D pose.
So of course you could say that that photo consistency constrain will never perfectly
hold for various reasons. First, the most obvious one is that we of course have sensor
noise, so even if you take two images from the same camera pose the difference image
will not be zero. Of course we might have some error in our pose estimation, so if you
take the difference there might be some scenes in the image that give non zero residuals.
There might also be a reflection and specular surfaces you know they appear in a different
color depending on the pose from where you are looking at them.
And there might be dynamic objects the world might not be static, things might disappear
or appear in the world. And all of this violates of course this photo consistency constraint.
And in sum this means that although most of the residuals will be close to zero some of
them will be not exactly zero at our optimization goal. And so if we look at the residuals and
the residual is now defined as the difference between the first image minus the warped second
image. Then this residuals will in general be non-zero.
And of course, then it makes sense to look at the distribution of this residuals. And
then, for a good camera pose in a reasonable scene we would expect that the residual is
around zero. So there should be a peak at zero and a relatively small variance in principle
according to the sensor noise of our camera. Of course, if we're not having the right camera
pose. Then the distribution of residuals is much broader because we suddenly compare the
intensities and colors of pixels that do not correspond. And then, as a result we get a
much larger residual in general and then this distribution might more look like this. So
the question then intuitively speaking is: how can we actually transform this very broad
distribution in a very peak distribution by modifying the camera pose.
And if we put this mathematically then our goal is to find a camera pose that actually
maximizes the observation likelihood of this residual distribution in the good case. So
we look at the probability every single residual given a certain camera transformation Xi then
we multiply this likelihood. If we assume that all pixels are independent that's of course
not always the case but it's a good enough approximation. So you can just multiply all
of these probabilities together and then maximize this product to find the right camera pose.
And now the question of course is how can we solve this optimization problem efficiently?
And for that we again employ the so called Gauss-Newton algorithm that you have seen
before for KLT tracking but also for signed distance functions in the previous video.
And before we apply that actually we first take the negative logarithm that just simplifies
our computations enormously because that turns the product into a sum. And now instead of
finding the maximum we can look for the minimum. And at the minimum you all know that the derivative
has to be zero there. Otherwise it would not be a minimum. So what we can do is to derive
this expression and set the derivative then to zero.
And because this a chained expression here we can apply the chain rule for derivation
and that gives us this term here in the middle where we first derive the logarithmic probability
with respect to our residuals and then we derive again the residuals with respect to
our camera motion. And then this sum is set to zero.
So one problem here is now that just using a quadratic cost term corresponds to a normal
distribution is actually not very robust. You see an illustration of that in a second.
But the good news is given that this formulation that we had before can actually plug in arbitrary
probability distributions for our residuals just by rewriting the minimization problem
as a so called least square problem. We can still minimize it as if it was a quadratic
error function. And now one problem obviously is that the residual function computes the
residuals. The difference between two images given of a particular pixel, given a 3D transformation
is not linear because we have rotations in Xi. And so, what we can do is to linearize
then the cost function or the residual function using a Taylor approximation then solve for
the minimum and then relinearize and then do the same again.
And this method is called the Gauss-Newton method for minimization.
Just to illustrate how this different cost functions look like. The normal distribution
is the most obvious one. So if you implement something like this you would always start
with a normal distribution which leads to a quadratic error function in the end. And
the disadvantage here is that large residuals give very large cost terms. And this means
that out layers on you image for example due to reflections, due to moving objects and
so on and so on, give you very large error terms and will actually push your estimate
to the wrong minimum. And so it makes actually sense to discard
pixels that has a too high residuals just because you saying these pixels are outliers
and you want to use them in our estimation. And one option then is to use Tukey weights
that just down weights an error after a certain threshold. The disadvantage there is depending
on your camera motion it could actually happen that you moving much too fast and that
everything is actually treaded as an outlier and you can't estimate your camera pose at
all because everything is considered as an outlier with zero costs and you're actually
not converting at all.
The alternative is and this is what Christian Kerl then proposed in this ICRA paper in 2013
is to apply a so called t distribution that leads to this to the cost function shown in
blue. So where we have a kind of a quadratic term
in the middle and the further we go out to the sides the more it converges towards a
certain limit. And this means that outlier pixel still have a certain weight. The algorithm
still tries to get rid of outliers as much as possible but it will not discard the images
because they are outliers.
So just to give you an example how these different images and residual images look like. Imagine
we have these two input images shown on top. Of course both of these input images have
a depth image that we are getting from Kinect or from a Kinect like sensor. And then we
can take the difference between these two images and then we are getting these edge
image, looks more or less like an edge image actually. And now you can wonder what would happen to
my residual image if I would move around a virtual camera that is looking at the point
cloud of the second image. And by moving this camera around we could move it closer to our
first input image - the pose of the first camera. And then ideally given that this photo consistency
constraint holds we would get a black image for the residuals. And now what Gauss-Newton
does is actually to linearize this residual function at our current pose estimate. So
we're computing an image Jacobian that tells us how the image changes in brightness if
we move the camera a long all six coordinate axes. So if you move it forward, backward,
left, right, up and down and if we rotate it around its three rotation axes.
And we now try to rotate it to find actually this zero residual image that we are looking
for. One problem of course of this linearization step is that it only holds for very small
camera motions. So if you're are moving by more than one pixel actually or a few pixels
then actually this linearization is not valid anymore. And so but what you can do then is
to apply a coarse-to-find scheme. You have seen that before with the KLT tracker in 2D.
You build an image pyramid and then you first match the smallest coarsest images on the
highest pyramid level. And then, you use the estimated motion to initialize again Gauss-Newton
at the next layer, find the next camera motion between those and so on and so on.
And this means that you're running maybe four or five image pyramid layers and you running
a full Gauss-Newton at every layer that takes maybe four to five iterations sometimes it
even converges quicker. And at the end you even obtain a very high accuracy camera pose estimate.
And to see how this looks like in practice. This is a video that we rendered from one
of the benchmark sequences from the TUM RGB-D benchmark. Here a camera was moved around an otherwise
static scene and we now run this direct visual odometry algorithm to estimate the motion
between two consecutive RGB-D frames. And then, we just concatenate this transformation
on and on over all 2000 images of the sequence. And then, we render that as the red line you
are seeing here. And now one interesting thing is that you here can see that the world by
itself is not moving at all or only moving very slowly. And this actually shows that
the method has a very low drift. So because in principle if you would match two consecutive
images there is always a certain drift between them. But then this drift accumulates up the
longer you go of course but in this example you can see that even if we go around for
more than a minute or so around this table the drift is still there you can see at
the end of this video the table has moved slightly, maybe for 30 centimeters or so and
there is a slight rotation. But given the large number of images and the purely pairwise
matching there was actually not too much of difference.
And now here at the end of the video Christian overlaid, the blue point cloud is the reference
point cloud from the very first frame and the colored one is the point cloud from the
very last frame. And you can see that there is a certain drift here in the camera pose
but it is not too bad.
And the good news is now that this method is actually runs in real time on a single
CPU core because all operations that you need to do to estimate the motion are extremely
simple. You always just need to compute the difference between one image and the warped
second image. And this can be done extremely quickly on a normal CPU. You can of course
also be parallelized easily. And this means we can now exploit the full image information
from a RGB-D camera to estimate directly the geometry between two frames. Now as we have
seen already of course the dense or direct visual odometry takes two RGB-D frames as
input and gives us the relative poses output.
But still one problem here is that dense visual odometry suffers from drift. You've seen it
in the video in the end of this very long trajectory we accumulate a certain drift.
And now the question is: how can we actually eliminate this drift further to stabilize
the camera pose estimation. And the idea then that Christian came up with
last summer is to extend this into a full pose graph SLAM system. Were we again like
PTAM select certain key frames. We try to detect loop closures and add additional edges
in between. And then, we optimize in between and build this pose graph using existing libraries.
So I don't want to go into detail too much here but we will provide you again with further
information on this topic. But it's also easy to understand it from this illustration here.
So the idea is again that the camera, the odometry computes the camera pose as we go.
But now every now and then, say every 20cm or so, we take a so called key frame. And
instead of now always matching our current camera to the previous camera we always localize
with respect to our previous key frame. And that removes already a lot of the pose drift
that we have seen. But the other extension is that whenever we add a new key frame we
actually try to match it with previous key frames. And when we have a successful match
then we add one of this green intermediate edges in between. And these edges, you can
imagine them as springs that keep our pose graph together, and whenever we add such an
intermediate spring you can see how the camera nodes move a little bit to relax. And especially
once we're finishing the whole loop here around the table and we are able to do a large loop
closer here at the end. You can see that the pose graph really changes a lot one this edges
are added.
So I switched back here just before the moment when the loop closure happens. Now and you
can see that all the camera poses get adapted slightly to undo the drift that we have seen before.
And then of course we can render this scene again as a point cloud. And now, this point
cloud looks much more consistent. There is no longer this drift that we have seen before
with the visual odometry. So now all cameras are consistent to each other and that's a
good starting point for mapping. Now one problem of point clouds is that it don't looks so
nice, depending of course on your application you would like to have again. A mesh as we
have seen before using marching cubes, but one problem here is to run marching cubes
we would need to generate a high resolution 3D voxel grid as before. And this voxel grid
consumes very much memory because it grows cubically. So in the last video we showed you
this reconstruction of the kitchen or our quadrotor lab and the person and for that we generally
use a resolution of around 256 to the power of 3 voxels. And then, it fits nicely in memory
and you can easily compute it in real time. But one problem is that as soon as you increase
this resolution then you memory consumption goes up by a vector of 8. Every time you double
the resolution the memory consumption grows by a vector of 8. And this means that it scales
very poorly to larger environments.
And now the idea that Frank Steinbrücker had to remedy this problem is to actually
use an oct-tree as data structure that only stores those cells that are actually close
to the surface because we're not interested in all the voxels that are far away from our
surface. But we only need in principle to model one voxel in front of the surface and
one behind. Of course when you implement that you need to make certain tradeoffs. We allocated
a little bit more than that, but nevertheless, the idea that we only store a small band around the actual surface.
And then, another cool thing that you can do with oct-trees is to store the geometry
not only at the leafs of the oct-tree but store it at the intermediate layers as well.
And that then gives you the geometry at multiple resolution. So you have a multi resolution
signed distance function then from which we can compute this mesh.
And the other cool thing with oct-trees is that we can grow the tree in principle arbitrarily
because whenever we leave the construction volume we can just add a new top node, a new root
node, and get larger and larger. So in principle there is no fixed size except for memory limits
of your host station.
And with that Frank took a very long sequence of RGB-D images of over 24.000 images. It
took him I think more than half an hour or more an hour in our lab to actually record
it. And then, Christian run his visual SLAM algorithm
on top of it, so we removed the drift with that automatically. We get good camera poses.
And then, after that Frank created this oct-tree signed distance function representation and
on top of that we then again run marching cubes to generate this mesh.
And as you can see you can really zoom in, you get lots of details on the keyboard, sometimes
you can even recognize papers that are lying around, you can see the screen, you can see
persons, small details, and at the same time we are dealing with a very large geometry
here.
So maybe just to give you just a few numbers here: this model now still fits in the memory
of a recent GPU, it consumes around 3.4 GB of memory including the oct-tree and the mesh.
And then again, you can store the mesh in a file and then use that for architectural
purposes or for computer games and so on.
And then, we actually found that the mapping on GPU ran extremely fast. Frank obtained
frame rates of around 200 frames per second to be integrated in this tree. The reason
for that is that we have actually much less voxels that we need to update because we're
only updating instead of the whole voxel grid we're only updating locally around the surface. And that
means that the whole algorithm runs extremely quickly. And then, we thought you know we
don't really need 200Hz so let's try again to bring back this algorithm to CPU.
And this is actually what happens frequently, first when you start research on something
you need all the strongest PC that you can imagine, the best 3D sensor that you can imagine
and then you barely mange to get a nice 3D reconstruction or a nice algorithm running.
And then, the more you think about it the more you realize where you can actually tweak
the memory consumption. And as a side effect this also tweaks the processing power more
that we need. And so Frank reimplemented the whole thing on CPU. He used a lot of tweaks
and optimizations he relies on SIMD instructions that allows you to run four instructions at
the same time on one single core. And then, he still using two cores now, one for updating
the oct-tree and extending the oct-tree and a second CPU core to incrementally generate
this mesh that is then displayed in a viewer at the same time.
Now in this visualization you can still see this different level of detail. Some of the triangles
here come from a very coarse signed distance function at a higher level because the camera
was very far away, while other parts where the camera has already passed through get
very fine and tiny meshes. So this one goes down to I think at less than 5mm in resolution.
And at the same time you get the texture but you don't need it. Sometimes it's better to
see how the geometry looks like if you look just at the gray geometry.
And then, we also realized after a while, this is now a work from Jakob Engel another
PhD student in our lab, that we can transfer this concept back to monocular cameras and
with that in principle it becomes applicable to Parrot ArDrones as well, so that's what
we want to try next. This video now shows the direct visual odometry
with monocular camera. But also Jakob is working at the moment towards a direct SLAM system
that again tries to close loops and optimize then the whole pose graph to obtain an even
better drift free 3D map. So next to the dense tracking the idea is now that we need and
depth image of course from somewhere to be able to do this image warping. And the idea
is now that for every pixel that has a non-zero gradient, wherever you see some corner or some edge
in the image you can actually try to measure its distance by picking the right frame. The
previous camera frame you wish to compare it to. And then, you can update independent Kalman
Filters for all the pixels in the image and this gives you then the so called semi-dense
depth map here on the left side. And this corresponds in principle to a 3D point cloud
as you can see here on the right. And the cool thing with using a monocular
camera here is that you actually not limited to indoor, like we are with the Kinect, you
can actually also go outdoors. And in contrast to previous methods where you extract key
points for example we can also compute the depths of parts of the scene that actually
are not a corner but just an edge.
And you can see here you get even the depths for the clouds very far away and you get close
objects also represented at the same time.
So to summarize the lesson of today, we've looked at direct methods for visual odometry
and visual SLAM. We've introduced the photo consistency constraint
as our main constrain that we used during optimization.
We've looked at loop closing for the SLAM problem, the graph SLAM problem. As I said
we only touched SLAM briefly but if you're interested in more then please follow the
link after this video to learn more. And then, we have also looked at large scale
3D reconstruction by using signed distance functions and oct-trees. And the good news
here is that actually Christian and Frank decided to make the software completely available
as open source. So please visit either our homepage or our Github page download this
and run it all by yourself.
So this video now concludes our edx course on Autonomous Navigation for Flying Robots.
I hope you enjoyed the course a lot it was also fun for us to prepare all of that. I
hope we got you interested in this topic in general, I hope you learned something here
and there. Maybe some of you have already now transferred some of your insights to a real
quadrotors, maybe you have a Parrot ArDrone or one of the Bitcraze Crazyflie quadrotors. And
so we're looking forward to see how you liked the course and what things could be improved
in future classes. And with that I wish you all a great time. Please drop us a line if
you like to send us some feedback. And have fun and take care.