Welcome back everybody.
So in this video I will give you a short example on 2D geometry for a planar robot.
So imagine that we have a simple robot being located somewhere in 2D space.
And then we could describe its pose by its position in x and y direction,
and its rotation around the yaw axis.
This means that this robot has 3 degrees of freedom, namely two 2D translation and a 1D
rotation or orientation.
And as we have seen in the previous video we could represent such a pose by using a
euclidian transformation matrix, consisting of a rotation part and a translation part.
The rotation part would just encode this heading angle Psi here. And the translation
vector would encode the position in x and y direction.
And this is a 3 by 3 vector, this matrix is also called SE(2),
standing for special euclidian transformation of 2 dimensions.
And now just to fill a few numbers, to make it more concrete, imagine the robot stands
now at x position of 0.7, y position equals 0.5, and its heading 45 degrees to the upper right.
And then, this would mean that the robot pose could be described by the following matrix
as shown here on the slide.
We have now the robot standing somewhere in space. And now, one common task is now that
we want to know where the robot would end up, if it would move one meter forward.
Another important question that we look in afterwards is: what motion actually do we need
to execute to reach a certain position? Like for example, to move back to the origin of our world.
But now, to answer the first question. So imagine the robot would move forward by 1 meter.
Then, what is its position afterwards?
And we could of course first describe a point being located 1 meter in front of the robot
in its local coordinate frame, which would mean that we could say: this is a vector of
1, 0, and if you look at the homogeneous or augmented coordinates than it would be 1, 0, 1.
And this would give us a vector in the local coordinate system of the robot.
And if we want to convert this point to global coordinates, then we can just multiply it
through the robot pose being described by this matrix we have computed before. So we
would multiply this vector 1, 0, 1, and obtain then the coordinate 1.41, 1.21, 1, and this
would mean that the robot would end up at the location 1.4 meters, 1.2 meters away from the origin.
So this transformation is also known as a transformation from local to global coordinates.
Sometimes, as I have already indicated, we need to do the inverse, so we have global
coordinates and we want to know in the local coordinate frame of the robot where these
coordinates are, relative to the robot.
So how can we transform now instead,  global coordinates to local coordinates.
So in the first example we've transformed local coordinates to global coordinates, by
multiplying the robot pose with the local coordinates and now of course we can just
reverse this equation to obtain local coordinates from global coordinates. For that we need
to inverse the robot pose, and because of the special form, this robot pose is euclidian,
we can specify the inverse directly because the rotation part can just be transposed.
The rotation part or rotation matrix as you remember is an orthonormal matrix, and that
has the property to get the inverse you can just take the transpose of it.
And similarly we can compute the new translation just by taking the transpose of the rotation
times the translation, and by flipping the sign.
And in this way we obtain now a very efficient way of transforming global coordinates to local coordinates.
Now, this was now just referring to points in front of the robot. We can of course also
do the same for motions, that means for transformations. For example, imagine that the robot moves
forward by 20 centimeters and 10 centimeters to the left and then additionally also turns by
10 degrees. And then, this motion can again be described
by a euclidian transformation that we would have to apply. So by filling in these values
we can again obtain a certain euclidian transformation that describes the robot motion.
And if you want to compute now the final pose of the robot, after executing this motion,
we can just concatenate the previous robot pose X times the motion capital U. And from
there obtain again a certain euclidian transformation,
that contains the pose after the robot has executed this motion.
Of course, it is important here to execute these transformations in the right order, so it's
not the same, AB is not the same as BA. It's very clear that this must be the case,
imagine that you move 1 meter forward and then turn 90 degrees to the left, as illustrated
here with the red arrow. Is clearly not the same as if you would first turn by 90 degrees
and then move 1 meter forward. So it is very important to remember that
order matters for concatenating transformations.
And this now brings us to so called robot odometry, because very often we want to estimate
the robot motion from it sensors or from information that we have. And there are different ways
of obtaining such a robot motion. First of all, of course we know typically what motion
commands we gave to the robot, of course we never know exactly whether these controls
have been executed properly, but typically from the controls that we give, for example
from the joystick commands that we send to the quadrotor we can make certain predictions
about the resulting robot motion that we would expect.
Another option of course is to use odometry sensors like wheel encoders, this is harder
on quadrotors, but for wheel robots you could have wheel encoders that just count the number
of wheel spins either of the motor or of the wheel. And then you could use that to derive
the robot motion that the robot did. The other option is to use a velocity sensor,
and this is for example what the ArDrone has with its down looking camera.
So this is a sensor that gives us the current velocity of the robot, and then by integrating
the velocities over time we can again determine the robot motion in a certain time interval.
And this process of integrating the odometry is also called dead reckoning, and in principle
it's just a mathematical procedure to determine the present location of the vehicle or of
a robot from its odometry readings, whatever those are.
This can be usually achieved by using the estimated or measured velocities and integrating
that over the elapsed time. So for example, and for being able to do that
you typically need a motion model that tells you how the controls or the IMU readings or
velocity readings from your sensor can be translated into the robot motion between two
time steps. Such a motion model usually takes as input
the previous robot pose and the issued control command or the odometry readings and computes
from there the new robot pose X at time step t.
And of course, you have lots of such time steps, usually IMU readings arrive
at 200 Hertz, very frequently. And then you need to integrate them up to be able to make
predictions of the current pose of the robot.
And this already brings us to the next exercise, so we recorded some flight data from a real
flight of a Parrot ArDrone quadrotor. And we extracted the IMU readings, which contain
the horizontal speed of the robot in x and y direction, in its local frame, and the angle
of speed, around its vertical axis.
And from these three parameters we want to infer the position and orientation of the
robot in the global frame, at every point in time. And your task now is to integrate these
values to obtain the robot pose and the trajectory that the robot traversed from there.
So to summarize the things that we've looked at in this video:
we've looked at 2D robot poses,
we've looked at the conversion between local and global coordinate frames,
we also looked at the concatenation of motions
and then we have introduced the concepts of odometry,
and how odometry readings can be used to infer robot motions and then again robot poses.