Hello.
And welcome back, everybody, to the second part
of the first lecture on autonomous
navigation for flying robots.
In this video, I will briefly illustrate a few
of the use cases of quadrotors and with that
motivate why we believe that quadrotors will become really
relevant commercially but also scientifically
in the near future.
So before we start with the more technical applications,
let me first ask you to think personally
what you would like to use such a quadrotor for.
And for the moment, just think of it
as an autonomously flying camera.
And then, depending on your personal interests,
you might come up with the idea that you could film yourself
during your next ski run, to have a camera that just follows
you automatically or that flies in front of you
and takes really nice imagery.
In a similar application, quadrotors
could also be real life-savers.
For example, after an avalanche goes off,
you could send out a team of quadrotors
to quickly monitor the hill from above
to get visual imagery such that the rescue forces can quickly
come to the victims and save them.
Similarly, also after nature catastrophes,
like a tsunami, of course, or an earthquake,
quadrotors are really versatile helpers
that can be sent into buildings to inspect them.
In particular, if you're not sure
whether the building is still safe for humans,
if possibly the building could collapse,
then you better send in a robot.
And quadrotors have the advantage
that they are not obstructed by debris on the floor.
So imagine you would send in a wheeled robot,
then it might get stuck very soon if there
are stones or parts of the wall lying on the floor.
Similarly, and more interesting for personal use,
are quadrotors that you can send above your house,
to check for example the roof for damages after a storm.
Similarly also for inspecting buildings in general.
So for example, bridges have to be inspected on a yearly basis.
And that's a quite expensive effort,
because you have to have one or two inspectors being
transported next to the supporting
structure of a bridge to look visually
at the state of the pillars.
And if you had a very easy to use flying camera for that,
then that would save enormous amounts of money and time,
obviously.
Another application is in remote farming.
You could send out quadrotors quickly to crop fields
to check whether addition watering is needed,
whether the plants are healthy, to monitor a field in general.
But then even if you detect certain diseases,
you could spray certain substances
on the plants very precisely and exactly the right amount based
on your visual inspection.
Another huge topic, of course, is to map,
to use quadrotors to map buildings,
both from the outside and the inside.
I guess most of you will already have
taken measurements of your own apartment.
If you're moving to a new flat, you
have to take all the measurements of the furniture
and of the rooms and doors.
And if you had an automatic tool,
like a small quadrotor, that you could send in a room
and would generate a 3D map, this would be very helpful.
So this helps people, common people like you and me.
But it also helps, of course, architects to quickly
scan in huge buildings to get such 3D maps.
This is also highly relevant for industrial applications.
If you look at production sites, then most of the time
there is also no accurate floor plan.
And similarly, walking around and taking all the measurements
can be quite cumbersome.
And also if you have three-dimensional structures
like pipes and so on, then it's not
really easy to create such a map manually.
Also very interesting, but still at a quite early stage,
are transportation tasks for quadrotors.
Amazon launched recently a video showing an octocopter
transporting a package to a customer.
This was more a proof of concept, of course,
because there are so many unresolved legal issues there.
And then also Domino's Pizza showed a video
where they delivered a pizza to a client.
So while this is still at an early stage,
it's clear that with quadrotors, we're
actually close to implementing such applications.
So with that, I've shown that there
are many useful applications for quadrotors.
And that it also has a large commercial potential
for the future.
However, current solutions require typically
a skilled human pilot that navigates manually
the quadrotor in these applications.
And that obviously limits the applicability.
This again motivates the main question in this course,
namely, how can we increase the autonomy of flying robots?
This brings me down then to our first exercise,
interactive exercise that we have prepared for you.
So we would like you to propose one or more ideas what
you would like to use an autonomous
quadrotor for once it exists.
And then just write this idea in the message forum.
And then vote for your favorite idea.
And then we also would like you to discuss there
what the particular challenges are of each of these ideas
and how large the commercial potential is.
And then, based on your proposals,
we will discuss the three most popular ideas next week
in class.