Hello and welcome everybody to Autonomous Navigation for Flying Robots.
In this video we look at sensors and of course in particular at sensors that are relevant
for quadrotors and micro aerial vehicles.
The most important sensor in every aerial vehicle is a so called inertial measurement
unit (IMU). That is a device that consist of accelerometers and gyroscopes to measure
the inertial motion of the quadrotor and it's typically used for altitude stabilization.
Range sensors are also important with that the ArDrone measures the distance from the
floor and controls that. And then GPS of course is a very important
sensor especially for flying outdoors. And cameras also are super important, for both,
estimating the horizontal speed if you have an optical flow sensor looking downwards or
for a forward camera to detect landmarks in the world.
As I have said internal measurement units typically consists of accelerometers, and
a single accelerometer measures the acceleration that is applied to the sensor. You can imagine
such an accelerometer to look like a spring damper system in the easiest case. So you
have a mass that is attached with a spring to a support structure, and when you accelerate this
construction or this device in vertical direction then the mass will move up or down.
By then measuring the deflection of the mass you can get a measurement of the acceleration
that is applied to the sponsor.
Of course such an accelerometer measures all accelerations that are applied to it.
So if you have a vertical accelerometer then it will always measure the gravity.
So you have to take probably care of gravitation when you estimating the accelerating forces.
Gyroscopes measure the orientation if you have a standard gyroscope or they measure
the angular velocity, which is then called a rate gyro. In such a case you need to integrate
then the angular velocity to obtain the absolute angle.
So in the simplest case for building a gyroscope you can use a spinning wheel that's rotating
at a very high speed. And such a wheel is mounted with a gimbal
device that is a device which can rotate 3D around it. Then the spinning wheel will keep
its orientation no matter what you do to the case around it.
And in this way by measuring the orientation of the wheel inside, with respect to the outer
casing you can determine the orientation of yourself. Because the wheel will keep its
orientation no matter what we do around it. Such things have been constructed by many
people in the past and they can be used for example to measure the rotation of earth.
But they are also used in this way in airplanes; for example, in old airplanes where you really have these
spinning wheels and when you switch them on it also takes a while to reach their speed
and you can even hear them when you listen carefully.
Modern gyroscopes of course use different principles. Most common are MEMS sensors that
have vibrating structures inside. Their measurement principle is then based on the Coriolis effect.
So the vibration itself keeps its direction even if the sensor or the device is turned.
And then again you can use capacitive sensing to see whether this structure gets closer
or further away from the electrodes. And there are different types of such gyroscopes.
The most common one is called the tuning fork gyroscope, where you just have something that's
vibrating very quickly and keeps this position in a certain plane. And when you move or when
the sensor is rotated then this tuning fork will keep its orientation and virtually be
deflected with respect to the sensor itself.
You also have sensors that contain vibrating wheels and there are also laser based systems,
but typically not in this size class that is used for a quadrotor.
Inertial measurements units, also abbreviated as IMUs now combine both gyroscopes and accelerometers.
A single gyroscope is obviously not enough because it just measures the angular velocity
in one direction or around one axis.
This is why typically IMUs contain 3 gyroscopes next to each other, one for every axis.
And the gyroscope by itself provides only an angular velocity so you need to integrate
that over time to obtain the absolute angular position. But because the readings from the gyroscopes,
especially from such small gyroscopes, will be very noisy the angular position will drift
over time just because small errors over time will accumulate.
This drift can be relatively small, for example, 1 degree per hour. On smaller quadrotors or
if you have smaller gyroscopes then this can be even be 1 degree per second or 1 degree
per minute, depending on the quality.
Then there are also accelerometers in IMUs, again you need 3 of them to measure the acceleration
in all 3 spatial directions. An accelerometer provides accelerations and it also measures
of course the earth gravity.
From there you can again then integrate your estimated speed and estimated position.
This is usually done in an algorithm or in an implementation called IMU strapdown algorithm.
You get the date from the accelerometers and the gyroscopes, may let's start with the bottom
left. With the gyroscopes we're getting the angular rates in all 3 directions
and then the first computational block here just integrates those to obtain the attitude
just by adding them up.
And when you have the attitude you know in which direction you will expect a gravitational
force. So you can use that to compensate for gravity from the acceleration readings, which
means that after this gravity compensation you have the pure acceleration that is applied
to your IMU at the moment.
When you integrate this acceleration then you obtain the velocity of the device, and when you integrate
that again you get the position.
It should be noted of course, that when you integrate twice such noisy readings then the result
will be extremely noisy and extremely wrong. So the position integration of MEMS IMUs is
not useful over longer periods of time. But you can usually get rather good predictions
for the next 100ms maybe even up to 1 seconds or so, but after that it will be extremely inaccurate.
The estimated acceleration after gravity compensation then typically run through a low pass filter
to see if there is any acceleration remaining in a certain direction, and this is then usually
because the attitude is not completely right. This can be compensated by estimating the
bias of the gyroscope and then feeding it back into the attitude integration to compensate
for such a bias over longer periods of time.
GPS is also very important especially for flying outdoors. I guess most of you will
know the GPS system, as this is the same as every smartphone uses.
The idea is that you have many satellites circling earth and every satellite transmits
its position and time.
The receiver then receives these messages from the satellites and measures the time
difference in the individual signals between the individual time steps from the satellites.
Then by evaluating these differences the receiver can calculate the position on earth from these
so called pseudoranges.
There are a large number of satellites rotating around earth. Every satellite in the GPS-system
has a 12 hour orbit, they are flying roughly in 20.000 km height. There are 6 orbital planes
around earth and each of these planes has at least 4 satellites, typically much more.
They are located roughly at 60 degrees distance of each other, depending on how many satellites you have.
This ensures that there are always at least 4 satellites visible, typically much more.
As I said, every satellite transmits its orbital location, the so called almanach and the current
time. And because all satellites share the same frequency for transmission the transmission
rate is extremely low. It is only 50 bits per second. And this message there transmitting
has 1500 bits which is not much, but nevertheless, to transmit that it takes roughly 12.5 minutes.
So this is why a cold start of the receiver takes a very long time before you get the first fix.
GPS has 2 different modes of operation. The normal one that is used by the most smartphones
is called the position from pseudorange mode. For that the GPS receiver needs to see at
least 4 different satellites. It's 4 because the receiver has to estimate both, the current
time and its position on earth. And the position on earth is a 3 dimensional
vector depending on how you representing it, as longitude, latitude and elevation or simply
as x,y,z with respect to some reference point. But this means that we have to compute at
least 4 different values and for that we need 4 independent measurements.
This first mode of operation is relatively inaccurate, typically you get positioning
accuracy between 3 and 15 meters, depending on the equipment that you have, but also depending
on the atmospheric conditions. But it gives you an absolute position on earth and this
is very useful of course for navigation systems in cars, but also for airplanes and quadrotors.
The other mode of operation requires an additional base station or reference station. And the
idea then is to not only use the pseudoranges, but also to determine the exact phase shifts
of the signal between the receiver and the base station.
With that you can achieve extremely high accuracies typically far below 1 millimeter. But the
position that you then getting is not absolute on earth but it is relative with respect to
your reference station. Such systems are called real-time-kinematic-GPS
or differential-GPS, and become more and more affordable and also smaller. Such that we
can hope that they will sooner or later fit on our quadrotors.
The next sensor that is relevant for us are
range sensors, in particular ultrasound range sensors.
The idea of most range sensors is to have an active sensor to emit a signal and measure
the time the signal needs to return to the sender/receiver.
And when we are talking here about ultrasound, then we are effectively using the propagation
speed of ultrasound to determine then the distance between the sender/receiver and the object.
So here for example we can see the sender/receiver it sends out the red waves. These waves
are reflected by the object and then the receiver will here its echo.
And this time measurement times the velocity divided by 2, because the signal has to traverse
both the ways from left to right and then from right to left back again, gives directly the
distance. So this is a very simple measurement principle
and therefore it is very often used.
The disadvantage of course at least of ultrasound is that the range is limited. So you can only
do that up to a few meters, depending also on you surface it works less well on grass, it works
better of course on things like stone or better reflecting surfaces.
Another problem is that the opening angle of a speaker or microphone is whether large,
so typically the beam that is send out has an opening angle around 20 to 40 degrees.
And that means that it could also happen that you are measuring the distance to something else that's close
to your sensor.
And another problem of course is that the sensor doesn't work on certain objects that either
absorb the sound or reflect it in a different way, but that the sound doesn't return to the receiver.
But in any case the advantage here is that those sensors are extremely lightweight to
build, a few grams, and extremely cheap so you can get them for a few Euros. Probably if
you buy them in quantities they become even cheaper.
Then the last, and form our perspective in the computer vision group of course the most
interesting sensor is a camera. We have already seen in one of the previous videos how the pin-hole
camera looks like from a mathematical perspective. The idea is you have the world, and the world emits
some light because it is lit by the sun or by any other light source. And then the rays
from the object pass through the pin-hole and then fall onto the film or light sensor,
which is light sensitive and that we can read out then electronically.
Of course, most cameras don't use the pin-hole idea, but have a lens that focuses the light
on the film or sensor.
The advantage here is that you have a larger aperture, which means that more light is passed
on to the sensor. And that helps of course then during image acquisition.
The disadvantage of using lenses is that they typically induce some radial distortion on
the image. Depending on how expensive your lenses are this effect is stronger or less
strong. It's in particular bad for lenses that have large opening angles. So typically
for webcams this is not a large problem, but if you getting maybe above a 100 degrees opening
angle, then these deviations become visible very strongly. And the larger it gets the worst it gets.
Typically you can see these deviations especially in the corners of the image.
So if you see lines in the images that are not straight any more then you know that you are probably dealing with lens distortions.
In most cases there are different cases for modelling these distortions. A very common
model is to use a low order polynomial to describe the deviation from the ideal image
and the observed image.
So in this case you have this r here, which refers to the radius or the distance of the
optical center of your camera or of your image. And then this coefficients Kappa_1 and Kappa_2
refer to how strong this deviation is on your lens.
So now for being able to use these camera models we of course need to determine all
the coefficients in the models. For the pin-hole model this means that we
need to determine the focal length f_x and f_y, and also the optical center c_x and c_y.
For the distortion model we need to know the coefficients Kappa_1 and Kappa_2 and possibly
even higher order distortion coefficients.
And then, of course the question is: how can we actually determine these parameters?
A very common method for doing that is to show a checkerboard to the camera and
use that to establish correspondences between 3D points in the world and 2D points on the image.
And from such a set of observations the coefficients of the camera model can then
be determined. So in general every observation between a
2D point and a 3D point produces two constraints,  one for the x axis in the image and one for the y axis in the image.
And then you can use that to solve for the
intrinsic parameters, like the focal length and the optical center, but also the distortion coefficients.
So the image in the lower left shows the calibration toolbox in ROS for monocular cameras.
You just show a checkerboard in different configurations and also at different parts of the image.
It's usually a good idea to hold it close to the image borders because as we have seen
before the distortion is the largest close to the image border.
When you have taken enough of these observations
you can calibrate all the coefficients. And then here on the right this has already happened.
You can recognize that because now all the lines in the image are actually straight
as they should be.
So to summarize the lesson of today:
We've looked at various sensors that can be used on quadrotors and micro aerial vehicles.
We've seen that IMUs can be used to measure attitude, the velocity and the position of the vehicle.
We looked at range sensors that can be used to measure distances.
And we've looked at GPS to measure the global position
of a quadrotor when flying outdoors. And then lastly, we have looked at real cameras
and how they can be calibrated to establish the correspondence between 3D points in the world
and 2D observations on the image plane.