Hello and welcome everybody to the course Autonomous Navigation for Flying Robots.
In the previous videos we have introduces 2D geometry, and then illustrated how that can be
used to compute odometry for a 2 dimensional planar robot. Of course, quadrotors live in
a 3 dimensional world, so in this video we will now extend that to full 3D. Similar as before
we can now define points in 3D. A 3D point of course consists of 3 dimensions for the x, y and z axis.
And agian, we can augment such a vector by a 1 in an additional row at the end, which is then called
an augmented vector again. We can define homogeneous coordinates or a homogeneous
vector that has four elements. And remember, two homogeneous vectors are representing the
same point in 3D if and only if they only differ by scale. Using such points we can
now a line in 3D. There are different ways of representing lines.
A very simple form is to just use 2 points. And the line connecting these two points can
then be defined as a linear blending between the coordinates of these two points. So in this formula if Lambda
is 0 then we are exactly at point p, and if Lambda is 1 then we are exactly at point q.
For any values between 0 and 1, we would interpolate between p and q along line
segment joining these two points. And if Lambda can take any real value, then we are moving
along the infinite line defined by these two points.
We can also define a 3D plane, a 3D plane can be described by 3 parameters, in principal.
But it is easier to use the homogeneous representation. So this vector m here, m tilde has 4 coefficients,
and if you multiply that with a 3D point, x bar or x tilde, and set it to 0 then this
formula defines all points lying on the plane.
And again, from this equation you can see that the scale actually doesn't matter. So
if you multiply it by a constant then you still getting the same points on the line.
Similar as before, we can now normalize this plane equation by saying that the first 3
components x and y and z have a length of 1. Then this vector actually corresponds
to the normal vector. And if it has length 1 it's a unit normal vector. And then the
last coefficient d specifies the distance of the plane from the origin.
Then we can also define 3D transformations again. A translation as before can be specified
by a multiplication of a 4 by 4 matrix with a vector. For only a translation we would
have the identity in the upper left and then the 3 dimensional translation vector in the
upper right. And then, if we replace this identity in the
upper left by a 3 dimensional rotation matrix, then we obtain an euclidian transform.
Elements of this type are also called to be elements of the special euclidian group of dimension 3.
Just saying that we are dealing here with rotation and translation at the same time.
And as before you can define a scaled rotation, where we have an additional scaling factor
to grow or shrink objects or trajectories in 3D. You can define an affine transform
to stretch an object. You can define projective transformations
and homographies that are even more general. But for the moment, and mostly for this course we need euclidian
transformations to move around the robot in 3D and to compute motions between poses.
So now let's look a little bit more at 3D euclidian transformations. Obviously the translation
which is a 3 dimensional vector has 3 degrees of freedom because we can move around the
object or the quadrotor along all 3 axes. And similarly also the rotation has a 3 degrees
of freedom because we can turn the quadrotor around all 3 principle axes.
Now if you look closer at this rotation matrix then you see that it actually consists of
9 elements because it's a 3 by 3 orthogonal matrix. And this group is also called a special
orientation group SO(3) because it preserves scale and the angles.
And to read such a rotation matrix you can look at the column vectors and then these
vectors correspond to the coordinate axes after the transformation.
So what do we now typically need to do with this rotation matrices? Or what are the operations
that we frequently have to apply? But of course one thing, and we have seen
that already before, we need to invert them and need to be able to concatenate them. For
example, to integrate the odometry from sensors and of course we need to the inverse.
Sometimes we need to estimate a rotation matrix because we want to find out how the robot moved between
two time steps. And now the question is, how easy are these operations on matrices? So
is a rotation matrix actually the right representation to solve these tasks?
And obviously 3D rotation matrices can very easily concatenated, just by multiplying them.
And they can also be very easily be inverted.
So those of you who have listened carefully will remember that the rotation matrix or
an orthogonal matrix can be inverted just by taking the transpose of the matrix. And
that's of course a super-fast operation.
The disadvantage is, and that's especially a disadvantage if you need to find the rotation
between two points in space, is that it's completely over-parameterized.
You have 9 coefficients instead of only the 3 real degrees of freedom.
So if you use that in an optimization task then you will have to make sure that the nine
parameters your are estimating actually form a valid rotation matrix and that's actually
not very trivial.
So the question is: aren't there any other representations that are minimal or close
to minimal and that help us during this optimization problems?
One very common form and probably also the best known form of such a representation are
the euler angles.
The euler angles are just a product of 3 consecutive rotations
around a predefined order of axes. For example, it would first rotate around the x axis, then
around the y axis, and then rotate around the z axis.
Especially in aerial navigation the so called
roll-pitch-yaw convention is very common.
And this means that you specify first the roll angle along the main axis of the quadrotor
or the plane. Then the pitch angle, which specifies the rotation around the wings of the robot (plane).
And then the yaw angle, which describes the heading of the quadrotor or the plane.
Then you typically want to convert from euler angles to rotation matrices and vice versa.
And you can do that as follows: so you can specify
the euler angles as 3 values, the roll, pitch and yaw angle. Then we use that to compute
3 individual rotation matrices. A rotation around the z axis, a rotation around the y
axis, and a rotation around the x axis, and then you concatenate all 3 of them.
So every individual rotation matrix is very simple, because it's just a sine and cosine
to describe the rotation around a certain axes. But if you multiply all of them together
then you get a very ugly expression as shown her at the bottom.
And then again, if you want go back from a rotation matrix to roll-pitch-yaw angles, then you
could use these formulas. There are other formulas as well that bring you there. Because
it's over parameterized it's hard to find the best way in the presents of noise for doing that.
So the advantage of euler angles clearly is that it's a minimal representation. You only
have 3 parameters and they have a very easy representation, especially when your angles
are close to 0, because then you can just imagine in your head how the plane would be rotated
or how far it is away from the resting position. The disadvantage is that there are many different
euler representations and there is typically confusion when somebody sends you euler angles,
because you never know whether they use the XYZ convention or is the other way around
ZYX and so on.
So I think there are 24 different ways of interpreting euler angles and that makes it
sometimes hard to communicate with them in the right way.
The other problem is that it's really difficult to concatenate them because you have always
to convert them to a rotation matrix and then do the concatenation there and then extract
again the resulting euler angles.
And the last problem, and that's actually in terms of optimization the hardest one that
euler angles have singularities: they can get locked in a so called gimbal lock problem,
as illustrated here. It can happen in the euler angles that two
axes are being aligned and in this situation you losing 1 degree of freedom.
For example, these 3 rings here, so each of these rings now describes one rotation
accordingly to the roll-pitch-yaw formulation. But it can happen that all of these axes then
align, and then we have all of this three disks lying in one plane. And then in this plane
you can't rotate anymore around the central axis, the yaw angle.
This can be very bad and can't be solved with euler angles.
An alternative representation and also quite intuitive one is the so called axis/angle
representation. There the idea is that you describe a rotation by a rotation axis. A
normal direction vector in 3D and a rotation angle Theta that says by how far you rotate
around this axis.
This representation than has 4 degrees of freedom because you need 3 degrees of freedom
to specify this direction and a fourth parameter to specify the rotation angle.
You can combine both of that together by saying that the length of you axis directly encodes
the rotation angle. So a rotation of 0 would just be the 0-vector. A rotation of 180 degrees
would mean that your rotation vector has a length of Pi.
This representation, where you have just 3 parameters, is also called the angular velocity
representation or a so called twist. This is again a minimal representation, but
it is not unique similarly to the euler angles. I guess you can imagine why this is the case.
So every 2 Pi you repeat the same rotation, because if you rotate more than 360 degrees
then you are again at the same spot.
There are again formulas to convert from axis angle to rotation matrices and back.
From axis/angle to rotation matrices the conversion formula is called the Rodriguez formula, as
given here. The inverse is also given here.
For more information there is lots of more things to be said here, but to keep it simple,
and because we don't really need it in the rest of the course I would like to refer you
to the book of Ma and colleagues and in particular to chapter 2. If you google for this then
you can find an online copy.
So as I said the axis/angle representation is also called twist coordinates. The advantages
are: it's a minimal representation, and a second advantage is that the derivations are
really simple of that. So especially for optimization problems that
we will see later the axis/angle representation is really beneficial.
The disadvantage again, similar to euler angles again is that it's difficult to concatenate them.
You always need to go to a rotation matrix, and then multiply them there and convert
them back to axis/angle. And the conversion is also fairly slow because
you need to compute sine and cosine, which can be at least on some processors costly operations.
So a last representations for 3D rotations is so called quaternions.
A quaternion is a 4 dimensional vector representing a rotation. It can be split into a real and
a vector part. The real part is just a number and the vector part is a 3 dimensional vector then.
And you can normalize them such that the length
of the quaternion is exactly 1. And in this case you can imagine these unit
quaternions to be points on a 4 dimensional sphere of radius 1.
And then there is one ambiguity in quaternions: opposite sign quaternions represent the same
rotation. So the unit quaternion actually just lives
on one half of a sphere, and the other half of the sphere then represents the same rotations.
But otherwise quaternions are unique.
So the really good news on quaternions is that they are easy to multiply, to concatenate
and they can be easily inverted. So they are really efficient and easy to implement. And
this is the reason why many quadrotors that need to do these operations onboard actually
use the quaternion representation. For example to concatenate two quaternions
it's just a small number of multiplications, and subtractions and additions that you need
to do. So things that you can do fairly easy on an embedded system. Also to compute the
inverse is extremely easy you just flip the sign of either the real or imaginary part.
So two more things that you would like to do with quaternions is to rotate a 3D vector
using the rotation represented by the quaternion, and this turns out to be just again a multiplication
of the quaternion with the vector and the conjugate of the quaternion, which is extremely
fast to compute. And if you want to, you can convert of course quaternions to the other
types. For example, it's closely related to the axis/angle
representation. But of course, you can also transform a quaternion to a rotation matrix and convert
the rotation matrix to a quaternion.
So to summarize that, there are different representations of 3D rotations.
There is not really a single best one it depends on your application.
If you jusst need to just concatenate things then rotation matrices and quaternions are very well suited.
If you want to optimize a 3D representation,
then the axis/angle representation is very well suited.
And maybe one thing in general that is good to know, even for experts in 3D orations or
3D geometry it's really hard to parse or read a 3D rotation vector, no matter in what representation.
So if I see euler angles I typically do not know what rotation they do correspond with,
except if it's maybe close to the origin. And the same holds for a rotation matrix,
I think there are very few people only who can tell you how an object is oriented if
the see the rotation matrix. And it gets even harder for the axis/angle
and in particular for the quaternion representation. So if you look at something like this and
don't know what rotation it is, be assured this is normal and there is no good way of
interpreting it manually. But one thing that can help you here because
you need to debug of course your program at some point is to use good 3D visualization tools.
For example, under Linux when you use ROS (the Robot Operating System), there is a good
tool called Rviz. Under C++ there is the library QGLViewer. And of course for our online exercises
we have this WebGL based 3D viewer that will help you to determine whether your orientations
and rotations are right.
Now the last part in this video is now that we need to be able to do 3D to 2D perspective
projections, as they happen in 2D or in cameras. So for example, here we have two objects being
located in the real world in 3D. And we have a camera actually observing these objects.
And then these objects being projected on the image plane of the camera. So we need
to find a way to compute from the 3D points in the world the 2D coordinates on the image
plane. And the most used model for cameras that holds
for most cameras which have normal lenses is the so called pin-hole camera model, where
you just remove essentially the last component of your homogeneous vector to obtain a 2 dimensional
homogeneous vector of your point. And then again, x tilde is homogeneous so
we need to divide by the last coordinate to obtain the real coordinate on the image plane.
One problem of course is so far if we just down project a 3D point in the world to 2D,
the 2D point will still be given in the same units as our 3D point.
For example, if our 3D points are specified in meters, then also the 2D point will be specified
in meters on the image plane, but of course, what we need with digital cameras is the pixel
position. So we need to convert this position in meters to a position in pixels. And for
that we need to apply some scaling and offset. This matrix that does this scaling and offset
is usually called the intrinsic matrix. It is sometimes abbreviated with a K and it consist
of 5 parameters. Namely the focal length f_x and f_y that specifies in principle the opening
angle of your camera. The larger this focal length is the smaller the opening angle of your
camera is and vice versa. A normal camera for example, like a webcam
with say 60 degrees of opening angle has a focal length of around 500 to 1000.
Then we also need to specify where the camera center is. This is typically in the middle
of the image, but it doesn't necessarily have to be there. It depends on how exactly where
the lens is mounted and where exactly the sensor is mounted. So during calibration it makes often
sense to calculate these values. And then there can be a skew factor that determines
whether or not the pixels on the image array are actually orthogonal or not.
But actually on all modern cameras there is no skew, so this s can be assumed to be 0.
And then one last thing, of course the 3D point coordinates that we've been looking
at previously are typically given in world coordinates.
So before we can project them onto the image plane we need to transform them from world
coordinates to the local camera system. This transformations is also called the camera
extrinsic parameters. In these parameters is described where the camera is located in
3D space. And this is similar as we have seen before,
the conversion from a global coordinate system to the local coordinate system of the camera.
And now we can concatenate all these transformations so we have a 3D world p_w being transformed
into the local coordinate frame of the camera. And then being projected to 2D, and
scaled and offsetted according to the camera intrinsic.
And then, these homogeneous vector x here gives us the coordinates on the screen or on the
image plane.
So to summarize the video of today:
we have looked at 3D points, lines and planes, we have also introduced 3D transformations,
in particular the euclidian transformation that we will be using a lot in this course.
And then, we have look at different representations for 3D orientations. And as we have summarized
earlier, the choice greatly depends on the application you're looking at and in the next
quiz we will ask you again to summarize which of these representations you still remember
and what the advantages and disadvantages are.
And we looked at 3D to 2D perspective projections as it happens in a normal camera.
So these things here that we have looked at today are really important and you really
have to know them by heart.
If you had the feeling by watching this video that you didn't fully understand it, then
my advice would be to look at the computer vision book of Richard Szeliski, in particular
chapter 2. It's fully available online (http://szeliski.org/Book/)
with lots of material. Please have a look at that.