Hello and welcome everybody back to video 8.2.
In this video we will introduce signed distance functions.
And in particular we will then show an algorithm that uses signed distance functions to track
the pose of a quadrotor in real time and create simultaneously a 3D textured map of its surroundings.
Before we start with the technical details let me first show you this video. This is an
AscTec quadrotor called Pelican and it has a 3D depth camera on board. And it now uses
the images of this 3D depth camera to generate a 3D model of its surroundings and at the
same time estimates then its position, its 3D pose, in real time and uses that for position
control. And in the remainder of this video I will show you how this works and how this
can be done. And then this now here is a visualization of the flight trajectory. Actually you can
see that it is quit shaky the quadrotor did not follow nicely a certain path. But nevertheless
the algorithm is able to run and the quadrotor follows the predefined path.
So this is our platform in more detail you can see it's also a quadrotor it has four
rotors, it has an autopilot board in the middle that does attitude control and contains the IMU.
And then, on top we have mounted an RGB-D camera. The good thing about this Pelican
platform is that it can carry up to 600 grams of additional payload. So you can add more
sensor as you wish. And we then decided to add a RGB-D camera. It's similar to a Microsoft
Kinect just a little bit more lightweight. And it contains a full computer running Ubuntu
we have now an Intel Core2Duo, but they also sell it with an i5 so you can get really reasonable performance.
And then, in the video you have seen before we've used this on board PC for a Kalman Filtering
and the autopilot board for position control. But we still had an external computer that
was running the 3D mapping because at the moment we need a graphics card for it.
So just to give you a brief outline of what depth cameras are and how the work.
This is how this ASUS camera looks like. It consists of two cameras, namely an infrared
camera and a color camera. And the infrared camera looks at the scene where it sees the
normal infrared image but it also sees a dot pattern that is projected by the sensor itself
from a slightly different location. And then, this pair of the infrared pattern projector
and the infrared camera forms a so called stereo baseline which gives us the possibility
then to compute the depth of every pixel - so the distance of every pixel from the sensor.
And there are different sensing principles for generating such depth measurements. Stereo
cameras and structured light cameras like this one match two images so either a reference
image that you already know from your projector  or you just observe two independent images
with a stereo camera and then you try to match them or you have direct measurement principles
where you measure the time of flight of a light pulse that you are sending out and the
time until it returns.
So before we now present our algorithm I thought it would be nice to also present a little
bit what happened before. We are using signed distance functions and
they have actually been introduced by Curless and Levoy for 3D reconstruction already in
1996. The basic idea here is that they represent
distance to the surface in a voxel grid. You see later an illustration of what that actually
means. And they already run at that time a data fusion
of multiple images into a 3D model. But it didn't do camera tracking and of course it
was also not running in real time at this time.
This changed dramatically with the appearance of Kinect. And then, the first algorithm that showed that
you could really do nice 3D reconstruction was KinectFusion, so I really recommend that you
google for KinectFusion or follow the link at the video to look at the original KinectFusion
video. It was for the first time that people showed
you can get really nicely looking 3D reconstructions in real time from the Kinect.
So KinectFusion uses ICP to track the camera pose. ICO stand for Iteratively Closest Point
and it is a really popular algorithm to align two point clouds. The problem here is of course
that we don't have point clouds or we have one point cloud from the sensor but we represent
a model using this signed distance function. So KinectFusion emulates a synthetic depth
image a synthetic depth cloud, and then, aligns these two using ICP.
And then, we said that this is of course not optimal because you need to emulate a depth
image. So can't we do that more direct? And then, we came up with the idea to estimate
the camera pose directly using the signed distance function and as you will see this
is a very efficient way and even more accurate than if you would first have to go via synthetic
depth images and then run ICP on that.
So now let's look at what signed distance functions actually are. Imagine that we have
a house that we want to reconstruct in 3D. And then we could define a function that has
the value of 0 exactly at the location of the surface of the house and that has negative
values outside of the house and positive values within.
And of course we can't represent the continuous function very well in a computer. So we would
just sample this function in a grid and this would give us a signed distance grid.
And now in this example the blue cells are negative cells outside of the object and the
cells with positive distances are within the object.
And now the next step of course is that we need to compute this signed distance function
from depth images. For the moment we try to compute it for a single depth image. And then,
we will extend that later to multiple depth images.
So the problem is that we want to estimate the value of all cells of our signed distance
function and that means that for every cell we have to estimate its distance to the surface.
Computing the euclidean distance is whether involve computationally but a very simple
approximation to that is the so called projective distance that you can just evaluate by projecting
every cell into the view of the camera, and then, looking up the depth value that you
observe at this point. And then, you can take the difference between these two and then
have an observed projective distance. This is not exactly the same as the euclidean
distance but it is good enough, at least if your opening angle is narrow enough. And this
is why we decided to use that.
And now the next step of course is that we have multiple depth images, so every voxel
is observed multiple times. And now what we do is we compute the weighted
average over all measurements. Which means that at every voxel we have to keep the sum
or the average distance and the sum of all weights. And then, with every new depth image
we can just update this two values. And then, we can do the same actually also
for the color. So we can compute the weighted average of every voxel in the color space.
And so for now we have assumed that we know the camera poses that's of course not true.
When we have a flying quadrotor. But we will look at this in a second. But first let's
look at how to actually visualize a signed distance volume.
There are different algorithms for actually doing that, KinectFusion used ray casting.
But a different method is to extract a mesh from it. A mesh has the advantage later that
you can easily import it in other programs like a CAD program for example. And then,
you can actually take measurements within your volume.
And one very popular algorithm for extracting a mesh from a signed distance function is
called marching cubes. And the basic idea behind this is that we need to find the zero
crossings in the signed distance function because we know that whenever the sign changes
we know that there must be a surface somewhere in between. We're switching from outside the
object to inside the object, and then, what marching cubes does is to interpolate distance values
of both of these voxels to find exactly the location of the estimated surface. And with
that you get a really good resolution that's typically much higher than your voxel grid
resolution and so you getting much smoother surfaces. And this works of course in 2D,
then it's called marching squares but it also works in 3D, then it is called marching cubes
because then you're looking at one cube at the time.
From there this gives you then vertices and faces that you can safe to a file for example
and your mesh is then represented as a list triangles.
Now the next step is that we need to estimate the camera pose and for that we assume that
we have already build the signed distance function from the first k frames. So this
means in the very beginning we would assume that we know the initial pose of the quadrotor,
say it could be located at the origin. And then, with every next frame we continue
as follows. So we were initializing then the signed distance function from the first frame
or from the first k frames. And then we get a new camera frame for which we don't know
the camera pose. Of course you could make a first prediction. Maybe just by assuming
that you have a constant velocity. So you're moving in the same direction as before or
you just assume zero velocity initializing it with the previous pose.
And then, the depth camera gives you a surface in 3D. And now our goal is of course to align
the surface to the surface that is stored in our signed distance function. And now KinectFusion
actually does this as follows. It simulates the synthetic depth image from your current
estimate of the camera pose and then runs ICP between the two to find the right camera
pose. And this is actually not necessary because
what ICP then in the end is doing is again computing distances of your reference model
to your target model. And this is actually not necessary, so we realized then when we
were looking at that that you can actually directly use signed distance functions to
read out these distances. So if you look very clearly now every part of the green line
should coincide with the zero crossing that we have in the signed distance function. And
when it is not lying on the zero crossing then our camera pose is not yet correct.
So what we try to achieve is make this green line match exactly the black line. And for
that we can formulate an energy function as follows. So every pixel on the depth image
can be projected into 3D space given a certain rotation and a translation. And that
gives us then a 3D coordinate in the world frame. And for this 3D coordinate we can look up
the distance value from our signed distance function. We can then spare it if we assume
that the noise is normal distributed or apply any other robust norm. And then, sum these
costs over all pixels i and j. And we of course seek to minimize this sum because we know
that our minimum should be at the place where this green line coincides with this zero crossing
in the signed distance function. And we minimize that using Gauss-Newton method
similar to what the KLT tracker has actually been using. And of course when you are optimizing
something like this remember that you have a minimum representation, so it makes sense
to represent this rotation matrix R here as angular velocities for example, because then
you have only three degrees of freedom instead of nine components of a rotation matrix.
And then, we can actually use this concept to perform mapping with a quadrotor. So as
we said before we equip the quadrotor with a depth camera and then we feed the depth
images that we get. We load then on to an external computer just because the on board
PC is not strong enough to do that at the moment. And we update the signed distance
function, and then, estimate the next camera pose. And then, we feedback this camera pose
to position control that then again runs on the quadrotor and that uses it then to follow
a trajectory. And then, actually only as a side product
we obtain this 3D model from the signed distance function even with color that we can then
use or that an architect could use to show how a room looks like.
And just to give you a few more examples, these are some of our lab spaces here in Munich.
So we flew a small rectangular shape with the quadrotor in one of the labs. And this
gives us then this 3D model of the world. You can recognize some of the desks, but
the important thing here is that this automatically has the right scale because the Kinect sensor
has a fixed baseline and so we know about the scale of the world. And so an architect
could directly measure the height of a table or the distance between walls.
This is another corner that we have in our lab with two sofas so if you are ever close
to Munich then please visit us and then you can see these sofas and the lab for real.
And an interesting thing then is that you can actually not only use that for 3D room
scanning with a quadrotor and position control but for an algorithm itself it does not matter
whether you scanning a room or you actually scanning an object or a person. And so we
figured that we can actually use that to scan persons in 3D. In this case we put the person
an a swivel chair that we rotated slowly and you can see in the upper left corner there
is the action light sensor and on the screen you get immediately a model of the person.
This part of the video shows now a little bit more detail. You can see how the 3Dmodel
is curved out while the camera is apparent is virtually moving around the object of course
not for real - the object rotates - but for the algorithm it doesn't matter whether the
camera moves or the world moves.
And then, the cool thing is this is the visualization of the underlying voxel grid. The cool thing
then is that you can also modify this signed distance functions very easily. You can add
components like this socket for example and you can make a model hollow on the inside.
And there is a good reason why you want to do that because the interesting thing is that you
can actually print these models then in 3D and in color. And that gives very nice figures
that you can then put in a book shelf or give to your parents as a present. So this is a
very simple technique to make 3D scans of objects. It can be a person but it can also
be a room.
And for this particular object we even launched a website called fablitec.com and if you're
interested to try this out for yourself then please navigate there and download a demo version.
To sum this up, today we have looked at depth cameras in combination with quadrotors. We've
introduced signed distance functions that are very powerful representations for 3D space when
you're dealing with depth cameras. We've look at methods to track the camera pose with respect
to a signed distance functions. And we have shown that we can actually use that for position
control of the quadrotor. And just as a side product here this gives
us, as I said, with marching cubes a mesh  that we can then pose process either by loading it into a CAD
program or to take measures of a building or to use it for person scanning and then
for person printing.