Hello and welcome everybody to week 8. As I promised in the beginning of the course
we will now focus in this last week mostly on recent research results mostly coming from
our group here. So we are very excited now to share these
slides with you and we hope that you enjoy this last week.
And our first topic in this video is a system for visual navigation for flying Parrot ArDrone.
We made this one fully available as open source so for those of you who have an ArDrone, and
I know that there are some of you around. You can actually try this out at home or in
your lab to better see how this works and to have fun with it and possibly of course
to extend it.
So as you know the Parrot ArDrone is a relatively low cost platform. It only costs 350 US dollar
so it's cheap to buy, but the pretty cool thing is and this makes it so attractive to
us, both in terms of research and also in education is that it is controllable via WIFI.
So the only thing that you need is a laptop and then you can connect over wireless to
the Parrot ArDrone and it will stream sensor data and you can stream back control commands.
And the good thing is that the manufacture decided to put everything, the API and the
communication protocols, open source. So it's very easy to access data and to control it
from a PC. And there are many different language bindings around. For us, we mostly develop
in C and C++. This is also the primary library that Parrot is providing.
But the community has released other bindings, for example to Python and a complete reimplementation
in JavaScript running in a web browser.
And this has fostered many different directions for research and also in our lab we started
roughly 3 years ago with Parrot ArDrones.
Now, when you start programming a robot, and the Parrot ArDrone is of course also a kind
of a robot, you need to need to setup a certain software architecture. In particular when
your software solution becomes more and more complex. And most of the time, I guess you
have already noted that, a large system contains multiple components you have state estimation,
you have control at different layers, and for all of that you like to write independent
modules that you can link together as you need it for your application. And this is
now where so called robot or so called software architectures come in. A good robot architecture
of course is modular because this allows you to reuse code that you have written before.
It is robust, which means that even if one of the components crashes that it doesn't
kill the whole robot. You know ideally if one thing crashes then it could either be
restarted, reinitialized or just switched off. This also means that you have some tools
to know whether something has crashed to inspect the state of the current system.
With a Parrot ArDrone you typically have the quadrotor itself in the air, but you also
have a base station and potentially other quadrotors at the same time. So a good robot
architecture should be decentralized such you can add more and more nodes and you rely
as little as possible on a centralized architecture.
As I said before the modular concept also facilitates the reuse. You like to separate
out as many independent libraries as possible to make it as simple to put together as possible.
A good architecture also needs to talk to the hardware of course. So you need some abstraction
of the hardware and underlying software libraries to provide a common interface that you can
switch one localization module with another one.
And this means that it's an advantage to define for certain common modules a fixed interface
or a fixed protocol of what information to exchange.
Another very important aspect is because this often won't run from the first day on. So
you need to debug it somehow. And that means if you have an architecture that helps you
with introspection. For example where you can switch on debugging output as you go or
where you can look at whether the individual modules are still running and how they are performing.
And then this greatly helps you.
Similarly it helps a lot if you can log your data to a file and then replay it just to
trace down some of the bugs this can help. But of course in the end you always have to
run everything on the real robot just to make sure that it really works.
Another aspect and that's often overlooked is of course that a good robot middleware should also be very
easy to learn and easy to extend.
And this means in particular because we have at least here now at university lots of new
students coming in every semester and robot architectures that are very hard to understand
because they are poorly documented or because there are no tutorials are really difficult
for students to learn. And so a good architecture facilitates that
and has some auto-documentation that makes it easy to navigate within it.
And such robot architectures are also called robotic middleware. They provide the infrastructure
between different modules, they regulate the communication between these modules and provide
such data logging facilities.
Some of these middlewares or probably all of them also help you with, as I said debugging
and a very important part is visualization of your data. In particular because you will
be often debugging things in 3D and rotation matrices are very hard to read as you know.
It's important that you have tools that simplify visualization of 3D geometry.
For example tools that can directly display transformations or trajectories and so on
and coordinate systems.
There are several such systems available, there are some open source ones and closed
ones. ROS, which is the abbreviation for Robot Operating System, which is certainly the most
popular one, so this is the one we are using. But there are other systems as well that have
quite some popularity still. Player/Stage, CARMEN has been around for a long time and
YARP and OROCOS are also good systems. OROCOS is in particular specialized on real time
control, so if you have hard real time constraints then probably OROCOS is a good thing
to look at.
And of course there are also all kinds of closed source solutions. They generally have
a better support and maintenance but they also cost money and it's sometimes hard to
know what of the modules do internally.
So this is just an example to show you how such an architecture could look like for a
navigation task.
Of course there is somewhere the robot at the very bottom which we need to talk to and
then there is typically a set of hardware drivers that gives us access to the raw data
from motors or our sensors. Then typically there is an abstraction layer
that just gives us images in general this is for example provided by ROS which provides
you a common message format for images and transformations. And then on top of that you
have all kinds of custom modules. For example that run localization or visual odometry,
then do global path planning, we might have a user interface, and then, at the end you
need controllers and potentially collision avoidance and subroutines and so on.
So this is the website for ROS, it's as I said one of the really good documented systems.
So if you're interested in going any further with quadrotors or with robotics in general,
then pleas have a look at ROS. There are very good tutorials, both video tutorials but also
written tutorials with very easy copy and paste code that you can quickly run to understand the
basic concepts. And the whole thing is completely open to
the community so it's very easy to extend and ask for help there.
And now let's look at how to actually implement a camera based navigation with the Parrot
ArDrone. The following slides now are summarizing our work that we presented at IROS 2012 and
we recently published a much larger article in the RAS journal just this year.
So this is the general architecture we have the quadrotor, as you know that talks over
wireless with our computer. There we receive images at 18 Hertz sometimes
20 depending on the WIFI connection. We also get IMU data from the quadrotor at a much
higher rate. And we send back control commands we chose to send them at 100 Hertz but sometimes
you would also like to reduce this value.
And then, on the laptop side, we have three parts, we have a monocular SLAM
system that actually runs our localization, then we have an Extended Kalman Filter that
fuses this visual localization with our IMU data and a PID controller that then generates
the control commands that we need for position control and waypoint following.
So let's first zoom in this monocular SLAM system for that we actually relied on an external
library that is also available as open source. The so called PTAM library - Parallel Tracking
And Mapping - of Klein and Murray published at ISMAR 2007.
And it's a so called visual SLAM system, SLAM stands for Simultaneous Localization And Mapping,
which means that we don't assume at all that we are given any prior map of the environment. But that the SLAM
algorithm has to bootstrap both the map and has to find its position within this map.
So because there is a dependency of localization and mapping, and mapping again depends on
good camera poses this is also sometimes called a chicken and egg problem.
The general idea behind this PTAM library is now to extract visual features in the images
and then to match these visual feature between the key frames.
I don't want to go too much into the details here. We added some references on edx for
a longer explanation of PTAM and SLAM in general but for the moment just assume that with that
system we are able to use PTAM to find the camera poses at the same
time simultaneously estimating feature points in the world.
And the cool thing about this PTAM library is that it is highly efficient and available
as open source so it's just a plug and play module that we can use whenever you have a
monocular single camera to generate a map, a sparse feature map but a map. And to localize
our camera with respect to that in real time.
And this PTAM is in principle split into two processes, there is one process that estimates
the camera pose in hard or less hard real time and a second thread that does not run
in real time and optimizes the map. And the map optimization problem gets more and more
complicated the more key frames you're adding, so while initially this process also runs
in real time as soon as you add more and more key frames and features it gets slower and
slower. These two images show you a quick feeling for how this looks like.
We have the video feed from the quadrotor as visualized on the left side. It detects
corners in it, so called FAST corners, and then it tracks, like the KLT tracker, these
features to the images through the video stream and tries to estimate the 3D position of these
features and the camera poses. And this is visualized in here on the middle
in this 3-dimensional view. You can see these 3D point features just depicted in red and
the camera poses depicted in its coordinate system further on the left.
And then we extended PTAM in two ways first we linked PTAM with the Kalman Filter that
integrates also the information from the IMU and simplifies then the pose recovery once
the tracking is lost in PTAM. And we also added a scale estimation method that allows
us to get absolute scale for a monocular map. And the problem there is that in general if
you only sensor is a camera then you never know how large your world is because the
camera motion could be very small and then the world could be very small or camera motions
could be very large and then the world could be very large.
Just from a monocular camera you can't tell about the absolute scale of the world.
Because we have this IMU data in particular the ultrasound measurements to the floor we
have an absolute measurement that allows us then to estimate the scale of the monocular
map as well.
This Kalman filter then in the middle is just as you know it the only difference is that
it has a slightly larger state vector. We track the 3D position, the 3D velocities,
the attitude, the speed of attitude and the yaw speed in its state.
And then, instead of having a simple delay free model we calibrated our motion model
more carefully. So we know exactly how our controls influence the attitude and then how
the attitude influences the speed and that again the position. And that gives us a much
better prediction then what we had now before. The other very important part is that the
Kalman Filter also allows us to compensate for the delays. We have looked at that in
lecture 4. I think using the Smith Predictor, so the idea is just using prediction steps
of the Kalman Filter to predict a little bit into the future and then to pass this pose
in the future on to the PID controller that then virtually runs without delay. This is
now a visualization of this time delay problem. In contrast to what we look at in lecture
4 we have actually three different sources of information all of them have different
time delays. So the problem here is that the PTAM pose comes in with the largest delay
because we need to transform the images and then we need to run PTAM on this image. And
this means we generally have more than hundred milliseconds time delay between the PTAM pose
and our current point at time. We getting also the IMU readings and those come with
two different delays as Jakob actually found out and we're modeling this properly. Then
we have a Kalman Filter that does updates every five milliseconds or so and the thing
is now, whenever we get a new observation we have to roll back the whole EKF, so we
store the full state of the EKF for one second or so and whenever a new measurement comes
in we roll back the state and then integrate the measurements again and make a prediction
slightly to the future. And the reason for that is even if we would
estimate our state at the last point where we received the last observation then our
pose prediction would still be late and we would have this delay in the PID controller
and so what we do is we extrapolate our pose roughly every five milliseconds into the future
just to accommodate for the transmission delays from WIFI and the time it takes for the quadrotor
to actually responds.
And then on the PID side or the controller side we just run a very simple
PID controller. The set point that we give to the PID controller is a position in 3D
and a yaw angle. And then, Jakob implemented some high-level control routines to either
hover at a particular desired position or that you can run in assisted control mode, where you
have a Cartesian joystick so to speak that allows you to move the quadrotor in world
coordinates instead of local coordinates and you can follow waypoints.
And this looks now as follows this is a video that we took at the open day in 2011. Here
the quadrotor is in the middle of the air. It has a set point that it tries to maintain
and Jakob is continuously pushing it away and as you can see the quadrotor realizes
that by returning over to its original pose. And this is a quite robust demo so you can
run it as I said also at home or in your lab. But it's also a nice thing to show to people
and then you can show on the computer screen how the raw data looks like of the quadrotor.
And this is now a visualized little bit in more detail here in the second video. First
of course we can hold the position that is here indicated with this red cross. And then,
you can see now in the bottom left the 3D map with the camera poses of the key frames
and the 3D visual features. And on the right side you see the life view from the quadrotor.
you can see the features that it found in the world and the features that it successfully
matched with world points in 3D that it uses to estimate its pose.
And you can see that the quadrotor is even then able to return to its hovering point
when you occlude all sensors for a little while. So in this case the odometry doesn't
give you any useful information you completely lost in principle. But because PTAM has a
relocalization ability it can recover then at least if it looks into the right direction
of the scene. But it can even then recover if this is not the case because we still have
the gyroscopes from the IMU that tell us in which direction we're looking at.
So in this video you can now see how the map is actually initialized in the very beginning
so the map is completely empty. The quadrotor takes off and while it takes off it initializes
the key points using a KLT tracker. And once it has an initialized map it continuously
extends it with new key frames and new key points. And you can see that you can fly arbitrary
figures. This is also one of the basic functionalities. There is even a small scripting language that
allows you to fly arbitrary figures as the ArDrone.
And the cool thing is because we know the scale of the world this hose or this figure
here really has absolute scale. So we can define beforehand how many meters we want
the quadrotor to fly to the left or to the right.
So to summarize this video I showed you now some of our videos on the Parrot ArDrone, we've
introduced ROS as a really good middleware that I would recommend you to use. I've introduced
briefly PTAM as a monocular SLAM module that you can just use out of the box. But we didn't
go much into the details here. As I said there will be some links after this video to get
more information about PTAM if you're interested. And then, we showed this working system that
enabled visual navigation with the Parrot ArDrone. It can fly relatively fast and accurate
to given way points. And as I said there is full source code and documentation available on
www.ros.org.