Hello and welcome to video 6.3. In the previous video we've introduced the
Kalman Filter (KF) and the Extended Kalman Filter (EKF). And I know that things have
been pretty theoretical there and this is why we have now in this video a whole bunch
of nice visualization and a pretty nice example on how EKF looks like in practice.
So imagine that we have a robot that is moving in 2D, and then, as you know we can describe
its state with 3 parameters because it has x position, y position and an orientation
or heading psi. And this robot can move around, we assume
it's a quadrotor so it can move in all directions arbitrarily so it can move forward with a
speed of x dot, move sideward using a speed of y dot, and it can rotate around its axis
using a speed of psi dot.
And furthermore, we assume that the robot makes occasionally observations. And again
it sees a visual marker with its camera and it can determine its pose relative to the
robot. So it sees a marker at a particular position
x and y in a particular orientation psi.
And now it is important to note that we represent the state in global coordinates, so this x
and y and psi are with respect to a global coordinate frame that is located somewhere
in the world. But our odometry and the visual observation of the marker are given in the
local frame of the robot, which is typically the case with a robot, depends on your sensors,
but typically all sensor measurements are made in the intrinsic frame of the robot.
When the robot goes forward it doesn't care about where the origin of the world is. It
just goes forward within its own coordinate frame. And the same applies typically to observations
of its sensors because it has a camera and in its camera image it sees somewhere the marker, so
it's relative to its camera. This is not always the case I should say for
example, if we look at GPS then you always get global coordinates but for most sensors
like for ultrasound and cameras actually you make local observations.
And we've discussed this in depth already in week two, so if you feel confused in this
example by the coordinate transforms and the representations, then please go back to this
video to get more details, and there are also some very nice exercises that you can do to
refresh your knowledge of coordinate transforms.
So in any case, this is our representation of the state and now the next question is,
We need to specify two things, namely
our motion function and our sensor function. And you have seen that before, the motion
function depends on our previous state and our current control that we give.
And now we need to transform the speeds in the global frame. So we can say that our new
x position depends on the previous x position times this odometry speed rotated by our current
heading angle times the time interval between which we get these odometry updates.
The same holds of course for the y axis and for our heading we have a much simpler expression,
because we can just add up our previous heading plus the rotation speed times our time interval.
So this is clearly nonlinear because we have
sine and cosine in the formula in our motion function. And to be able to run the EKF we
need now to linearize this motion function and as we have seen in the previous video
for that we need to compute the derivative motion function, which means that we derive
this function with respect to our current state.
Which gives us then a matrix and this means that we end up with a 3 by 3 matrix in this
case where the columns correspond to the derivatives with respect to x, y, and psi.
And the rows correspond to the rows that we had before giving our successor state in x,
y, and psi again.
So I think we also have such an exercise prepared for you where you have to specify the motion
function and derive something like this on yourself.
For the sensor model we also need to construct this sensor function or observation function.
But his is a bit more complicated because we have to convert between this divergent
coordinate systems.
And this is as follows: imagine that we now where the marker is located in global coordinates.
And now we know that somebody has attached a marker at 2 meters distance from the origin
and this marker is oriented into a certain direction. You need to know that to be able
to compute the position of the robot if it sees this marker somewhere.
So this is given a priori the marker location and global world coordinates is given a priori.
And then, the robot makes local observations of this marker and uses this knowledge of
where the marker is in the global coordinate frame to update its position estimates.
And now, for being able to use this and the Kalman Filter we need to define this observation
function, which given the state of our robot x determines the sensor observation z.
And because our sensor makes observations in its local frame we need to compute the
pose of the marker relative to the robot. And this can be done as follows, I mean there
are different ways of computing this, but this is I thought maybe the most intuitive
one. So first we can construct the transformation
matrix that corresponds to our global robot pose. You have seen that before in week two.
Given our x, y, and psi of the current state we can construct this 3 by 3 transformation
matrix, remember the upper left part is the rotation matrix, 2 by 2 in this case, and
the upper right vector, x and y is our translation vector.
And now we can use that to transform coordinates from the local system to global system. So
in our case we are actually giving global coordinates from which we need to infer the
local coordinates. And this can be done by inverting x. But as you remember from week
tow, there is a very efficient way we can transpose the rotation matrix and replace
the translation part with minus rotation matrix transposed times t.
And if we fill in the values or if we fill in the formulas then we and up now with the
following observation function. So the first two components are just the local
translation vector of where we expect the marker to be seen by the robot given its global
coordinates. And for the orientation we can just compute the difference between the global
marker orientations minus our current heading of the robot. And this gives us then the local
heading of the marker.
And now, again for the Extended Kalman Filter we need to derive this observation function
because it's again nonlinear, similar to the motion model. So we need to derive this with
respect to all components of our state. So we derive x with respect to x, y, and psi.
And then again, we obtain such a 3 by 3 matrix which is called the Jacobian. And this is
what you then plug into our EKF.
So just to pinpoint again the interesting parts. We have constructed the motion model
g which we can directly fill in here. We have derived g with respect to the state which
gave us this matrix capital G that we plugin here.
We have derived our sensor model, which we plugin then in this equation and we have derived
the sensor model which gives us capital H that we need to compute the Kalman Gain.
So now we come finally to a few demo runs of our extended Kalman Filter that we have
constructed on the previous slides using the sensor model and the motion model as explained.
We visualize now the state of the robot using this black circle with the black line. This
visualization shows our mean estimate of the pose of the robot.
So it shows the position in x and y, and it shows our mean estimate of its orientation.
And this robot now goes around given a sequence of commands. We assume at the moment that
we don't have any observations. So we just run the prediction step or the motion update
of the Kalman Filter until the end.
And then, the interesting thing is that we can also visualize the uncertainty or this
covariance within the Kalman filter. So in this simulation we assume that the robot is
absolutely certain that it starts at the origin of the world, but the further it goes the
less certain it gets on its position. So the blue ellipse now denotes its uncertainty.
For example depending on which isoline you draw this could be the 95% isoline which means
that the probability mass within the circle has 95% of the total mass.
And now, after the first 10 steps for example, we give a rotation command to the robot so
it will turn by 90 degrees and move around and then move on. And as you can see the uncertainty
here of the robot state grows infinitely with every step the robot gets a little bit
less certain about where it is. But other than that, because we don't get any updates
we assume our zero mean noise assumption says we follow exactly the controls that we have
given to the robot. Now for this example now we just assume that
there is a large process noise for x and y in the odometry.
If we now additionally assume that we also have noise in our heading then the following
happens. I let this run for a few steps. So the interesting difference now is that
the uncertainty in y direction increases dramatically. I should say here that we still have the same
noise in x and y direction. But this new uncertainty comes now from the fact that the robot is
additionally uncertain about its current heading. So it doesn't really no, whether it's still
looking perfectly to the right or whether it has already turned to the left or to the
right. And also if it would go forward this would lead to a different position along the
y axis. And this is why this ellipse grows much more in y direction than it does in x
direction. And now here in this step the robot turns in y direction by 90 degrees and moves
on. Now it seems that this covariance actually rotates. This is actually not the case, so what
happens here is that we have a very large uncertainty in y direction plus the uncertainty
in our heading direction. And so the more the robot moves now the less certain it gets
again in x direction, in left right direction, you know along its motion. And so we actually
have an overlay of both the uncertainty in y direction that we had before plus new uncertainty
along the x direction now. And the combination of this two give this new ellipsoid.
And you can see that in combination now the heading uncertainty this ellipse really grows
massively, so the robot is absolutely uncertain after it does the round where it is located.
So and now we will add some observations, for that we assume that the robot can observe
a marker in the world. But this marker can only been seen by the
robot if it is close enough, so at this distance it cannot see the marker, and so the uncertainty
grows as before. So it starts at the origin and moves to the right and the uncertainty
grows. Now when it comes close to the marker it can
actually detect it for a while. And what we can see now is that the uncertainty shrinks
again because as long as it sees the marker it is perfectly certain or it is more certain
about its position than before. And then when it loses the visual contact
to the marker the uncertainty grows again as before.
Just to see this again, the uncertainty grows, when it detects the marker the uncertainty
shrinks and when it loses again the visual contact to the marker the uncertainty grows again.
So far we've assumed now that the robot has a good initial guess of its starting position.
And now, let's assume that we don't have a good guess. So the robot is actually still
moving from the origin indicated by these red crosses here but our Kalman Filter because
it has been initialized with a incorrect initial guess is actually moving at a different location.
So now the robot moves and has a growing covariance as before.
And then, as soon as it detects the marker it can actually compute or correct its position using the marker observation.
And then, you can see that it gets on track quite quickly and if it now moves around then
it remains on track because it had this observation.
So you can see how this marker pulls the state estimate to the right location.
And now, we additionally assume that our yaw estimate is wrong and we assume that we have
some noise on our yaw estimate, so we get again this ellipsoid as before but as you
can see we are relatively far away from the true position indicated by the red cross.
But now again, as soon as we detect the marker the Kalman Filter pulls us to the right location
and decreases correctly the covariance of the EKF.
And then again, as soon as we lose visual contact to the marker the covariance grows
again with the behavior that we have seen before.
So I've indicated this already before, if we have a bad initial guess then it is generally
a good idea, typically you don't know really where you are in the beginning, but just set the inital Sigma
to a large value. Because this means then that you state estimate is extremely uncertain
and this means that as soon as you get the first sensor observation that you will immediately
trust it because then your sensor is more accurate than your current estimate of your
the state. So for example here, we start with a relatively large ellipsoid and as you can
see the red crosses lies within this ellipsoid which is typically what we want. The real
state should be at a higher probability within your covariance ellipsoid and as soon as we
see the marker it converges on the right location. And if you would compare this plot now with the
plot that we had before then you could see that it converges much faster to marker because
the marker gets more weight because it is actually intersecting the uncertainty,
the observation of the marker, which is a Gaussian with our state estimate, which is
Gaussian again. And then we trust of course more to the Gaussian with the smaller covariance.
The main difference to the previous plot is that it converges faster because now our uncertainty
of the state is so large that we will trust the marker observation immediately.
Now one last example again, we have a wrong initialization. The marker is now located
in the middle and whenever the robot comes close enough it sees this marker and can reduce
its uncertainty.
So to summarize the video of today, we have given a nice visualization or a 2D example
of the Extended Kalman Filter. We have shown all steps of the derivation
of the motion model and the construction and derivation of the sensor model. And we have
discussed several example runs of the Kalman Filter.