Welcome, everybody, to the fourth and last part
of videos for the first lecture this week
on Autonomous Navigation for Flying Robots.
So this video will be fun because we've
collected lots of video clips that
showcase a little bit of the progress
and history of Quadrotor Research over the past years.
So as all of you know, the history of aviation
started with fixed wing airplanes.
In 1903, the Wright brothers performed
the first successful flight-- motorized
flight-- with their airplane.
The general idea of an airplane is
that you have a special shape of the wing that
produces a lift when you move forward at a high speed.
And in this way, the plane gets
lifted-- experiences a lift-- and you
can control the attitude of the plane
by flaps that are installed in the wings
but also at the end of the plane.
Planes are very successful and are technologically
well understood.
Probably everybody of you have already flown with an airplane.
It's relatively fuel efficient but one significant problem
there is that you always need a runway to achieve
the speed that is high enough to actually take off.
And similarly for landing, you also need a runway.
You can't just land somewhere, wherever you want.
Another problem also is that you can't
stop in the middle of the air.
You can't just stay at a certain position.
You always have to move forward to be sure that you have enough
speed so that your wings generate enough lift.
This is then what motivated people to look for, or develop
so-called vertical takeoff and landing devices.
And interestingly, the first such vehicle
was built in 1924, 10 years before the helicopter.
And this first device actually was a quadrotor.
The problem however, with a quadrotor
is that if you don't have any electronic control then
it's extremely hard to stabilize the flight.
You can imagine this is you have four different joysticks, then
that you have to control all by yourself and that makes it,
of course, very hard then to fly in a purposeful way
and not to crash.
Therefore, quadrotors were not very successful at that time
and then, as I said, roughly 10 years later in 1936
the helicopter-- first helicopter
had it's first successful flight.
The idea there is that instead of having four rotors that
are hard to control, you just have
one main rotor in the middle and by a very intelligent, or very
smart mechanical construction this rotor can adjust
the pitch of the propeller, depending
on the current orientation, or a current rotation
angle of this main rotor and that leads then
to different thrust in different regions around the helicopter.
And with that, you can control the pitch and roll.
And with this design, it becomes possible to navigate,
relatively easy to navigate manually.
Of course, you still need a skilled human pilot,
but this can be done so only a single person can do it.
One problem obviously, is that, as you
remember from the previous video,
that if you have only a single rotor that
uses a torque on your vehicle.
So if you wouldn't do anything else,
you would start turning around your own axis.
And this is why a helicopter has a second tail rotor that
then compensates for this torque.
The good thing about helicopters is
that they are easy to fly by a pilot.
But a disadvantage is that you need
this relatively-- mechanically-- relatively complicated
swash plate in the middle.
And also the rotor blades are relatively large
and that makes it relatively dangerous
when you come close to buildings.
For example because if you get-- if you touch something--
then you'll probably crash.
But nevertheless, helicopters and planes
were the most used aerial vehicles
until maybe 10 or 15 years ago.
Because those were the only vehicles
that you could fly and control easily yourself,
using a remote control or using a joystick.
This changed dramatically when with the development
of new MEMS sensors that appeared in end of 90s
and the beginning of 2000s.
Because that then suddenly enabled
hobbyists to develop micro aerial vehicles that
could do the attitude stabilization on board
using such sensors.
And then that lead to the development
of the first remote controlled quadrotors
that were actually relatively easy to fly.
And then of course people started
to add cameras to the quadrotors and use that
for recalling extremely impressive flights.
This one was recorded in New York, for example.
And in the quadrotor you can come--
because it's an unmanned vehicle-- you
can come relatively close to such structures
or to the buildings.
You don't have to be afraid that the pilot could get hurt,
You can really create stunning views from above.
And this is a technique that has become quite popular now
among photographers and movie makers.
Many stunt scenes in the new James Bond movie for example,
have been recorded from quadrotors.
Also during sporting events partially
quadrotors are used that then remote controlled
by the photographer.
Of course the development continued then
in this direction.
By just adding a camera that can transmit the video signal,
you can actually get to very nice aerial views
and a very immersive experience of that.
This group here for example from Sweden,
used an Oculus Rift device in combination
with a quadrocoptor to get a live stereo view of the world
around them.
It's actually an octocopter.
And then you get an image like this for seeing this now live,
you would have to-- need an Oculus,
but you can imagine that this is sort of a system like this
you can have lots of fun when you're flying around.
And as nice as all of this is, it
is still remote controlled, and so there the main question
for us, in the remainder of this course,
is how can we actually achieve autonomous flight.
And also people in universities have
started to look at this problem and initially
then used external positioning aids
like a GPS system for example for outdoor flying or motion
capture systems for indoor flying.
So GPS is relatively easy to receive.
The only problem is that it's not very accurate
and that you don't get too frequent position updates.
Maybe you can read it at 2 Hz or so, depending on your receiver.
This is different if you go indoor.
If you have a motion capture system,
then usually you get poles updates at 200 to 500 Hz
and you get you can get down up to a millimeter accuracy,
for example.
And if you have to position then of course
you can ride the controller that moves
to the quadrotor to the desired goal location.
But even if you fine tune your controller as good
as you can from a theoretical point of view,
if you run it for the first time you
will notice that the quadrotor will not exactly
perform the trajectory that you've been hoping for.
And so you need some training or adaptation of the flight
parameters of dynamic calibration,
of the dynamic parameters, to actually make
the quadrotor perform the trajectory you desire.
Then when you have done that, when
you have a good calibration and you can really
do impressive things, for example.
You can perform flips with the quadrotor,
but you can also fly very accurately to certain positions
and through, for example, through windows.
And this is now probably for the first time we are-- quadrotors
really exceeded, where autonomous quadrotors exceeded
the capabilities of manual pilots.
So a manual pilot would have a very hard time here
to do something similar.
But of course with a computer you can train and plan
motion trajectories that are very complicated
and that for example allow a quadrotor
to fly through such a window.
It's interesting to note here that the quadrotor cannot--
it's not-- stable in this position.
So as you know, it's only stable if you're leveled horizontally.
As soon as you are moving vertically, for example, then
you can only hold this position for a very short period
of time.
You can increase this or you can adapt
that to pinpoint playing, for example.
This is a video from the flying machine arena at ETH Zurich.
Here two quadrotors are tracked at the same time
by motion capture studio and also the ball is tracked.
And then you can develop algorithms
that can control a quadrotor fast enough that it actually
returns a ball.
And with that you can create a tennis companion, for example,
that could play ping pong with you.
Another really cool video that probably inspired
lots of people to see more in quadrotors than just toys
was this video from the GRASP Laboratory
at the University of Pennsylvania.
It was shown for the first time that you can actually
build larger structures by using a quadrotor.
So here it's still a motion capture system
used to track the position of the quadrotor,
and so this allows you to get to the position of the quadrotor
but also the position of all the parts that you want to move.
With that, it becomes possible to construct such a structure
that you could think of building larger structures on roofs,
for example, of buildings that are
hard to reach otherwise, and so on.
And another cool thing of course about quadrotors or robots
in general is that it scales very well, so
if you can do it with one robot and it's also
interesting to think about how to do it in teams of robots.
And the execution time, or time to completion of course
decreases linearly, ideally, if you
have more robots at your disposal.
So this was a very nice video and this then convinced
many robotics labs to start working
on autonomous quadrotors and similar problems.
And then another thing that of course also happened
at the same time was miniaturization.
So instead of having large quadrotors,
you can try to make them as small as possible,
as lightweight as possible.
This has a number of advantages.
They are smaller, they need less space, they make less noise,
they are less fragile.
And they are of course also less dangerous for humans.
And then you can again train the dynamics model and so on.
And when you have multiple robots,
then you can do a formation flight.
Cooperate between these robots for example
to make them move coordinatedly through a window.
So this is now an array of four by five nano quadrocopters.
It's very interesting to look at it.
You can do fun stuff with them.
But also the path planning problem
gets much more complicated if you
have to deal with 25 robots instead of one.
The next thing then is that you would
like to have a natural interface to interact
with such quadrotors.
You can't preprogram all the motions that you want.
You don't want to use a computer interface for that.
And this work here, which was a student project at ETH,
showed that you can use, for example, a Kinect
sensor for tracking a person and then
the person can, in a very intuitive way,
specify the target position for the quadrotor.
So all of these are very cool sites.
But it's clear that for real applications,
external motion capture systems are somewhat impractical.
And so the question is how they can
do the same, also with onboard sensors?
And of course the one of the simplest answers
is just to use a GPS receiver.
We will also deal with that in some
of exercises in this course.
An alternative is to use a laser scanner for example.
But this is relatively heavy and relatively expensive to use.
So we strongly focus, in our research group at least,
on using cameras.
Also including depth cameras like the Kinect
for getting good 3-D models and optical maps for autonomous
navigation.
So the goal in general both of course for this lecture
but also for our research in general
is that we want to enable flying robots
to operate fully autonomously in 3-D environments.
And for that we want to use primarily the onboard sensors
and then in particular an onboard camera
because it's relatively lightweight sensor
and it provides rich data about environment.
Then of course we need to focus on all kinds of subproblems
including, that we will also partially cover here
in this lecture, and including 3-D navigation but also
localization.
The quadrotor needs to know of course where it is.
We need a 3-D reconstruction of the environment
we are operating in.
Simply to avoid obstacles.
But also to be able to plan trajectories,
find the shortest path between two points and so on.
Then at a higher level, we are also
interested in exploration often seen
and semantic scene understanding and of course an intuitive user
interfaces.
For example to be able to follow a person automatically
and to understand the gestures of a person.
So the instructors of this course
are, it's me and Daniel, Professor Daniel Cremers.
You have support of one of our Ph.D. students Christian Kerl,
and two of our master students Julian Tatsch,
and Jonas Jelton who will help us with the exercises.
Our Computer Vision Group here at TUM
has more members of course.
So next two Professor Cremers and me
are two more post-Docs and 11 Ph.D. students.
And of course we have a whole bunch
of master students working on all kinds of problems.
So our research topics are not only
quadrotors and depth cameras.
We're also looking at Visual SLAM of course and then 3D
reconstruction, but also image segmentation and scene
understanding shape matching.
For example, if you try to find correspondences
between two or three shapes.
And more generally, however we have
people working on convex optimization
of all kinds of problems for example
in optical flow or motion estimation, super resolution,
and so on.
So in the remainder of this video,
I just want to show you a few of the research results
that we did over the past years.
This is actually one of our first videos on quadrotors.
And this was the master thesis project
of Jakob Engel, who's standing here in the middle.
And he used a Parrot AR.Drone in combination with PTAM,
with the PTAM library to build an initial map
of the environment and then use that map
to localize the quadrotor.
And then even if you push away the quadrotor from it's set
point it's automatically able to find back
to it's designated location.
In this video you can see a bit more details on the approach.
In the middle you can see the quadrotor
flying in a typical environment.
In the bottom right to see you get the live view
from the quadrotor that is being used by PTAM
to build up initial map.
It just extracts visual features,
so-called fast corners in this case,
and then triangulates them and optimizes their 3-D poles
to obtain a so-called feature based three dimensional map,
which is visualized on the left side.
And with this visual map it can quite correctly
recover and find its position and then use
that for flying back to its poles.
Another problem is, of course that if you only have PTAM,
pure PTAM only recovers or learns a 3-D map up to scale
because with just a single monocular camera,
you cannot infer how large the world is.
But because the AR.Drone has this ultrasound sensor,
it can measure the distance from the ground and also
its absolute horizontal speed.
And by using these measurements, it
becomes possible to estimate the real scale of the world.
And then with that, fly figures, fly automatically
figures that have a fixed size in the environment.
So for this figure, for example, you
can specify beforehand how large the sides of the holes are.
Then we also have been working with the AscTec Pelican
platform.
Here, this was a paper that we submitted to RSS,
and published at RSS last year.
Here we have a Kinect/Asus sensor mounted on the quadrotor
and from the data from this sensor
we are able to estimate the poles of the quadrotor
in real time, but also generate a 3-D-- a dense 3-D map
of the environment.
And as you can see from this model,
this would already be quite useful for an architect
to take some measurements, for example, to decide how large,
how high the table is or how much space you
have in the kitchen for an additional cabinet.
We're also interested in 3-D reconstruction in general.
Not only from quadrotor data, but also from handheld data.
This is work done by Frank Steinbrucker
on large scale 3-D reconstruction.
This is actually the corridor of our group in Munich,
so if you ever come visit us, you
might recognize some of the offices.
and it would be of course very nice
if you could do that automatically
with a fleet of quadrotors at some point.
So if you'd like to know more about our research
or our group in general, you're welcome to visit our website
at vision.in.tum.de.
We provide there the full length papers of our research.
We also publish some code and open source.
So If you'd like to try out some of our approaches by yourself,
then you're welcome to do so.
We also have a YouTube channel on which
we provide lecture videos from the previous years.
And also some research videos that accompany all the papers
that we published.
We also have a Facebook page if you
want to stay updated on news and things
that are going on in our group.
And of course you can also meet us
at scientific conferences and workshops.
We're actually regularly present at ICRA and IROS and RSS,
which are robotics conferences.
And we are also present of course
at the Computer Vision Conferences such as ICCV, CVPR.
The European Computer Vision Conference ECCV
and the German Computer Vision conference, GCPR.
With that, I hope I have interested you in this course.
I hope I see most of you back next week
when we look at linear algebra and 3-D geometry which
will form the basis for the remainder of this course.
We also look then a little bit at sensors and actuators
that are used on quadrotors.
Good.
Have a nice week, then, and see you back soon.