Hello and welcome back to lecture 2.2 on 2D geometry.
In this video I will introduce the basic concepts of 2D points and lines, and we will discuss
how to transform these entities using 2D transformations.
As you all know we can represent 2D points, as a 2D vector which we will denote by a
boldface x. This vector has two components x and y, which represent the coordinates of this
2D point. We can also represent the same 2D point by what's called an augmented vector.
This is a 3D vector where the first two components represent this point, the coordinates.
And the third component is just 1. This vector we will denote by x bar.
At a first glance this makes things more complicated seemingly, but as we will see in this video
it actually simplifies calculations, such as intersecting lines and points, and such
as representing transformations of these points in terms of simple matrix-vector products.
Furthermore, we can introduce a representation for 2D points the same 2D point by what's
called a homogeneous coordinates, sometimes also called projective coordinates. These
are 3D vectors that have three independent components, but the key idea is that two homogenous
vectors that only differ by scale actually represent the same 2D point.
We can then convert back from homogenous to inhomogeneous coordinates, simply by dividing
through the last element. So here for example, if you have a homogenous
vector with components x tilde, y tilde, w tilde, dividing by the last component w tilde
gives you back the 2D coordinates x and y representing this point.
In particular, of course with homogeneous coordinates, w tilde can become 0. Assume
we have a point x tilde with this three components, and we now let w tilde go to 0. Then the point
coordinates x and y of this point move towards infinity, and so for w tilde equals 0 these
points are called "points at infinity" or "ideal points", and they then in fact represent
a direction in space.
We can represent lines as you all know by some offset from the origin and some direction
of the line. In this class we will use a homogeneous coordinate
vector l tilde to represent lines. It contains three components a, b, c, and the idea is
that any point on the line, written in this augmented vector x bar is on the line, if
and only if it is orthogonal to l tilde. So the scalar product of x bar and l tilde
being just ax + by + c must be 0.
Of course, again as with homogeneous coordinates for points, here as well two vectors represent
the same line if they only differ by scaling. In particular this allows us to define a normalized
line equation, where the homogeneous coordinate vector l tilde, representing the line, is
chosen such that the first two components define the normal vector, so a unit vector
be that is orthogonal to the line. And then the third component here d is simply the offset
from the origin.
With homogeneous coordinates we can very easily define a line connecting to points. So if
we represent these two points x_1 and x_2, in terms of homogeneous coordinates, then
the line connecting them is simply given by the cross-product of the homogeneous coordinate vectors.
Similarly if we want to define the intersection
of two lines, represented in homogeneous coordinates by l_1 tilde and l_2 tilde.
Then the point in their intersection is given by the cross-product of this two vectors. And so here you can see
how things like intersecting lines or connecting points with a line can be very easily done
in homogeneous or projective coordinates.
Similarly these projective coordinates help to model 2D transformations of points or lines.
Here the simplest transformation you can think of is a transformation is a 2D translation.
That is a vector x is translated to a vector x' simply by adding an offset vector t.
That's a 2D vector representing this offset. We can represent the same transformation as
a matrix-vector product once we write the vector x as an augmented vector. Again the
third component being 1. Then this x + t can be written as a matrix-vector product with
a 2 by 3 matrix where the first block is an identity matrix and the last column is the
2D translation vector t.
If we write both the input and output in homogeneous coordinates x tilde and x tilde prime, then
the transformed vector is obtained from the original vector x tilde by a matrix multiplication
with a 3 by 3 matrix that contains in the upper left corner an identity matrix, the
upper right part of the last column is the translation vector and below we have 0s and 1.
We can generalize the translation by adding a rotation, this leads to what's called a
rigid body motion or a euclidian transformation. And in standard 2D coordinates we can write
it as Rx + t. In homogenous coordinates, again we can just write it as a matrix-vector product.
Where the upper left hand corner is the rotation matrix R, containing cosine and sine in for
a 2D transformation of this angle Theta the rotation angle. So this is an orthogonal matrix.
i.e. RR^T = I and it has determinant +1. And again in this matrix the 3 by 3 matrix
defining this Euclidian transform the upper right hand corner we have the translation vector t.
It's actually quit useful that you can write transformations as matrix-vector products,
because it allows you to very elegantly concatenate transformations. So if you concatenate two
rigid body transformations, then it simply amounts to a matrix product of the two matrices.
Rigid body transformations are transformations which preserve distances and angles, and vice versa.
One can actually show that any transformation which does preserve distances and angles is
in variably a rotation plus translation.
We can generalize this rigid body transformation by introducing a scaling by a scalar little s here.
And that leads to what calls a similarity transform that consists of a translation and
a scaled rotation. We can write it again in homogeneous coordinates
as a matrix-vector product, where the upper left hand corner is the scaled rotation matrix s times R.
Similarity transforms no longer preserve length because of a potentially non-uniform scaling s
but they still preserve angles, as shown in the upper right hand side. So a square
for example can be transformed to a rectangle.
We can further generalize the similarity transform by replacing the rotation matrix in the upper
left hand corner by an arbitrary matrix, 2 by 2 matrix. And this leads to what is called
an affine transformation. As you can see in a homogenous coordinates this transformation
has 6 parameters. And in particular what is preserved in an affine transformation is that
parallel lines remain parallel. So angles are no longer preserved in general,
length is not preserved, but parallel lines remain parallel.
We can further generalize the affine transformation to the most generic 2D linear transformation,
and that in homogeneous coordinates. And that is called the homography or projective transformation
and that can be written by a matrix large H tilde, which is a homography matrix and this
is a 3 by 3 matrix containing 9 elements, but you should remember that we working in
homogeneous coordinates.  Meaning that two vectors are identical if the only differ by scaling.
That implies for two homograph matrices, if the only differ by scaling they actually correspond
to the same projective transformation. What is preserved in a homography or projective
transformation is that straight lines remain straight lines. So as you can see here in
the upper right hand drawing, in the homography transformation of the rectangle: parallel
lines do not have to remain to be parallel, but straight lines will always remain straight.
What have we learned in this video and lecture, we learned about 2D points and 2D line, in
particular we learned about homogeneous or projective coordinates for points and lines,
and we saw that these coordinates drastically facilitate the study of 2D transformations.
In particular we studied transformations like the translation, the ridged body motion,
the similarity transformation, the affine transformation and the most general case the homography or
projective transformation.
In the next video we will study these entities and aspects on a particular example. And this
will then lead us to an exercise, where you can learn to apply these techniques in geometry.
Thank you