Hello and welcome everybody to lecture 5.2 in this video we will give a short recap on
probability theory. And the reason for that is that I thought that
before we go on with the Bayes Filter and the Kalman Filter that it doesn't hurt to briefly
review the basics of probability theory, just to make sure that we have all the same background.
I actually hope that most of the concepts present in this video will already be familiar
to you, but if not then I would really urge you to look at a preliminary course on probability
theory before you continue with this course.
So the basic idea behind probability theory is that we have a random experiment that can
produce a number of possible outcomes. For example, we can role a dice, and then this
dice can produce different outcomes from 1 to 6 for example. And then, this space of
possible outcomes is called the sample space. And now, we can talk about events that can
occur. And in principle an event is an element of the power set of this sample space. So
one possible event A could be that we are interested in even numbers, so A would correspond
to the subset of 2, 4 and 6. And now we can talk about the probability of this event to
happen. This would be denoted by P(A). And in this particular example the probability of this proposition would be 0.5.
In general there are 3 axioms behind modern probability theory. The probability of such
an event is always a number between 0 and 1. And there is the set of all possible
outcomes, which is called omega. And the probability of omega is always 1. Which is an event that
always happens no matter what the outcome is of our random experiment.
And the probability on the other hand of the empty set of outcomes of course never occurs.
So the probability of the empty set is 0.
And there is a third axiom that says: if you're interested in the probability of the combination of two events,
then this equals the probability of event one P(A) plus the probability of event B minus the intersection between these two events.
So it might happen that event A and B have some outcomes in common and if we wouldn't subtract
the probability of this intersection, then we would count certain outcomes twice.
Now, the next concept is the so called random variable. We start with discrete random variables,
which is just denoted by a capital letter say X for example. And a discrete random variable
can take only accountable number of values, x_1 to x_n for example.
And then the notation P(X = x_i) refers to the probability that this random variable
X actually takes a particular value x_i. And then, this function P is called the probability mass function.
Now, in most cases actually we are dealing with continuous random variables; for example,
because we want to model the position of a robot in 2D or in 3D.
And then X would be a continuous random variable. And then, the problem is that we can't really
specify anymore the probability that X takes a particular value, say that the robot is exactly
at X equals 3. You know the probability for any element of
this set would go to 0 actually. So instead of stating the absolute probability of a certain
event we are now talking about the density function,
which is denoted by a lower case letter p. And the relation between this density and
the probability is that when we are looking at an interval in this continuous space for
example if x is between a and b, then the probability is equal to the integral over
the density of x in this interval.
And to understand or to look at this graphically imagine now the robot is driving along a corridor
and it has a certain likelihood. It sees a door knob and so it inferred a probability
distribution form which it knows that it stands in front of door.
And then, this probability density function could look as follows: there are certain peaks
in front of doors and then depending on the sensor model and the motion model as you will
see later some of these peaks might be stronger than others.
The next property of proper probability distribution is that it always sums to 1. The reason for
that is that if we look at all possible values that x can take, then we are actually looking
at the full set omega and the probability of omega is 1.
And so if we marginalize out this variable we have to obtain 1.
The same holds also for the continuous case but then we need to integrate over the domain of x.
The next concept is the so called joint probability. This reverse to the case where we have
2 random variables or more, say X and Y for example that could encode the 2D position
of a robot in x and y direction. And then, we can write this as P(X = x and Y = y )
And just as a shortened we often then just write a P(x,y) to keep the notation intuitive
and understandable. Of course, we always make sure then that the symbol that we use for the values
is the same as the symbol for the random variables, so X equals x and then Y equals y in this case.
So if X and Y are independent variables, then they don't influence each other. They describe
different properties of the world and then this joint probability of X and Y actually
corresponds to the individual probabilities of x times the probability y.
And now the notion P(x|y) is called conditional probability, which says
that if we already know that y takes a particular value, then how does this influence our probability distribution over x.
For example, if we throw a dice and this dice can take values between 1 and 6, and a normal
dice you know gives you a uniform distribution. And now, say random variable X encodes the value that
we are getting from the dice. And now, we could define a second variable Y that is just binary
and tells us whether the number that we've thrown is even or uneven.
And now if we would know that the number that we have thrown is even for example, then the
probability distribution over X is of course not uniform anymore, but the likelihood of
even number then is 1/3 and the probability of uneven numbers is 0, given that we know that
the number has to be even.
And then, mathematically speaking this corresponds to the following equation,
so the conditional probability P(x|y)P(y) equals exactly the joint probability P(x,y) of x and y.
And now, if X and Y are independent again, completely independent, so they don't say anything about
each other. Then the conditional probability of P(x|y) just equals the probability
of x, P(x). Because knowledge of Y does not influence the probability distribution of X.
So if we introduce now a third random variable Z we can also talk about the conditional
independence between to variables. So for example, if we are looking at the probability
distribution over P(x,y|z) then this can corresponds to the product of the conditional probability of P(x|z)P(y|z).
Note that this does not imply that X and Y are independent but they are in this case
independent as long as we know the value of Z.
And this notation now is actually equivalent to the following two things,
so it says that: if the knowledge of Y does not change our probability distribution over
X and vice versa, then the two variables X and Y are conditional independent given Z.
The next concept is called marginalization, if we are looking at a joint probability distribution
P(x,y) for example, and we marginalize out Y, which means  that we are no longer interested in the value of Y.
And we sum up over all possible values that Y can take, then we obtain the probability distribution just over X.
So in this way we can generate the marginalized distribution over X from the joint distribution over X and Y.
And again, you have two cases because we could have a discrete random variable for which
we would specify the probability mass function or we could have a continuous variable for
which we would have to specify the probability density function.
And just to illustrate this with an example, imagine that we have the following joint probability
distribution between to variables X and Y.
And X can take different values x_1 to x_4 and Y can take different values from y_1 to y_4.
And then we have a certain joint probability table that we can specify using these 16 different values
And now we can marginalize over X for example, to just obtain the probability of Y independent
of X, and then, we obtain the row on the right side or we could marginalize out the y's, and
then, sum over the probabilities row wise and obtain the last row.
So the next important concept is the expected value of a random variable. This means if
we roll a dice and we would like to know what is the average value that we are getting out
of it? How many steps can we move forward with our figure in a board game for example?
Then we would compute the weighted average of all values that a random variable can take
on. So for example, if this random variable can take values of x_i, then we would multiply
this value with the probability that the random variable actually takes for this value
and this actually gives us then the expected value of this random variable.
In the continuous case you would have to take the integral over the whole range of values
that this random varibale can take on.
And it is important to note here that the expectation is actually a linear operator,
so if we are looking at an expression E[a X + b] then we can pull
out the factor and the offset from the expectation operator and directly compute the expectation
of X and then do our computations afterwards.
The second important concept is the covariance of a random variable.
And it just measures the squared expected deviation from the mean. So it says how large our spread is.
In the 1 dimensional case this is also the variance, if we have a multivariate problem
with multiple random variables then it is the covariance matrix that you've might have seen before.
Now, if we need to estimate this mean or the covariance from observations that we are getting
from our sensors for example. Imagine that we have a GPS sensor and that continuously gives
us 3D position estimates of our quadrotor, then we would get a sequence of position observations x_1 to x_n
from a 3 dimensional space. And then, we would like to know what our average position is. We could just sum over all of these observations
and divide by the number of observations that we got and this then called the sample mean.
And at the same time we you could compute the sample covariance just by removing the mean from
all our observations taking the dot product with the transposed vector and normalizing
it by 1 over (n-1). And then, this gives us the spread over the GPS signal
for example, which typically is around 3 to 5 meters.
So this was a quick recap on probability theory we have introduced random variables,
we've looked at joint and conditional probabilities. We've looked at marginalization,
and we looked at the sample mean and the sample covariance, and how to compute that from data.
And now this forms a very good basis for the next video where we will introduce Bayes law
and give some examples.